<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter from General Ludlow to Dr. Hollingworth ... defending his former letter to Sir E.S. [i.e. Edward Seymour] which compared the tyranny of the first four years of King Charles the Martyr, with the tyranny of the four years of the late abdicated king, and vindicating the Parliament which began in Novemb. 1640 : occasioned by the lies and scandals of many bad men of this age.</title>
            <author>Ludlow, Edmund, fl. 1691-1692.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 218 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 54 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48058</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1469</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13691</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13137388</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13137388</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97943</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48058)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97943)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 426:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter from General Ludlow to Dr. Hollingworth ... defending his former letter to Sir E.S. [i.e. Edward Seymour] which compared the tyranny of the first four years of King Charles the Martyr, with the tyranny of the four years of the late abdicated king, and vindicating the Parliament which began in Novemb. 1640 : occasioned by the lies and scandals of many bad men of this age.</title>
                  <author>Ludlow, Edmund, fl. 1691-1692.</author>
                  <author>Hollingworth, Richard, 1639?-1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>viii, 72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Amsterdam :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Pages 66-67 have print faded, and p. 72 is stained in filmed copy. Pages 50-end photographed from Cambridge University Library copy and inserted at the end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ludlow, Edmund, fl. 1691-1692. --  Letter from Major General Ludlow to Sir E.S.</term>
               <term>Seymour, Edward, --  Sir, 1633-1708.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1625-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97943:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97943:1"/>
            <p>A LETTER FROM General Ludlow TO Dr. Hollingworth, Their Majeſties Chaplain AT St. <hi>Botolph-Aldgate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Defending his former Letter to Sir <hi>E. S.</hi> which compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Tyranny of the firſt Four Years of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Martyr, with the Tyranny of the Four Years of the late Abdicated King.</p>
            <p>And vindicating the Parliament which began in <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1640. Occaſioned by the Lies and Scandals of many bad Men of this Age.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Veritas emerget Victrix.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I acknowledg it were better if we could have <hi>Job</hi>'s Wiſh, That this Day ſhould periſh, that Darkneſs and the Shadow of Death ſhould cover it, that it ſhould not ſee the dawning of the Day, nor ſhould the Light ſhine upon it: It were better to ſtrike it out of our Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendar, and to make our <hi>January</hi> determine at the 29th, and add theſe remaining Days to <hi>February. Dr.</hi> Burnet, <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Salisbury, <hi>his Sermon at St.</hi> Laurence <hi>Church,</hi> London, <hi>January</hi> 30, 1680.</p>
            <p>AMSTERDAM, Printed <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1692.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:97943:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="iii" facs="tcp:97943:2"/>
            <head>To all ſincere Lovers of OLD ENGLAND, Inhabiting in the Pariſh of St. <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolph-Aldgate,</hi> London.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Countrymen;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>'TWas a great Man's Saying, That <hi>EVERY CLER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GY-MAN is not qualified to ſuſtain the Dignity of the Church's Jeſter.</hi> That therefore before Men be admitted to ſo important an Employment, it were fit that they underwent a ſevere Examination; and that it might appear,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Whether they have ANY SENSE;</hi> for without that how can they pretend, and yet they do, to be Ingenuous? Then, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they have ANY MODESTY,</hi> for without that they can only be <hi>SCURRILOUS</hi> and <hi>IMPUDENT?</hi> Next, <hi>Whether ANY TRUTH,</hi> for <hi>true Jeſts</hi> are thoſe that do the greateſt Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution? And, <hi>laſtly,</hi> 'Twere not amiſs that they gave ſome Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count too of their <hi>CHRISTIANITY;</hi> For the World has always hitherto been ſo uncivil, as to expect ſomething of that from <hi>the CLERGY,</hi> in the Deſign and Stile even of their lighteſt and moſt <hi>uncanonical Writings.</hi> But,</p>
            <p>With very little regard to theſe, <hi>two dull Books</hi> have been lately obtruded upon the World, by one and the ſame <hi>Author,</hi> as I am aſſured; The one, under the Title of <hi>A DEFENCE of King</hi> Charles <hi>the Firſt, OCCASIONED by the Lies and Scandals of many bad Men of this Age, By</hi> RICHARD HOLLING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>WORTH,
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:97943:3"/>D. D. <hi>THEIR MAJESTIES CHAPLAIN, at St.</hi> Botolph-Aldgate. The other called, <hi>A VINDICATION of their Majeſties Wiſdom, in the late nomination of ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Perſons to the vacant Arch-Biſhopricks and Biſhopricks, OCCASIONED by the ſcandalous Reflections of unreaſonable Men, By A MINISTER of</hi> London. Now,</p>
            <p>This <hi>Author</hi> having ſought theſe <hi>OCCASIONS</hi> to be trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and declaring a doughty Reſolution that he will be further ſo, rather than loſe the Lechery of his Scribling, and the vain Glory of his Pedantry, 'tis fit that ſuch an <hi>arrogant Levite,</hi> who ſeats himſelf in<note n="*" place="margin">Epiſtle De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatory to the Defence.</note> 
               <hi>a Juncto</hi> with their <hi>Majeſties,</hi> to conſult wiſely how <hi>to preſerve them from a People who mean them no Harm,</hi> ſhould be a little animadverted upon; which task I undertook, after I found that Perſons of better Ability, would not trouble themſelves with ſuch contemptible Pamphlets.</p>
            <p>I had prepared, and did purpoſe to have ſent with this, ſome <hi>Remarks</hi> upon the pretended <hi>Vindication of their Majeſties Wiſdom;</hi> but finding that my Notes upon the <hi>Doctor's Defence</hi> of <hi>King</hi> Charles <hi>the Firſt,</hi> are ſwell'd beyond the Bulk which I intended, I have laid aſide thoſe <hi>Remarks,</hi> till I have occaſion to write again to this mighty <hi>Vindicator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When I wrote to <hi>Sir E. S.</hi> this time twelve-Month, I only diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours'd of the <hi>King's firſt Four Years;</hi> and did intend, if ever I wrote further upon that Subject, to have proceeded regularly with the ſucceding Years of his <hi>Tyranny;</hi> but having engaged my ſelf to follow the <hi>Doctor</hi> in his Ramblings, I could not at preſent purſue my Intention, but may hereafter do it.</p>
            <p>Having reſolved to make this Addreſs to you, <hi>my honoured Countrymen,</hi> I will take the liberty to obſerve two or three things, which are omitted in my Letter to the <hi>Doctor;</hi> He ſaith, <hi>pag. 3.</hi> That <hi>great Numbers call this King a Tyrant and A PAPIST too, though he ſo ſtronuouſly aſſerted and pleaded the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Cauſe, as it is profeſſed by THE CHURCH OF</hi> ENG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND, [That means <hi>THEIR PARTY.</hi>]</p>
            <p>Now, that <hi>he highly favoured POPERY,</hi> is moſt evident; and to what I have already offered to evince the Truth of that Charge, I do add theſe Inſtances.</p>
            <p>I have told the <hi>Aldgate-Chaplain,</hi> that this <hi>King,</hi> by a Letter to the <hi>Pope,</hi> ſaluted <hi>Antichriſt</hi> with the Title of <hi>Moſt holy Father.</hi> That <hi>Letter</hi> from the beginning to the end ſavours of <hi>Popery.</hi> For,
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:97943:3"/>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>He profeſſes therein, that nothing could affect him ſo much, as AN ALLIANCE with a Prince that had the ſame apprehenſions of THE TRUE RELIGION with himſelf,</hi> [That was the KING of <hi>SPAIN,</hi> A NOTABLE PROTE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STANT.]</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>He calls Popery THE CATHOLICK, APOSTOLICK, Roman RELIGION, all other NOVELTY and FACTION.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>He proteſts he did not eſteem it a Matter of greater Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, to be deſcended from great Princes, than to imitate them in the Zeal of their Piety, who had often expoſed their Eſtate and LIVES for THE EXALTATION OF THE HOLY CROSS.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>He ſolemnly engaged to the Pope, to ſpare nothing in the World, and to ſuffer all manner of Diſcommodities, even TO THE HAZARDING OF ESTATE AND LIFE, for to ſettle a thing ſo pleaſing to God, as UNITY WITH</hi> ROME.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Behold, what <hi>a good Sign</hi> of PROTESTANTISM here hangs <hi>at the King's Door.</hi> Moreover, when the <hi>Pope's Nuncio</hi> delivered a Letter to him from the <hi>Pope,</hi> wherein PROTESTANTS <hi>are called</hi> MONSTERS <hi>of</hi> HERESIES, and the <hi>King</hi> was invited <hi>to return the Poſſeſſion of theſe moſt noble Iſles to the</hi> PRINCE OF THE APOSTLES. He expreſſed himſelf in theſe words; <hi>I KISS HIS HOLINESS FEET for the Favour and Honour he doth me; ſo much the more eſteemed, by how much the leſs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved of me HITHERTO. And HIS HOLINES SHALL SEE WHAT I DO HEREAFTER. So that his Holineſs ſhall not repent him of what he hath done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He was as good as his word here paſſed to the <hi>Pope,</hi> as all the World afterwards ſaw. Tho that moſt horrid <hi>IRISH REBELLION</hi> broke out the <hi>23d</hi> of <hi>October, 1641.</hi> the <hi>Lords and Commons,</hi> who complained that <hi>it was framed and cheriſh'd in</hi> England, <hi>could not obtain a Proclamation to declare thoſe blcody Miſcreants, Traitors, till</hi> January <hi>enſuing;</hi> and then the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Warrant went to the <hi>King's Printer</hi> from his <hi>Secretary of State.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">IT is his Majeſty's Pleaſure, that you forthwith print in very good Paper, and ſend unto me for his Majeſty's Service, forty Copies of the Proclamation incloſed; leaving convenient ſpace for his Majeſty to ſign above, and to affix
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:97943:4"/>the Privy Signet underneath: And HIS MAJESTY'S EXPRESS COMMAND IS, THAT YOU PRINT NOT ABOVE THE SAID NUMBER OF FORTY COPIES, and forbear to make any further Publication of them, till his Pleaſure be further ſignified; for which this ſhall be your Warrant.</q>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Whitehall,</hi> 
                        <date>January 2, 164<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Edw. Nicholas.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>See here what ſpecial care was taken, that a few only ſhould come to the knowledg of this <hi>Proclamation,</hi> which was at that time more obſervable, by the late contrary Practice againſt the <hi>Scots,</hi> who were in a very quick and ſharp manner proclaimed, and thoſe <hi>Proclamations</hi> Forthwith diſperſed with all imaginable diligence throughout the whole Kingdom, and <hi>ordered to be read in all Churches,</hi> accompanied with <hi>Publick Prayers and Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crations.</hi> But his Averſion to the proclaiming and proceeding againſt the <hi>Iriſh Rebels,</hi> is not to be much admired at; for they called themſelves <hi>THE QUEEN'S ARMY,</hi> and declared that they roſe to maintain the <hi>KING'S PREROGATIVE,</hi> and the <hi>QUEEN'S RELIGION</hi> againſt the <hi>PARLIAMENT:</hi> And he had no ſooner yielded to iſſue this <hi>Proclamation,</hi> than (to obſtruct the quelling theſe <hi>Rebels,</hi> and give them time to increaſe and ſtrengthen themſelves) the <hi>King</hi> withdrew from the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and began <hi>Domeſtick Diſſentions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having given theſe ſlight Touches at the <hi>King's favouring Popery,</hi> and at his <hi>Acceſſion</hi> to the <hi>Iriſh Rebellion;</hi> I do now leave it to you to make a Judgment, whether he were ſo <hi>STRENU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OUS AN ASSERTER OF THE PROTESTANT CAUSE,</hi> as your <hi>DOCTOR</hi> inſituates; and I care not if once for all, I do acknowledg, that <hi>THE CLERGY may with good pretence to Reaſon ſay, that HE DIED THEIR MARTYR; for his being wrought upon by JESUITICAL COUNSELS, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a Liturgy upon the Scots, who had no ſuch thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, did very much contribute to the bringing him to the FATAL BLOCK.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall now for my own Vindication, entreat you do remember, that <hi>I never call this King A PAPIST,</hi> and I have ever eſteem'd it a piece of Artifice in <hi>OUR PRIESTS,</hi> to amuſe the People
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:97943:4"/>with the Suggeſtion, that he is falſly charged with <hi>Popery,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to Induct them to disbelieve or forget his Crime, which was moſt viſible to all Men, <hi>the Violation of the Laws and Liberties of the Kingdom;</hi> I have therefore choſen to decline the Diſpute about <hi>his Religion;</hi> and am ſire 'twill be found that I have not unjuſtly tax'd him with <hi>the Crimes of his Miſgovernment,</hi> which did ſo plainly and inexcuſably appear to all. And why ſhould we not think that ſuch things were cauſe enough to be ſtood upon by the <hi>Parliament</hi> and to juſtify <hi>their Quarrel</hi> before <hi>God?</hi> As if <hi>the Almighty</hi> did not abhor <hi>INJUSTICE, OP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PRESSION AND TYRANNY,</hi> unleſs <hi>Profeſſion of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> were alſo <hi>depraved</hi> Nay, be abhori it more in that place where the pureſt of Profeſſion is.</p>
            <p>That <hi>this King intended to bow or break us, to perſwade or force us to Slavery,</hi> is ſo clear by the whole courſe of his Reign, that 'tis amazing that Men (even of the higheſt ſtamp of <hi>TORYISM</hi>) ſhould have Front enough to deny it. The <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitical Court-Prieſts</hi> did then preach, <hi>That we were bound to obey whatſoever the King commanded, without queſtioning the Lawfulneſs.</hi> And why did they vent ſuch ſtuff, but to flutter and pleaſe the <hi>King?</hi> And how could he be delighted with it, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he thought it true and agreeable to his Deſigns? And that he honoured thoſe <hi>falſe Teachers,</hi> above the <hi>Prophets of the Lord,</hi> is evin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> both by his <hi>advancing</hi> them, and ſuffering thoſe <hi>Sons of Chenaariah</hi> to ſmite thoſe <hi>Michaiahs,</hi> and to puſh them with Horus of Iron that they might conſume them.</p>
            <p>The great Philoſopher <hi>Themiſtius,</hi> did ſay with equal Truth and Wit, that <hi>Flattering Clergy-men did not worſhip God, but the Imperial Purple;</hi> and 'tis a ſad Truth, that in our day, they have been <hi>SETTING THE PEOPLE ON MADDING;</hi> and the <hi>low Dejection</hi> and <hi>baſeneſs of Mind</hi> in too many of this Generation, is to be aſcribed to their <hi>PULPIT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STUFF,</hi> which has been <hi>the Doctrine and perpetual Infuſion of Servility and Wretchedneſs</hi> to their Hearers.</p>
            <p>The Caſe being thus, it becomes neceſſary to expoſe ſuch Men as theſe; for 'tis intolerable that <hi>your Doctor</hi> in his dull way of Calumniating, ſhould (as he doth) cenſure, reproach, and blacken the Actions and Memories of ſo many excellent Perſons, both <hi>Lords and Gentlemen,</hi> and alſo very learned and pious Divines. And on the other hand, <hi>a Reputation</hi> is to be won for <hi>King
<pb n="viii" facs="tcp:97943:5"/>Charles</hi> the Firſt, <hi>of Wiſdom, by Wilfulneſs and ſubtile Shifts; of Goodneſs, by multiplying Evil; of Piety, by endeavouring to root out true Religion;</hi> I have therefore in the enſuing Letter, taken ſome little pains in <hi>comparing his fair-ſpoken Words, with his far-differing Deeds;</hi> for 'tis most certain, that <hi>the World ever looks more at real Actions than verbal Proteſtations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am ſenſible, <hi>my good Friends,</hi> that I now write to Men endued with Reaſon; let not the <hi>Gooſe quill</hi> of <hi>a Chaplain at Aldgate</hi> make you all <hi>Ganders,</hi> and a ſound of Words bewitch you; his <hi>Tracts</hi> which I have mentioned look like <hi>pieces of Flattery</hi> compiled by <hi>A HUNGRY LEVITE,</hi> gaping after a <hi>Deanary,</hi> or <hi>Chaplainſhip at Whitehall.</hi> He, by his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Colours, ſets off a deformed Cauſe to gull you. Have you read this <hi>King</hi> in his <hi>Actions,</hi> and ſhall <hi>experimental Knowledge</hi> be confuted by this <hi>Doctor</hi>'s bare <hi>Aſſertions?</hi> Should we eſteem Truth by Words, how many <hi>Romances</hi> would be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as Authentick as our <hi>Bibles? 'Tis Truth only which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quers the wiſe;</hi> to be captivated by ought elſe, argues Folly.</p>
            <p>My laſt Requeſt to you is, that I may be rightly underſtood; I proteſt that no intent in trample on the Dead, or diſhonour his Duſt, but a Deſire to vindicate the Liberties of my Country, moved me to this undertaking; this unhappy <hi>King</hi>'s Miſcarriages and Crimes, ſhould have lain buried in Oblivion, if <hi>ECCLESI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ASTICAL MAKE-BATES</hi> did not rake all up again into freſh Remembrance whether we will or no. I am not conſcious to my ſelf, that by what I have wrote, I have loaded his Memory with other than <hi>Matter of Fact and Truth,</hi> which will be too hard for the greateſt <hi>Doctor</hi> of them all. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute> 
               <signed>Your affectionate Country-man and Servant, <hi>Edmund Ludlow.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97943:5"/>
            <head>A LETTER <hi>from General</hi> LUDLOW, <hi>to Dr.</hi> HOLLINGWORTH, <hi>their Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Chaplain,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>MIne to Sir E. S. <hi>(moſt Eximious Sir)</hi> bore date upon your laſt MADDING DAY: Another being now come, I eſteem my ſelf obliged to juſtify what I aſſerted in my laſt Year's Letter: To the end that I may keep my Country-men, and in particular thoſe of your Coat, right in their Senſes; and inculcate into the Men of this Generation, a due abhorrence of Tyranny, and a juſt Venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for Engliſh Parliaments. Having come to this Reſolution, and that upon the reading <hi>your Jewel of a Book,</hi> which you ſtile, <hi>A Defence of King</hi> Charles <hi>the Firſt, (occaſioned by the Lies and Scandals of many bad Men of this Age)</hi> which came to me as a New-Year's Gift, from an endeared Friend in <hi>London;</hi> I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe you will readily allow me to pretend to a title to an Acquaintance and Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with you: For though in the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of my laſt to Sir <hi>E. S. I gave a Challenge to DOCTOR</hi> P. (who occaſion'd that) <hi>to</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Tho I neither have, nor do think that I ever can be convicted of one Falſhood in my former Letter, (or in this which I am writing) yet I will confeſs one Error committed this time twelve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>month; 'twas this, I following a very faithful Hiſtorian, whoſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by an unhappy omiſſion of one Letter, ran him and me by conſequence into a great miſtake; and I, relying upon that Print, ſaid, That the noble Lord <hi>Conway</hi> had avowed in Parliament, that he <hi>never</hi> hated Popery; whereas his words in truth were, that he <hi>ever</hi> hated it.</note> 
               <hi>convict me of Falſhood in any one Particular there charged upon his</hi> incomparable Prince; yet I have not had one Word, either from him or Sir <hi>E. S.</hi> Therefore, in good Manners, I diſmiſs them from further trouble, as I might have done my ſelf, had you not fallen foul upon me: But ſeeing you muſt be ſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and have taken up the Cudgels, we muſt come to A TRIAL OF SKILL.</p>
            <p>To begin;</p>
            <p>You appear very warm at firſt, and therefore not ſo civil as a Man might hope you would be found, who profeſs ſo much Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97943:6"/>and Temper, as you ſometimes do. You ſay, <hi>'Tis A LEWD PAMPHLET, which goes under the Name of</hi> LUD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LOW. Why <hi>Lewd, dear Sir?</hi> 'Tis a received Opinion amongſt your Acquaintance at <hi>Billingsgate,</hi> that <hi>to call a Woman, Whore, and ſay you will prove her ſo,</hi> will bear an Action, otherwiſe not: I ſhall not therefore proſecute you for that, becauſe 'tis only your ſay ſo; you neither undertake nor offer one word to prove it: And indeed, ſhould I implead you upon it, I perceive you have expreſs'd your ſelf with that Caution, that I ſhould be Non-ſuited; For you add, that <hi>it goes under the Name of</hi> Lud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; <hi>by conſequence it may not be his.</hi> Why thus unmerciful, <hi>Doctor?</hi> You will not allow me to be Author of my own Book or Letter; and yet you declare it a barbarous Act in a certain <hi>Eſſex Doctor,</hi> (his Name I underſtand is <hi>Walker</hi>) and <hi>his Vertues and Piety will, I doubt not, find a room in future Annals and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords,</hi> ('tis your own delicate Expreſſion) <hi>when yours will be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten.</hi> I ſay, you allow him not to deny that your <hi>Martyr</hi> was the Author of <hi>Eicon Baſilice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I meet, <hi>Sir,</hi> in the next place, with a taſte of your <hi>healing Spirit.</hi> You treat me, and thoſe who believe the Truth, that you are no way able to gain-ſay, in a highly obliging, and moſt endearing manner,<note place="margin">Pag. 2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>A vile Brood, a factious Crew,</hi>  We are, ſay you: I may not now betray my own Innocence ſo far, as to ſuffer any thing of this to paſs upon me without a Vindication. I have aſſerted, that <hi>your SAINT was a NOTORIO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S TY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RANT,</hi> and for ought you tell me to the contrary, very fairly proved it, and that by abundance of Inſtances. Am I Unjuſt therein? Why then do not you refute me? Am I in the Right? Why then will you ſet your ſelf to out-face the Truth? That you do ſo, I ſhall demonſtrate, after I have minded you, out of <hi>my former Letter,</hi> what things you are either to <hi>falſify or juſtify</hi> (for you muſt know, that Railing, no more than Perſecution, can ever make a Convert) when you ſcrible again, if you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to convince any Man of an Error, who believes that <hi>King Charles</hi> the Firſt was a <hi>Tyrant:</hi> And I muſt tell you, that I am induced to make the Repetition which enſues, becauſe I cannot perceive, by the reading your Tract, that you have look'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond my <hi>Title Page;</hi> for there you find the only thing you men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mine, and that with Indignation; THE VILE BROOD, you ſay, call this Day, THE MADDING-DAY.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97943:6"/>I am moſt ſure that <hi>you do not anſwer,</hi> nor ſo much as caſt a look towards <hi>any one Paragraph or Sentence of my Letter.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</p>
            <p>This informs you, that (amongſt many others) the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Acts of Tyranny,</hi> are there enumerated, and placed to your <hi>Martyr</hi>'s Account. I ſhall <hi>(to oblige you)</hi> begin with the <hi>Church,</hi> for I know 'twill pleaſe you to ſee that precede the <hi>State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <q rend="margQuotes">THE KING we are talking of, in a Letter which he wrote to the <hi>Pope,</hi> ſaluted <hi>Antichriſt</hi> with the Title of <hi>Sanctiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſime Pater, Moſt holy Father;</hi> HE procured the <hi>Pope's Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> for his <hi>Marriage, which was ſolemnized according to the</hi> Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies <hi>of the</hi> Romiſh Church. HE agreed to <hi>Articles</hi> upon his <hi>Marriage, that</hi> Papiſts <hi>ſhould be no more moleſted for their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi> HE built <hi>Somerſet-Houſe Chappel,</hi> with conveniency for <hi>Friars; and permitted them to walk abroad in their Habits.</hi> HE <hi>aſſumed to himſelf a Power to diſpenſe with the Laws,</hi> in favour of Popery; particularly the 21th and 27th of <hi>Queen Elizabeth,</hi> by granting Pardons to <hi>Jeſuits and Papiſts,</hi> which paſſed by <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Warrant. HE inhibited and reſtrained both</hi> Eccleſiaſtical and Temporal Officers <hi>to intermeddle with Papiſts;</hi> which amoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to a Toleration. <hi>Popiſh Juriſdiction</hi> was exerciſed and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowed in <hi>Ireland; Monaſteries</hi> and <hi>Nunneries</hi> were erected there, and filled with Men and Women of ſeveral Orders. HE made above an hundred <hi>Popiſh Lords</hi> and <hi>Gentlemen, Lot as Lieutenants, Deputy Lieutenants, Juſtices of the Peace,</hi> &amp;c. And his LORD TREASURER <hi>(Weſton) died a Papiſt. Are theſe,</hi> my good Doctor, <hi>any of the VERT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ES and GRACES which King</hi> William <hi>and Queen</hi> Mary <hi>(as you tell them in your Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) do daily imitate?</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. (To paſs on to the State of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> in his Reign: <hi>Well might Men cry in that day, The Church! O THE CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH!</hi>) <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>This King's Biſhops,</hi> generally ſpeaking, were unſound in their Principles; they <hi>laid new Paintings on the Face of the old</hi> Whore <hi>of</hi> Babylon <hi>to make her ſhew lovely:</hi> They countenanced and cheriſhed <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and depreſſed <hi>Orthodox Preachers,</hi> how conformable ſoever; in particular <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> Land <hi>(whom you Doctor will have to be a tolerably good Man)</hi> allowed Books which favoured <hi>Popery,</hi> but denied to licenſe Books that were written againſt it.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:97943:7"/>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>This King's CHAPLAINS endeavoured to reconcile</hi> England <hi>to</hi> Rome, <hi>and ſcoffed at Preaching, Bibles, and all ſhew of Religion. MO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NTAG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E,</hi> one of his <hi>Chaplains,</hi> being proſecuted in <hi>Parliament</hi> for Crimes of this nature, <hi>your Martyr</hi> was incenſed thereat, granted him a Pardon, and <hi>made him Biſhop of</hi> Chiche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</q> [<hi>And now Doctor,</hi> pray tell me, <hi>have our moſt Excellent</hi> King and Queen <hi>made any ſuch Biſhops, or Chaplains as theſe?</hi>]</p>
            <p n="3">
               <q rend="margQuotes">3. THIS KING in his firſt Year, <hi>lent eight SHIPS (which he equipp'd with Monies given for the Relief of his diſtreſſed Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant</hi> Siſter, <hi>the</hi> Electreſs Palatine, <hi>and the oppreſſed</hi> Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants <hi>of the</hi> Palatinate) TO THE FRENCH KING, to fight againſt the diſtreſſed Proteſtants of <hi>Rochel:</hi> Theſe Ships were employ'd againſt the <hi>Rochellers;</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> boaſted, that <hi>they mowed the</hi> Hereticks <hi>down like Graſs.</hi>
               </q> [Pray Sir, <hi>your Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in the caſe; Can you think their preſent Majeſties will ever imitate their ROYAL GRANDFATHER in this Point?</hi>]</p>
            <p n="4">
               <q rend="margQuotes">4. <hi>King</hi> Charles <hi>the Firſt</hi> in the very beginning of his Reign, <hi>took our Goods from us againſt our Wills, and our Liberties againſt the Laws;</hi> he raiſed an Army, and required the Countries to furniſh <hi>Coat and Conduct-Mony;</hi> and againſt the known Laws <hi>put ſeveral to Death by</hi> Martial Law; HE levied Money upon the Subject by way of <hi>Loan,</hi> and menaced the City of <hi>London,</hi> that if they would not advance him Money, HE WOULD FRAME HIS COUNSELS AS APPERTAINED TO A KING.</q> [<hi>That ſurely,</hi> dear Doctor, <hi>could intend no other than ſuch a one as</hi> France <hi>is now plagued with;</hi> it may ſignify <hi>King</hi> in that Language, In our plain Engliſh, 'tis <hi>downright Tyrant.</hi>]</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">When it was urged that his requiring SHIP-MONEY <hi>was unprecedented;</hi> His haughty Anſwer was, That <hi>Precedents were not wanting for the Puniſhment of thoſe that diſobey the King's Commands; and that State-Occaſions were not to be guided by ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Precedents.</hi> Thoſe that refuſed to ſubſcribe to the <hi>Loan,</hi> were put out of the <hi>Commiſſions</hi> of the <hi>Lieutenancy</hi> and the <hi>Peace,</hi> and alſo <hi>impriſoned;</hi> and the Refuſers of the meaner Rank were bound to appear, and be enrolled for Souldiers to be ſent for <hi>Denmark;</hi> or were impreſſed to ſerve in the <hi>King's Ships.</hi>
               </q> [<hi>Here now is a ready way not only for the raiſing of Money, but alſo an Army for</hi> Flanders, <hi>and Sailers for our Fleet.</hi> But all your Rhetorick, <hi>Reverend Sir,</hi> will not work upon their <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties</hi> to imitate your <hi>good and great Man</hi> in theſe things neither.]</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:97943:7"/>
            <p n="5">
               <q rend="margQuotes">5. YOUR MARTYR ſuſpended Dr. <hi>ABBOT, Archbiſhop of</hi> Canterbury (<hi>who was a Man that wholly followed the true Intereſt of</hi> England, <hi>and that of the</hi> Reformed Churches <hi>in</hi> Europe, <hi>ſo far, as that in his time the CLERGY was not much envied here in</hi> England, <hi>nor the Government of</hi> Epiſcopacy <hi>much disfavoured by</hi> Proteſtants <hi>beyond the</hi> Seas.) I ſay, HE SUSPENDED this Excellent Perſon, and alſo CONFINED him, becauſe <hi>(to uſe his own words)</hi> HE REFUSED TO MAKE THAT GOOD BY <hi>Divinity</hi> WHICH THE <hi>King</hi> HAD DONE AGAINST THE LAWS. HE alſo thruſt Dr. <hi>WILLIAMS Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Lincoln</hi> from the place of Lord Keeper, and his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and the Council-Table, for appearing in <hi>Parliament</hi> againſt <hi>the Kingdom's great Grievance, the Duke of</hi> Buckingham; and afterwards he impriſoned him in the Tower for ſpeaking againſt the Loan, for refuſing to allow Proceedings againſt Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans, and <hi>propheſying that the Puritans would carry all at laſt.</hi>
               </q> [I doubt, Doctor, that ſhould the King and Queen imitate their Grandfather in theſe Practices, <hi>you would find your ſelf AS IT WERE overwhelm'd with Sorrow, and that ſuch Actions would ſwell your Grief above its uſual Banks, if not ſtir your Indignation.</hi>]</p>
            <p n="6">
               <q rend="margQuotes">6. THE TYRANT, reſolving to ſubvert the Liberties and Eſtates of the Subjects to his Will and Pleaſure, <hi>removed that grave and learned Judg Sir</hi> Randolph Crew, <hi>from the place of</hi> Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>of the</hi> King's Bench, <hi>becauſe he had declared himſelf againſt the</hi> Loan, and would not ſerve his turn in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring that the King might legally impriſon Men, <hi>durante be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neplacito.</hi>
               </q> [<hi>My Life for yours,</hi> Doctor, <hi>their preſent</hi> Majeſties <hi>will never follow this Example of your PATTERN FOR PRINCES.</hi>]</p>
            <p n="7">
               <q rend="margQuotes">7. HE upon the 30th of <hi>JAN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ARY (of all the days in the Year)</hi> 1627, ſent a <hi>Privy-Seal</hi> to the <hi>Treaſury,</hi> for the remitting 30000 <hi>l.</hi> into <hi>Holland</hi> to <hi>Burlemark,</hi> a Merchant, <hi>to be employed for levying Horſe and Men to be brought into</hi> England <hi>to ſupport his</hi> Tyranny.</q> [And can you think their Majeſties will ever write after this Copy?]</p>
            <p n="8">
               <q rend="margQuotes">8. HE had no ſooner paſſed the PETITION OF RIGHT into a Law, than he was found to violate it, <hi>by billeting of Souldiers, and levying the Subſidies of</hi> Tonnage and Poundage, which determined by his Father's Death; and were never pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to any his Anceſtors, but only by ſpecial Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</q>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:97943:8"/>[<hi>And what Opinion have you of King.</hi> William <hi>and Queen</hi> Mary, <hi>in reference as this Point,</hi> my good Doctor?]</p>
            <p n="9">
               <q rend="margQuotes">9. HE kept the Earl of <hi>Briſtol</hi> under Confinement, near two Years, without being charged with any Accuſation, or brought to Trial: And HE committed the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Arundel</hi> to the <hi>Tower</hi> in the time of <hi>Parliament,</hi> without expreſſing any Cauſe of his Commitment, in Violation of the Priviledges of the Peers.</q> [<hi>Ple warrant you,</hi> Sir, <hi>you'l never find their preſent</hi> Majeſties <hi>at this Work.</hi>]</p>
            <p n="10">
               <q rend="margQuotes">10. <hi>HE upheld and ſhelter'd the Grand Enemies of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth.</hi> When the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Buckingham</hi> was proſecuted in <hi>Parliament,</hi> as the principal <hi>Patron and Supporter</hi> of a <hi>Popiſh Faction,</hi> ſet on Foot to the danger of the CHURCH and STATE, THE KING interpoſed to reſcue him: When the <hi>Commons</hi> impeach'd him, and <hi>by one of their Articles charg'd him</hi> (in effect) WITH THE MURDER OF KING <hi>JAMES;</hi> THE KING told the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Lords,</hi> That to aprove <hi>Bucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s Innocence, HE <hi>could be a Witneſs to clear him in every one of the Articles.</hi> HE told the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons, That he would not allow any of his Servants to be queſtioned amongst them,</hi> much leſs ſuch as were near him. That he ſaw they aimed at the <hi>Duke;</hi> but aſſured them, <hi>he had not intermedied, nor done any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Publick, but by his ſpecial Directions.</hi> He added, That he wondred at the FOOLISH IMPUDENCE of any Man, to think that he ſhould be drawn to offer <hi>ſuch a Sacrifice.</hi> HE diſſolved three Parliaments, when they were intent upon the proſecution of the Duke.</q> 
               <hi>[We are ſtill at a loſs, good Doctor, this will not paſs with our King and Queen; we ſhall never hear them ſpeak or act at this rate.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">
               <q rend="margQuotes">11. <hi>HE impriſoned ſeveral Members of the Houſe of</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, (during the Parliament) <hi>for refuſing to anſwer out of</hi> Parliament, <hi>what was ſaid and done in</hi> Parliament. HE impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned others for managing <hi>a Conference</hi> with the <hi>Lords,</hi> upon their impeaching the <hi>Duke.</hi> HE, in the time of Parliament, <hi>ſent Warrants for ſealing up the Studies of other Members;</hi> and he cauſed the impriſoned Members to be ſhifted and toſs'd from <hi>Goal</hi> to <hi>Goal,</hi> to deprive them, by that wicked Artifice, of the Fruit of their <hi>Habeas Corpus;</hi> and of the Benefit of Free-born Subjects for the obtaining their Liberty; thus were they long detained in Priſon. The brave Sir <hi>John E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ios</hi> ended his days
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97943:8"/>in the <hi>Tower, not without ſuſpicion of foul play.</hi>
               </q> [<hi>I am ſure,</hi> Sir, <hi>you will not recommend theſe vertuous Practices to the imitation of their Majeſties.</hi>]</p>
            <p n="12">
               <q rend="margQuotes">12. <hi>HE ſtruck at the very Being of</hi> Parliaments; he ſent a threatning Meſſage to the Commons, that if he had not a time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Supply,</hi> he would betake himſelf to NEW COUNSELS. At another time he ſaid to the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons, REMEM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BER THAT PARLIAMENTS ARE ALTOGETHER IN MY POWER; THEREFORE, as I find the Fruits of them, Good or Evil, THEY ARE TO CONTIN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E, OR NOT TO BE.</hi> HE told the <hi>Parliment,</hi> the 17th of <hi>March</hi> 1627, That <hi>if they ſhould not contribute what the State needed, he muſt uſe OTHER MEANS;</hi> And his <hi>Lord Keeper</hi> added, That if the <hi>King</hi> found the Readineſs of their Supplies, be might the better forbear <hi>the uſe of his Prerogative;</hi> That the King thoſe that way of <hi>Parliament,</hi> not <hi>as the only way,</hi> but <hi>as firteſt;</hi> not <hi>as deſtitute of others,</hi> but <hi>AS MOST AGREE ABLE TO HIS DISPOSITI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
               </q> [<hi>You will readily agree with me,</hi> dear Sir, <hi>that King</hi> Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam <hi>hath not learn'd this way of ſpeaking to Parliaments.</hi>]</p>
            <p>I have now, <hi>Reverend Sir,</hi> briefly run over my former Letter, and thence preſented you with <hi>a Bone to pick,</hi> indeed a dozen, as luck will have it; and I could have doubled the number, but for the preſent I conclude theſe may ſtay your Stomach, this being <hi>a Faſting-Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt now tell you, that I am as much to ſeek as ever, for the <hi>Vertues of the Martyr,</hi> which deſerve their <hi>Majeſties imitation.</hi> But methinks I hear you reply to me, So you will eternally be, if you read ſuch <hi>lewd Pamphlets</hi> as <hi>Ludlow</hi> converſes with; you muſt apply your ſelf to the <hi>impartial, learned and infallibly convincing Works</hi> of the <hi>moſt candid Dr.</hi> Holling worth, if you will be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned in this great Point: He, <hi>good Man,</hi> jogs ſteadily on in the way of Truth, <hi>ſparing no Party,</hi> you may take his Word for it. May I ſo? He's then the Man for my Money; and caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off my <hi>Strumpet</hi> of a <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> I will READ, TRY and JUDG, according as another <hi>Doctor</hi> adviſes the Lewd Folks. And,</p>
            <p>I proceed (Sir) to the Examination of your <hi>Defence of King</hi> Charles <hi>the Firſt.</hi> You tell us, <hi>that in looking into and conſidering his Life, you found your ſelf equally affected with Joy and Grief.</hi> Now I ſhall attempt to aſſwage your Grief, but in doing is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97943:9"/>ſhall abate ſo much of your conceived Joy, that, with the late <hi>Eloquent Recorder,</hi> I doubt I ſhall bring you to <hi>a handful of Grief and a handful of Sorrow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ground your Joy upon your meeting with a Perſon <hi>ſo admirably tempered, ſo greatly condeſcending, ſo ready to comply with whatever was preſented to him for the good of his Subjects, of ſo great Conſtancy to the Religious Perſwaſions of his own Mind, that he would not forſake them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To begin with the laſt; becauſe you will have the <hi>Church</hi> to take place of the State. Are not we made happy at this day by the <hi>Hereditary Stubbornneſs</hi> of your <hi>Martyr's Son?</hi> he was ſo <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant to the Religious Perſwaſions of his own Mind;</hi> that rather than forſake them, he very fairly abdicated the Throne: <hi>He ſacrificed his Crown to FATHER</hi> PETRE'S <hi>IDOLATRY; his Father, to FATHER</hi> LAUD'S <hi>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>PERSTITION.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>HIS TEMPER will be ſeen hereafter: I ſhall therefore in this place only enquire, whether it appeared ſo admirably good as you inſinuate, when he ſtruck the <hi>Noble Earl</hi> of <hi>Denbigh.</hi> A BOX ON THE EAR, for only walking in the Privy Gallery at <hi>Whitehal.</hi> We are anon to examine <hi>his Condeſcention and Compliance for the Good of the People;</hi> and in doing it ſhall evince, how little you underſtand the Hiſtory of his Life, and what reaſon there is to mortify a <hi>Chaplain</hi> of their preſent <hi>Majeſties,</hi> for recommending this KING <hi>as a Pattern to future Princes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come now (Sir) to <hi>your Melancholy Part,</hi> which you thus expreſs;<note place="margin">Pag. 2.</note> 
               <hi>I have been often overwhelmed, AS IT WERE, with Sorrow and a lodding Grief.</hi> That, AS IT WERE, ſecures ſome hope in your caſe, for which there had been no room, had you been in earneſt overwhelm'd. But pray what brings you, <hi>Doctor,</hi> into this unhappy caſe? Why, <hi>this Prince, ſo every ways great and good, is libell'd by every ſawcy Scribler. A factions number of Men never ſpeak of him but as a TYRANT,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 3.</note> 
               <hi>A ROG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E, A RASCAL: They call the Day on which he was murther'd, and which is appointed by the Supream Power of the Nation to be reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly obſerved, THE MADDING DAY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There's no remedy (Sir) but Patience; there will ever be found ſome <hi>ſawcy Scribler</hi> or other upon this Subject, whilſt the World is troubled with any <hi>ſilly Defender</hi> of this TYRANT; as ſuch I ſhall continue to talk of him, and that with Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but I much ſuſpect that you have learn'd the rude Terms
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97943:9"/>of ROGUE AND RASCAL, from your own <hi>factions Crew, (you know whom I mean)</hi> when they are ſpeaking of his preſent <hi>Majeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>(dear Doctor)</hi> as to your MADDING-DAY, allow me to preſent you with the Opinion of a Perſon <hi>tolerably wiſe and thoughtful,</hi> I mean Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> now <hi>Lord Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> in his <hi>Sermon</hi> before the <hi>Aldermen</hi> of <hi>London</hi> (the Lord Mayor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſick, and therefore abſent) at St. <hi>Lawrence Church,</hi> upon the 30th of <hi>January</hi> 1680, he did expreſs himſelf in theſe words; <hi>I acknowledg it were better if we could have</hi> Job<hi>'s Wiſh, That that Day ſhould periſh, that Darkneſs and the ſhadow of Death ſhould cover it, that it ſhould not ſee the dawning of the Day, nor ſhould the Light ſhine upon it: It were better to ſtrike it out of our</hi> Kalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar, <hi>and to make our</hi> January <hi>determine at the</hi> 29th, <hi>and add theſe remaining days to</hi> February.</p>
            <p>In hope (Sir) that I have here offered ſomething to cool your <hi>red-hot Zeal</hi> for the Obſervation of this Day; upon which you, and many of your <hi>high-ſtown Brethren,</hi> have too long ſpouted out moſt fulſome Flattery upon <hi>your Royal Martyr,</hi> and been infuſing Principles of <hi>Slavery</hi> into the free-born People of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi> I now proceed upon your <hi>Defence:</hi> You ſay, that <hi>your Grief ſwells above its uſual Bank, and ſtirs your Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation againſt a VILE BROOD.</hi> Why? in earneſt <hi>Doctor,</hi> 'tis time to look out for Cure; 'tis not above two or three Minutes ſince you appeared only, AS IT WERE, <hi>overwhelm'd with Sorrow:</hi> Now the overflowing of your Grief, and raiſing your Choler, ſpeaks your caſe, AS IT WERE, deſperate; and I doubt you will <hi>run mad</hi> before your next MADDING-DAY: But I have undertaken the drudgery of reading you through, and muſt take what follows, and ſo muſt you.</p>
            <p>You go on telling me, That <hi>from theſe two Paſſions of Grief and Anger, you are reſolved to vindicate this great Prince; and IF POSSIBLE, to ſhame thoſe who do ſhew by what they vent, that they have neither Knowledg, Wiſdom, nor good Manners; nor indeed any thing elſe, that belongs to the Human as well as Chriſtian Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I found (Sir) by your ſtaring and ſoaming at the Mouth, what you would come to, and 'tis now with you as I foretold; Would any Man in his Wits ſet himſelf not only to put a Herd of Wild Beaſts to ſhame, but alſo to teach them Letters and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97943:10"/>Breeding? But <hi>an angry Doctor</hi> thinks himſelf fit for any thing, when at the ſame time I eſteem him capable of nothing; for no Man that falls into a Paſſion can argue well; and you (Sir) have undertaken a much more difficult Task than you are aware of. For I have read in the fore-mentioned Sermon of the <hi>Learned Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> an Expreſſion to this effect; That <hi>it might be expected that he ſhould enlarge on the Vertues, the Piety, the Magnanimity and Conſtancy of Mind, of this your Martyr; but he confeſſed the performing this to be a Task above his ſtrength:</hi> But what will not <hi>an aſpiring Chaplain</hi> eſſay? I have now (Sir) reached to what you reſolve upon.</p>
            <p>You tell me,<note place="margin">Pag. 4.</note> 
               <hi>That you intend only to run through the laſt eight Years of his Reign.</hi> Do you ſo, Sir? here's a Snake in the Graſs, <hi>Doctor,</hi> or elſe, <hi>why do you skip his firſt ſixteen Years?</hi> I wiſh, that inſtead of running through (which argues you in haſte) I do not find you flying over the Years you pitch upon; if you do, I ſhall endeavour to lure you back again; which that I may the more certainly do, I determine to keep pace with, or ſight of you.</p>
            <p>Proceeding, you ſay, that <hi>you are certain, that from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Long Parliament,</hi> Novemb. 4. <hi>to the day of his Death, he did every thing ALMOST that deſerved a better Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception than it met withal; and made ſuch various Offers and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcontions, as would have pleaſed any ſort of Men but thoſe who were reſolved to be Maſters of his whole Crown and Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>'Tis ſomething unhappy, <hi>good Doctor!</hi> when you ſeem to ſpeak with aſſurance, that you dare not adventure to do it without a Reſerve; your ALMOST in this place, abates much of the Glory of this Paragraph: He did every thing ALMOST; he made <hi>Offers and Condeſcentions;</hi> what thoſe were, I ſuppoſe, you intend to inform me by and by; when I ſee them, we will talk about them; and then, ſhould it be found that they were ſuch as were not ſatisfactory to the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> in that great <hi>Parliament,</hi> you will deſerve to be <hi>TOPHAMIZ'D</hi> for ſlandering the Repreſentative Body of the <hi>Engliſh Nation:</hi> and truly I think you merit ſomething beyond that Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for ſaying that <hi>their moſt Excellent Majeſties King</hi> William <hi>and Queen</hi> Mary, <hi>do daily imitate the Vertues and Graces of a King, who y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gree might have committed ſome Miſtakes in his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97943:10"/>in his firſt ſixteen Year's Reign, and yet did every thing</hi> (with an unlucky) <hi>ALMOST to redreſs ſuch things as his Male-Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration had put out of order, SO FAR AS HE CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LD BE SATISFIED THEY WERE O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T OF ORDER:</hi> For to the eternal Honour of their <hi>preſent Majeſties,</hi> and to the unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Comfort of all good <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> we ſee them daily acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſcing in the Wiſdom of their great Council, and redreſſing, not only ALMOST, but ALTOGETHER, the Diſorders and Grievances of two or three unhappy Reigns.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the next place you affirm, That when the Parliament ſat down in</hi> 1640, <hi>the King purpoſed and reſolved to conſent to every thing they could offer, which might be really for the good of his Kingdom:</hi> You are, Sir, too general herein for my Converſation; you talk as tho you had been one of his <hi>Privy-Council,</hi> or at leaſt a <hi>Chaplain</hi> to <hi>Archbiſhop Land.</hi> I cannot ſay what his Purpoſes or Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were, but when we come to Particulars, ſhall endeavour to weigh them by his Actions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Purſuant to what he purpoſed and reſolved,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 5.</note> (ſay you) <hi>he tells them frankly in his firſt Speech, that he was reſolved to put himſelf freely and clearly on the Love and Affection of his ENGLISH S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BJECTS; and withal, promiſes them to concur ſo heartily with them, that all the World may ſee, that his Intentions HAVE EVER BEEN, and ſhall be to make THIS a glorious Kingdom.</hi> Having ſaid this, you are running on, <hi>Doctor,</hi> but with too much ſpeed for me; you inſtantly add, <hi>I think,</hi> &amp;c. Well, ſo you may, and I intend to hear what that is anon; for now, and not till now, you have cut me out Work, and I muſt intreat you to pauſe a little, and hear what I obſerve upon what you but now declared: <hi>He told them he reſolved to put himſelf freely and clearly on the LOVE AND AFFECTION of his ENGLISH S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BJECTS.</hi> Can this be true, <hi>Doctor?</hi> Did he in earneſt ſay ſo? Why, he was born at <hi>Dumferling,</hi> how then can you repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent him abdicating his <hi>Ancient Kingdom,</hi> and renouncing the <hi>Love and Affection</hi> of the <hi>Scotiſh Nation?</hi> Seeing you are ſilent in this matter, I muſt it ſeems take the pains to examine it; and I promiſe to ſupply your Omiſſion with Impartiality, and all imaginable regard to Truth. And in doing it, ſhall ſhew, with what brevity I can, not only the reaſon why <hi>your Martyr did,</hi> at this Juncture, <hi>careſs and cajole an Engliſh Parliament;</hi> but how our Nation became ſo happy as to ſee one aſſembled, when
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97943:11"/>our Fathers had almoſt forgot the Name of a <hi>Parliament.</hi> The Story is this.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Reformation</hi> of <hi>England</hi> had never abrogated, nor ſcarce ſhaken the <hi>Prelatical Dignity</hi> in any <hi>Parliament;</hi> but in <hi>Scotland</hi> it was quite rooted out by Law, that Church having been ever much addicted to the Reformation of <hi>Geneva:</hi> By degrees it was reſtored, by the extraordinary Interpoſition of the Power of <hi>King</hi> James <hi>the firſt,</hi> yet not without many Difficulties, not without great Reluctancy of the <hi>Nobility, Gentry, and moſt of the Miniſters of that Nation.</hi> They ſuffered a great Diminution of their Temporal Liberties by the Introduction of <hi>Epiſcopal Juriſdiction,</hi> the <hi>Biſhops</hi> uſing rigorous Proceedings againſt Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of Quality, by <hi>Fines, Impriſonments,</hi> &amp;c. And the whole ſtructure of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Policy,</hi> ſo long uſed in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and eſtabliſhed by ſo many <hi>Acts of Parliament,</hi> was at one blow thrown down, their <hi>Conſiſtories, Claſſes, and Presbyteries</hi> were held in the nature of <hi>Conventicles,</hi> and all Deciſion of <hi>Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Controverſies</hi> confined to the <hi>Tribunal</hi> of a <hi>Biſhop.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Hollingworth</hi> in his Tract called, <hi>A Vindication of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Wiſdom,</hi> &amp;c. p. 9. ſaith, that <hi>Laud</hi> was <hi>A VERY GOOD MAN, the Book of Sports excepted:</hi> for ought I know he meant this <hi>Scotch Book,</hi> for <hi>it made Sport with a witneſs;</hi> if he did not, I am ſure this deſerved an Exception alſo.
<p>I am ſenſible of the <hi>Doctor</hi>'s In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, that he is addicted to raſh and inconſiderate Railing; therefore, tho I will not humour him, in reciting the Authority which I have for this <hi>black Story</hi> of his <hi>otherways very good Man,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I have in his Works no more than his bare word for what he aſſerts: my good Nature prompts me to adviſe him, not to give me the Lie in this matter, for I know thoſe who have been at <hi>Rome,</hi> and I can produce a moſt reputable Member of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> for what I here charge upon that <hi>very ill Man</hi> Laud. After this friendly Caution, the <hi>Doctor</hi> may deny it if he dares.</p>
               </note> That fierce, cruel, inſolent and Popiſhly-affected <hi>Archbiſhop Laud,</hi> was the main Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this fatal Work: He in the Year 1637, compoſed <hi>a Common-Prayer Book</hi> for <hi>Scotland,</hi> and deſiring, to demonſtrate his great Affection <hi>to the Court of</hi> Rome, ſent it thither to be approved by the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Cardinals;</hi> they returned it with Thanks for his Reſpect to them, but ſent him word, that they thought it not fit for <hi>Scotland.</hi> The GOOD MAN there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, further to ingratiate himſelf with his ELDER BROTHER, alter'd ſome things in it, and made it more harſh and unreaſonable; and then inſtigated the <hi>King</hi> to ſend it to the <hi>Scots,</hi> with an expreſs Command to have it read in their <hi>Churches:</hi> It varied from the <hi>Engliſh Common-Prayer Book,</hi> but <hi>the Alterations were for the worſe,</hi> eſpecially in the <hi>Lord's-Supper;</hi> it was expreſly commanded that the <hi>Altar</hi> (ſo
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97943:11"/>called) ſhould be ſituate to the <hi>Eaſtern Wall,</hi> together with many Poſtures of the <hi>Miniſter,</hi> whilſt he officiated. And in the <hi>conſecrating Prayer,</hi> thoſe words which in the <hi>Engliſh Liturgy,</hi> are directly againſt <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> were quite left out in that Book, and inſtead of them ſuch other words as in plain ſenſe agreed with the <hi>Roman Maſs-Book,</hi> viz. <hi>Hear us, O moſt merciful Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and of thy Omnipotent Goodneſs grant, ſo to bleſs and ſanctify by thy Word and Spirit, theſe Creatures of Bread and Wine, that they may be to us THE BODY AND BLOOD of thy beloved Son.</hi> In a word, the <hi>Scots</hi> affirmed, that all the material Parts of the <hi>Maſs-Book</hi> were ſeminally in this, and they could not reliſh it, that <hi>Laud</hi> and his <hi>Set of Engliſh Biſhops,</hi> ſhould urge them to a <hi>Liturgy more Popiſh than their own;</hi> and obſerved, that, <hi>for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, they were content to meet</hi> Rome, <hi>rather than</hi> Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</p>
            <p>The Book being read by a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> in the <hi>City</hi> of <hi>Edinburgh;</hi> the People expreſſed great deteſtation thereof; and the <hi>Biſhop</hi> who read it, had probably been ſlain coming out of the Church, had not a Noble-man reſcued him. The <hi>Nobility, Gentry and Miniſters,</hi> petitioned againſt it. The <hi>King</hi> threatned to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute them as <hi>Rebels,</hi> and commanded the <hi>Council</hi> to receive no more <hi>Petitions:</hi> Thereupon ſeveral of the <hi>Nobility,</hi> in the Name of the <hi>Petitioners,</hi> made a <hi>Proteſtation,</hi> that <hi>the Service-Book</hi> was full of <hi>Superſtition</hi> and <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and ought not to be obtruded upon them, without conſent of a <hi>National Synod,</hi> which in ſuch Caſes ſhould judg: That it was unjuſt to deny them Liberty to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe the <hi>Biſhops</hi> being guilty of High Crimes; of which till they were cleared, they did reject them as Judges or Governours of them: They juſtified their own Meetings, and ſubſcribing to <hi>Petitions, as being to defend the Glory of God, the King's Honour,</hi> and <hi>Liberties of the Realm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Scots</hi> concluded to renew the <hi>COVENANT which had been made and ſealed under King</hi> James<hi>'s Hand,</hi> in the Year 1580; afterwards confirmed by all the <hi>Eſtates</hi> of the Kingdom, and Decree of the <hi>National Synod</hi> in 1581; <hi>THIS COVENANT was for the Defence of the P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RITY OF RELIGION, and the King's Perſon and Rights,</hi> againſt the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> This was begun in <hi>February</hi> 1638, and was ſo faſt ſubſcribed throughout the Kingdom, that before the end of <hi>April,</hi> he was ſcarce accounted one of the <hi>Reformed Religion,</hi> that had not ſubſcribed the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:97943:12"/>The <hi>Non Covenanters</hi> were <hi>Papiſts, not exceeding</hi> 600 in number throughout the Kingdom; <hi>Stateſmen</hi> in Office and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour at that time; and <hi>ſome few Proteſtants</hi> who were affected to the <hi>Ceremonies</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and Book of <hi>Common Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>King</hi> ſent the <hi>Marqueſs</hi> of <hi>Hamilton</hi> to deal with the <hi>Scots to renounce their Covenant:</hi> but they affirmed, <hi>It could not be done without manifeſt Perjury</hi> and Profanation of <hi>God's</hi> Name; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted to have the <hi>Service-Book utterly aboliſhed, it being obtruded againſt all Law upon them.</hi> That their Meetings were lawful, and ſuch as they would not forſake, until <hi>the Purity of Religion</hi> and Peace might be fully ſettled, by a free and <hi>National Synod:</hi> And they declared, <hi>THAT THE POWER OF CALLING A SY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOD, IN CASE THE PRINCE BE AN ENEMY TO THE TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TH, OR NEGLIGENT IN PROMOTING THE CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHES GOOD, IS IN THE CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH IT SELF:</hi> And that the State of the Church at that time neceſſitated ſuch a courſe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>King</hi> at length, <hi>fearing leſt the</hi> Covenanters, <hi>if he delayed, would do it themſelves,</hi> called a <hi>National Synod,</hi> to begin at <hi>Glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gow</hi> the 21ſt of <hi>November</hi> 1638; but <hi>within ſeven days it was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved</hi> by the <hi>Marqueſs</hi> of <hi>Hamilton,</hi> in the <hi>King</hi>'s Name, and they commanded to ſit no more. But they proteſted againſt that Diſſolution, and continued the <hi>Synod</hi> when the Marqueſs of <hi>Hamilton</hi> was gone, and depoſed all the <hi>Biſhops;</hi> condemned the <hi>Liturgy, took away the High-Commiſſion Court, and whatſoever had crept into the Church ſince the Year</hi> 1580; <hi>when the</hi> NATIONAL COVENANT <hi>was firſt eſtabliſhed.</hi> When they themſelves broke up the <hi>Synod,</hi> they wrote a Letter of Thanks to the <hi>King,</hi> and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed a <hi>Declaration, Feb.</hi> 4. 1638, directed to all the ſincere and good Chriſtians in <hi>England,</hi> to vindicate their Actions and Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, from thoſe Aſperſions which Enemies might throw upon them.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Declaration</hi> was welcome to the People of <hi>England</hi> in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, and eſpecially to thoſe who ſtood beſt affected to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion, and the Laws and Liberties of their Country. In fine; the <hi>Scots</hi> are declared <hi>Rebels,</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> in Perſon, with an <hi>Engliſh Army,</hi> reſolved to chaſtiſe them. But,</p>
            <p>The generality of the Nation deteſted the <hi>War,</hi> knowing that the <hi>Scots</hi> were innocent, and wronged by the ſame Hand that they were oppreſſed; and they concluded, that the ſame Sword which ſubdued the <hi>Scots,</hi> muſt deſtroy their own Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97943:12"/>Yet glad they ſeem'd to be, that ſuch an Occaſion hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd, which might in reaſon neceſſitate the <hi>King</hi> to call an <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Parliament;</hi> but whilſt he could make any other ſhift, how low and diſhonourable ſoever, he would not endure to think of a Parliament. He borrowed great Sums of Money of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, and required <hi>Loans</hi> of others; and the <hi>CLERGY contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted liberally to this VVar,</hi> which was called <hi>BELL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M EPISCOPALE, THE BISHOPS WAR.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>King</hi> being animated to the War by the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> both of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland;</hi> the laſt perſwading him, <hi>that the COVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NANTERS were in no ſort able to reſist him;</hi> that ſcarce any <hi>Engliſh Army</hi> at all would be needful to fight, but only to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear; and his <hi>MAJESTY would find a Party great enough in</hi> SCOTLAND <hi>to do the VVork.</hi> He thereupon raiſed a gallant Army, which rendezvouzed at <hi>York.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Scots</hi> likewiſe (to render the King unwilling or unable to be a Tyrant) levied a brave Army, which advanced forward under the Command of <hi>General Leſley:</hi> They nevertheleſs <hi>conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued their firſt courſe of Petitioning the</hi> King; which being fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured by almoſt all the Nobility of <hi>England;</hi> at laſt, by the happy Mediation of thoſe Wife and Noble Counſellors, a <hi>PA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIFICATION,</hi> to the great Joy of all good Men, was ſolemnly concluded on, the 18th of <hi>June</hi> 1639, and the <hi>King</hi> granted them <hi>a free National Synod,</hi> to be holden <hi>Auguſt</hi> 6, and a <hi>Parliament</hi> to begin the 20th, to ratify what the <hi>Synod</hi> ſhould decree. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> returned home, praiſing <hi>God;</hi> who, without any effuſion of Blood, had compounded this Difference, and prevented a War ſo wickedly deſign'd. But,</p>
            <p>Shortly after the <hi>King</hi>'s return to <hi>London,</hi> his Heart was again eſtranged from the <hi>Scots,</hi> and thoughts of Peace; and <hi>he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the PACIFICATION to be burnt by the Hands of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Hangman:</hi> An Act than which, nothing could more blemiſh his Reputation, as rendring him not to be believed for any thing: For what Tie would hold him, when the Engagement of his Word, his <hi>Royal VVord,</hi> given in ſight of <hi>God and Man,</hi> could not bind? And having, upon the 18th of <hi>December,</hi> broke up the <hi>Scotch Parliament,</hi> he began to prepare for a <hi>new VVar.</hi> The <hi>Scots</hi> complained, that it was a <hi>Breach of their Liberties,</hi> not heard of before in twenty Ages, <hi>That a</hi> Parliament ſhould <hi>be diſſolved without their Conſent,</hi> whilſt Buſineſs of Moment was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97943:13"/>
               <hi>That whatſoever Kings in other Kingdoms might do, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned not them to enquire; but it was abſolutely againſt their Laws.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They hereupon ſent <hi>four Earls, as their Commiſſioners,</hi> to the <hi>King,</hi> to complain, <hi>that nothing was performed which he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed at the</hi> PACIFICATION; and to intreat redreſs of thoſe Injuries which had been offered them ſince the <hi>Pacification.</hi> But to add to the Grievances of that oppreſſed Nation, <hi>the King</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted two of their Commiſſioners to Priſon.</p>
            <p>In <hi>April</hi> 1640, the <hi>King called a Parliament in</hi> England; not to ſeek Counſel and Advice of them, but to draw Countenance and Supply from them; reſolving, either to make the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment pliant to his Will, and to eſtabliſh Miſchief by a Law, or elſe to break it. The <hi>Scots</hi> wrote a Juſtification of their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings to this Parliament; and adviſed them, <hi>to be wary in vindicating their own Laws and Liberties; this Parliament being procured to no other End, but to arm the King againſt his Scotiſh Subjects, and by that VVar to enſlave both the Nations; That after ſo many Violations and Diſſolutions of Parliaments in</hi> England, <hi>this was not called to redreſs Grievances; but to be ſo over-reach'd, (if they were not careful) that no poſſibility ſhould be left for the future, of redreſſing any. That ſome dangerous Practice might be well ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, when at the ſame time a Parliament was denied to</hi> Scotland, <hi>tho promiſed by the</hi> WORD OF A KING; <hi>granted to</hi> England <hi>when not expected, and obtruded upon</hi> Ireland <hi>when not deſired.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Parliament</hi> met the 13th of <hi>April,</hi> when the <hi>King</hi> requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>a Supply</hi> to carry on his <hi>VVar</hi> againſt the <hi>Scots,</hi> with a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe that he would afterwards redreſs the Kingdom's Grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. To which it was anſwered by many, That redreſs of Grievances was the chief End of aſſembling Parliaments, and ought to precede granting of Subſidies: That the People had no reaſon to pay for that which <hi>they neither cauſed nor deſired;</hi> and which could not prove to their Good, but quite contrary, to the great detriment of the whole Kingdom; That <hi>they would more willingly pay, to prevent that unhappy VVar:</hi> That <hi>the VVar</hi> would make the Breach wider, and the Remedy deſperate: That <hi>THE BEST J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STICE VVO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LD BE, TO FILL <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>P THE PITS VVHICH VVERE MADE TO INTRAP OTHERS, VVITH THE BODIES OF THOSE THAT DIGGED THEM.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:97943:13"/>
            <p>Upon the 5th of <hi>May,</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> to the great grief of both Kingdoms,<note n="*" place="margin">Upon the News of the Diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of this Parliament, Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Barberini,</hi> intituled, <hi>The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector of England,</hi> though he great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affected Arch-Biſhop <hi>Laud,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, That he feared he would cauſe ſome great Diſturbance in <hi>England;</hi> and that certainly, for his ſake, and by his means, the King had diſſolved this Parliament, which he feared <hi>Scotland,</hi> and moſt part of <hi>England,</hi> would take very ill.</note> 
               <hi>diſſolved this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> finding them no way <hi>diſpoſed</hi> to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance the War: But he PROTESTED, HE WOULD GOVERN ACCORDING TO LAW, as if the <hi>Parliament</hi> were conſtantly ſitting: And yet the very next day, to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream Grief of the People, he was ſeen to break his Word; for he commanded the <hi>Lord</hi> BROOKS, Study <hi>and</hi> Pockets <hi>to be ſearched;</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bellaſis,</hi> (Father of the preſent Earl of <hi>Fanomberg</hi>) Sir <hi>John H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Crew,</hi> Members of the Houſe of Commons, <hi>were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned:</hi> And the <hi>King</hi> publiſhed a falſe and ſcandalous Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration againſt the <hi>Commons.</hi> He then betook himſelf to other Courſes to carry on this <hi>VVar: The CLERGY contributed freely to it,</hi> and <hi>Collections were made among the</hi> PAPISTS. Great <hi>Loans</hi> were attempted to be drawn from the <hi>City;</hi> and for not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying therein, Sir <hi>Nicholas Rainton,</hi> Sir <hi>Stephan Soum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and other eminent Citizens were <hi>impriſoned:</hi> Nay, he went <hi>further,</hi> and had it under conſideration to <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oin</hi> 400000 <hi>l.</hi> of BRASS MONEY. [<hi>A Precedent for what the late King</hi> James <hi>did in</hi> Ireland.]</p>
            <p>The <hi>Scots</hi> taking Alarm at the Breach of the <hi>Engliſh Parliament,</hi> and at the King's Preparations, and finding themſelves bereaved of all poſſibility of ſatisfying him by any naked Supplication, they provided for their own Safety, and reſolved to enter <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> with <hi>a Sword in one hand, and a Petition in the other.</hi> The <hi>King</hi> marches his Army Northwards; but <hi>the Common Souldiers</hi> were found ſenſible of Publick Intereſt and Religion, though ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Commanders</hi> and <hi>Gentleman</hi> ſeemed not to be ſo: They de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared their averſion to the War, and <hi>queſtioned whether their</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains <hi>were not</hi> Papiſts.</p>
            <p>Upon the 28th of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1640, the <hi>Scots</hi> marching towards <hi>Nowcaſtle,</hi> the Engliſh <hi>Army</hi> encamped to intercept their Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage; but <hi>many of the Souldiers,</hi> not liking the Cauſe, <hi>forſook their Commanders:</hi> However; <hi>the Horſe</hi> engaged the <hi>Scots,</hi> but received a Repulſe, ſome on both ſides being ſlain; and Colonel <hi>VVilmot,</hi> with Sir <hi>John Digby</hi> and <hi>Oniale,</hi> both <hi>Captains of Horſe and</hi> PAPISTS, were made Priſoners. Hereupon the <hi>Scots</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Maſters of <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> and <hi>Durham.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:97943:14"/>
            <p>The <hi>King,</hi> by Proclamation, ſummoned all the Engliſh No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, with their <hi>Followers and Foroes, to attend his Standard at York,</hi> upon the 20th of <hi>September,</hi> againſt the <hi>Scots.</hi> But about <hi>twenty Peers,</hi> conſidering the great Calamity into which the <hi>King</hi>'s raſh Proceedings had thrown the Kingdom, framed, and ſent his <hi>Majeſty</hi> an <hi>humble Letter,</hi> repreſenting the Miſchiefs at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending his wicked War; the Rapines committed by his Army, <hi>wherein Papiſts were armed, though the Laws permit them not to have Arms in their Houſes,</hi> &amp;c. and they humbly entreated him to ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>a Parliament.</hi> The <hi>King</hi> thereupon ſummoned <hi>all the Lords</hi> to appear at <hi>York</hi> upon the 24th of <hi>September,</hi> and then declared to them, that OF HIS OWN FREE ACCORD, <hi>he had deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to call a</hi> Parliament and <hi>ſixteen Lords</hi> were agreed upon to treat with the like number of the <hi>Scots,</hi> and at length <hi>a Ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of Arms,</hi> till the 16th of <hi>December,</hi> was agreed upon; and that during that time the <hi>Scots</hi> ſhould be paid 850 <hi>l. a day;</hi> and <hi>they allowed Winter-quarters in</hi> England.</p>
            <p>Both Nations hereupon reſted in aſſured Confidence, that the <hi>Parliament</hi> would put a Period to this <hi>War; which could never have been begun, but for want of a</hi> Parliament. They were alſo confident, that the Freedom which the Fundamental Laws allow to <hi>Parliaments,</hi> could not be denied to this; to which the <hi>King</hi> WAS NECESSITATED, and upon which THE PEOPLE had ſet their utmoſt Hope, <hi>whom it ſeemed not ſafe, after ſo many and often repeated Oppreſſions, to provoke any further.</hi> So much for the Scotiſh Affairs.</p>
            <p>Now it may be thought that I have too long digreſſed; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to return to you, <hi>Reverend Doctor Hollingworth,</hi> We will try what <hi>Inferences</hi> may be raiſed from this Melancholy Hiſtory, to render it uſeful to the Engliſh Reader; I have declared that <hi>King Charles</hi> the Firſt <hi>was an inſufferable Tyrant;</hi> you affirm him to have ſet <hi>a Pattern for the beſt of future Princes, and that</hi> King William <hi>and</hi> Queen Mary <hi>are daily imitating him:</hi> And the laſt thing you ſaid was, That when the <hi>Parliament</hi> met in <hi>November</hi> 1640, <hi>He frankly told them, that he was reſolved to put himſelf freely and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on the</hi> LOVE AND AFFECTION OF HIS ENGLISH SUB<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>JECTS. Now I have been taking a great deal of pains to ſet this Matter in its true Light; and to ſhew whence this <hi>ſudden. Fit of Love</hi> to our Nation, <hi>with an excluſion of</hi> Scotland aroſe. And
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97943:14"/>
               <hi>(with your leave, Sir)</hi> here are <hi>two or three <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes of Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation or Inſtruction</hi> from what hath been ſaid.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That this <hi>Declaration of your Martyr's, that he would put himſelf on the Love and Affection of his Engliſh Subjects,</hi> was to draw them in, to ſupport him in his <hi>wicked War againſt the Scotiſh Nation;</hi> whom at the ſame time he called <hi>Rebels,</hi> and urged their Expulſion; tho <hi>he was under an Agreement for a Ceſſation of Arms, and to allow them</hi> 850 <hi>l.</hi> per diem, <hi>and Quarters in</hi> England, till their Complaints might be weighed in this <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Information;</hi> That <hi>he appeared an exorbitant and outragious Tyrant,</hi> in his Attempts upon that People.</p>
            <p>This appears in many Particular, to recount ſome of them briefly.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>In overturning their Church-Government, eſtabliſhed by many Acts of Parliament;</hi> and obtruding upon them <hi>Laud</hi>'s <hi>Liturgy,</hi> and <hi>Popiſh Ceremonies.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>In denying them</hi> (the undoubted Right of all Subjects) <hi>to petition for Redreſs of their Grievances.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>In diſſolving their Synod and Parliament; burning the Pacifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made with them, by the Hangman's Hands; and impriſoning the Lords ſent by them to petition him to perform his ſolemn Promiſes, and redreſs their Grievances.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>In levying Armies againſt them, and raiſing a Civil War,</hi> to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify himſelf in the violation of their Laws. A CIVIL WAR it was, ſaid the great <hi>Lord Digby, ſeeing we are of the ſame Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and under the ſame King.</hi> And,</item>
               <item>5. In the very thing for which you, <hi>Doctor,</hi> are now magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying him; I mean <hi>in attempting to</hi> make uſe of the <hi>Love and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh, to enſlave and ruin the Scotiſh Nation.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Information;</hi> That <hi>the Scotiſh Covenant was not a new Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Innovation,</hi> but eſtabliſhed by the Law of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and <hi>taken by</hi> King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, <hi>ſeventy Years before King</hi> Charles <hi>the Second took it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Information,</hi> That <hi>Biſhops and Clergy-men in Conjunction with Papiſts,</hi> abetted and aſſiſted this <hi>Tyrant</hi> in the Violation of the Laws, when the bulk of the <hi>Nobility, Gentry,</hi> and <hi>People of England,</hi> appeared undauntedly in defence of the Laws and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Kingdom.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:97943:15"/>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Information,</hi> That <hi>Popery hath greatly ſpread in</hi> Scotland <hi>over ſince</hi> Land<hi>'s Superſtition was introduced there;</hi> their number then not exceeding 600, and therefore <hi>Presbytery</hi> being now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored there by Law, it may be reaſonably hoped, that it will reduce many who have been deluded into that <hi>Idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Information,</hi> That PRINCES ARE NOT ALWAYS TO TRUST TO THE <hi>Inſinuations and Suggeſtions of Scotiſh Biſhops;</hi> ſeeing that when they inſtigated <hi>King Charles</hi> the <hi>Firſt</hi> to diſſolve the <hi>Synod</hi> and <hi>Parliament,</hi> he was ſeduced by them into a Belief, that <hi>the Scotiſh Covenanters were a contemptible num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; and that</hi> THEIR PARTY <hi>in</hi> Scotland <hi>was ſufficient to deal with them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Information,</hi> That <hi>the Scots were not Rebels</hi> in taking Arms to aſſert their Rights, and vindicate the Laws and Liberties of their Country. For <hi>my Noble Lord</hi> Ruſſel (the Honour of our Age) was moſt undoubtedly in the right, when, the day before his Murder, he wrote in his Paper left behind him, the following words: <hi>I cannot deny but that I have been of Opinion, that a free Nation, like this, might defend their Religion and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties when invaded and taken from them, the under pretence and colour of Law.</hi> I do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>firm this was his Orthodox Opinion, and theſe the words he wrote, tho they were left out of the Print, and in that day there might be reaſon to omit them.</p>
            <p>But to bethink my ſelf (Reverend Sir) and to return to what we were upon, I leſt you thinking at our laſt parting, I will now hear what your Head run upon. <hi>I think</hi> (ſay you) <hi>he that rends the firſt half Year's Tranſactions betwixt King</hi> Charles <hi>and this Parliament,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 5.</note> 
               <hi>will find he made his Word good to a tittle; for whatſoever they offered to him by way of Bill, which the Nation groaned under before, as a real, nay, but as a fancied Burden, he</hi> PRESENTLY <hi>poſſes it.</hi> To ſhew that,
<q>
                  <l>Againſt Experience you believe,</l>
                  <l>And argue againſt Demonſtration;</l>
                  <l>Pleas'd that you can your ſelf deceive,</l>
                  <l>And ſet your Judgment by your Paſſion.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>We muſt have a little Chat about this half Year, which has exerciſed your Thoughts; and I ſhall ſhew you the Reaſons wherefore I diſſent from your Opinion, That your <hi>Martyr</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:97943:15"/>READILY PASSED <hi>whatſoever Bills the Parliament affored for the Redreſs of the Nation's Grievances.</hi> Now a cannot remember one Inſtance in the whole Hiſtory of his Reign of a <hi>willing and ready Compliance</hi> with his People, in any one Act of <hi>Grace or Juſtice.</hi> Every thing of that kind in the whole courſe of his Life, was wreſted from him by the univerſal Outory of the Kingdom againſt his high Oppreſſions, which did never avail, but when the extremity of his Affairs wrought his ſtubborn Mind to a Compliance. And moſt ſure I am, that you are miſtaken in the ſew Inſtances you bring: You ſay, That he PRESENTLY <hi>paſs'd the Bills for putting down the</hi> Stan-Chamber <hi>and</hi> High-Commiſſion-Coures: But I affirm the contrary, and do thus prove it. The <hi>Parliament</hi> could never bring him to make a fair Bargain with them, they bought every thing at a very dear rate, and when they had come to his Price, they were ever in danger of being wick'd. They came to a Contract with him to yield up thoſe two accurſed <hi>Courts of Oppreſſion and Tyranny,</hi> and agreed to a POLL BILL, wherein every <hi>Duke</hi> was aſſeſſed at 100 <hi>l.</hi> a <hi>Marqueſe</hi> at 80 <hi>l. Earls</hi> 60 <hi>l. Viſcounts and Barons</hi> 40 <hi>l. Knights of the Bath, and Baronets</hi> 30 <hi>l.</hi> nother <hi>Knights</hi> 20 <hi>l. Eſquires</hi> 10 <hi>l. every Genduriam diſpending 100 <hi>l.</hi> per Annum, 5 <hi>l.</hi> and all others of Ability to pay a competent proportion; and <hi>the meaneſt Head in the whole Kingdom was not excuſed. [I hear there is now a Poll-Bill on foot in this preſent Parliament; and therefore, from the high Affection and Duty which I hear and ſhall ever pay to thoſe excellent Princes who do ſo happily fill their</hi> Grandfathers and Fathers Throne, <hi>I do here remember my Country men at what rate, and for what they were thus aſſeſſed in</hi> 1640. <hi>Then they were forc'd to buy off the Encroachments of a</hi> TYRANT, who had ſworn to maint ain their Laws and Liberties: but now they at lower rates, are only to enable the heſt Princes that ever ſway'd the Engliſh Scepter, to vanquiſh the worſt of Tyrants.</hi>] Well,</p>
            <p>This Bargain was ſtruck, and <hi>the Parliament</hi> reſolving very honeſtly to ſtand to it, they prepared the <hi>Bills,</hi> but finding the <hi>King</hi> begin to falter, declaring that he would take their Money, but would not at that time paſs the Bills to put down the <hi>Star-Chamber</hi> and <hi>High-Commiſſion-Courts;</hi> They <hi>voted, that he ſhould paſs all the three Bills, or none at all.</hi> However,</p>
            <p>Neither the <hi>Contract</hi> nor their <hi>Vote</hi> could hold him, he trick'd them here; and upon the 2d of <hi>July</hi> paſs'd the <hi>Poll-Money Bill,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97943:16"/>but demurred upon the other two.</hi> The afterwards, finding that the matter was very ill taken, and that it was not ſeaſonable to diſpleaſe the Kingdom at that time, he paſſed the other two Bills. And now hope that you are convinced, that he did not, ſo PRESENTLY <hi>paſs Bills for Redreſe of Grievances,</hi> as you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderately ſuggeſted.</p>
            <p>To proceed (Sir) you ſay,<note place="margin">Pag. 5.</note> That THE STAR-CHAMBER <hi>had been complain'd of as a Grievance, and therefore he ſigns the Bills to take it away:</hi> The HIGH-COMMISSION <hi>was a Court that moſt Mens Moths were opened againſt and he conſents to take that away two.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Very good! We have ſettled the Fact, theſe Courts were taken away, I have told you in what manner, and for what, Conſideration: I will now take leave to inform you, what great Reaſons there were to put them down <hi>Archbiſhop Land,</hi> and divers of his Brethren, had caſt off all Humanity, and were metamorphos'd into ravenous Wolves, and theſe Courts were under their management. The <hi>Star-Chamber,</hi> had abounded in extravagant Cenſures, whereby the Subjects were oppreſſed by grievous Fines, Impriſonments, Stigmatizings, Mutilations, Whippings, Pillories, Gags, Baniſhments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the <hi>High-Commiſſion,</hi> was grown to ſuch exceſs of Sharpneſs and Severity, as was not much leſs than the <hi>Spaniſh, Inquiſition.</hi> To repeat two or three of the many Inſtances of the horrid Oppreſſion, and barbarous Cruelty exerciſed in theſe <hi>Tyrannical Courts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the 17th of <hi>February</hi> 1629, Dr. <hi>LEIGHTON</hi> coming out of <hi>Black-friars Church (it ſeems then he was no Conventicler</hi>) was ſeized by a Warrant from the HIGH-COMMISSION-COURT, and drag'd to Bp <hi>LA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>D</hi>'s HOUSE; from thence, without any Examination, he was carried to <hi>Newgate,</hi> and there clap'd <hi>into Irons,</hi> and thruſt into <hi>a naſty Hole, where he continued from Tueſday night till Thurſday noon without Meat or Drink:</hi> They kept him in that loathſom place where Snow and Rain beat in upon him <hi>fifteen Weeks,</hi> not permitting <hi>his Wife</hi> or any Friend to come near him, and <hi>denied to give him a Copy of his Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> then they brought him into the STAR-CHAMBER-COURT, where an <hi>Information</hi> was exhibited againſt him, for publiſhing a Book called, SION'S PLEA AGAINST THE PRELATES.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:97943:16"/>
            <p>By his <hi>Anſwer</hi> he confeſſed, that when the <hi>Parliament</hi> was ſitting in the Year 1628, he drew up the Heads of that Book; and having the Approbation of five hundred Perſons inter their Hands, whereof ſome were <hi>Members of Parliament,</hi> he went into <hi>Holland</hi> to get is printed. That he printed but between five and ſix hundred only, for the uſe of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> but they being diſſolved, he returned home, not bringing any of them into the Land, but made it his ſpecial Cate to ſuppreſs them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Doctor,</hi> being charged by the <hi>Information</hi> with theſe words in the ſaid Book; <hi>We do not read of greater Perſecution of God's People in any Nation profeſſing the Goſpel, than in this our Iſland, eſpecially SINCE THE DEATH OF Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EEN ELIZABETH.</hi> He confeſſed the words, and anſwer'd. That <hi>the thing was too too true, as appeared by the Prelates taking away Life and Liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood from many Miniſters and private Mens</hi> of whom <hi>many were pined to death in Priſon,</hi> and many wandred up and down, their Families being left deſolate and helpleſs: That beſides this, <hi>the Blood of Souls had been endanger'd by the remoul of the faithful Shepherds from the Flock.</hi> This was a cutting Truth. And,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>D</hi> being enraged, <hi>deſired the Court to put the higheſt Cenſure that could be put upon him:</hi> That they did to his Content, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning him to have his Ears cut, his Noſe ſlit, to be branded in the Face, whipp'd at a Poſt, to ſtand on the Pillory, to pay 10000</hi> l. <hi>Fine</hi> (tho they knew he was not worth ſo much) <hi>and to be perpetually impriſon'd.</hi> The grateful Sentence being paſt, <hi>Laud</hi> pull'd of his Cap, and holding up his Hands, <hi>gave Thanks to God, who had given him Victory over his Enemies.</hi> A <hi>Knight</hi> moved one of the <hi>Lords</hi> about the dreadfulneſs of the Cenſure, inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating that <hi>it open'd a Gap to the</hi> PRELATES, <hi>to inflict ſuch diſgraceful Puniſhments and Tortures, upon Men of Quality;</hi> That <hi>Lord</hi> replied, That it was but <hi>in terrorem,</hi> and that <hi>he would not have any one think that the Sentence ſhould ever he executed.</hi> Nevertheleſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laud</hi> had his deſign; for upon the 26th of <hi>November</hi> 1630 the Cenſure was executed in a moſt cruel mamner, <hi>his Ears were out, his Noſe ſlit, his Face branded with burning Irons, he was tied to a Poſt, and whipp'd with a treble Cord,</hi> to that cruel degree, that he himſelf writing the Hiſtory thereof ten Years after, affirmed, that <hi>every Laſh brought away the Fleſh,</hi> and that he ſhould feel it
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97943:17"/>to his dying day. <hi>He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> laſtly, <hi>put in the Pillory, and kept there near two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in Froſt and Snow:</hi> And then, after this moſt bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Uſage, not permitted to return to his Quarters in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, in a Couch provided to carry him; but compelled, In that ſad Condition and ſevere Seaſon, to go by Water.</p>
            <p>After this, <hi>was kept ten weeks in Dirt and Mire,</hi> not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſheltered from Rain and Snow. <hi>They ſhut him up,</hi> moſt cloſely, 22 <hi>Months,</hi> and <hi>he remained a Priſoner ten or eleven Years,</hi> not ſuffered to breath in the open Air, until the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>November</hi> 1640, moſt happily delivered him; <hi>When he came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad,</hi> to proſecute his Petition in that <hi>Parliament, he could nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther go, ſee, nor hear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſurely, Dr. <hi>Hollingworth,</hi> (for I do not forget to whom I and writing) this diſmal Story had flip'd your Memory, when you ſaid,<note place="margin">Vindication of their Majeſties Wiſdom, <hi>p.</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>The Biſhop</hi> Laud <hi>was a very good Man, ſave in the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Book of Sports, and ſome other, as you fancy (for, you ſay, you are tender of judging) unneceſſary. Innovations.</hi> But you muſt put on Patience, to hear ſomething more of this bloody Villain's Barbarity.</p>
            <p>Upon the 1ſt of <hi>February</hi> 1632, <hi>Laud</hi> procured Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> to be ſent <hi>cloſe Priſoner to the</hi> Tower: There he lay till the 21ſt of <hi>June</hi> 1633, when an <hi>Information</hi> was exhibited againſt him in the <hi>Star-Chamber;</hi> for publiſhing a Book concerning <hi>Interludes,</hi> intituled,<note n="*" place="margin">Note, that no particular Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages in the Book were mentioned in the Inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation.</note> 
               <hi>Hiſtriomaſtix,</hi> WHICH WAS LICENSED BY A Chaplain of Dr. <hi>Abbot</hi>'s, Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi> Upon the 17th of <hi>Feb.</hi> 1633. he had this heavy Sentence paſs'd upon him; <hi>To be impriſon'd for Life, pay</hi> 5000 <hi>l. Fine; be expelled</hi> Lincolns-Inn; <hi>diſabled to exerciſe the Profeſſion of a Barriſter; degraded by the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of</hi> Oxford <hi>of his Degree there taken: and that done, to be ſet in the Pillory at</hi> Weſtminiſter, <hi>and have one of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Ears there cut off; and at another time to be ſet in the Pillory in</hi> Cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ide, <hi>and there have his other Ear cut off.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tho many of the <hi>Lords</hi> never dreamt of the Execution of this horrid Judgment; Nay, tho Queen <hi>Henrietta Maria,</hi> (which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves an honourable mention, and ſhe ſhall have it, for <hi>fire was their preſent Majeſties Royal Grandmother</hi>) <hi>earneſtly interceded with the bigotted, cruel and mercileſs King,</hi> (he ſhall have that too, with your leave, Doctor, for <hi>he was a Tyrant</hi>) <hi>to remit its execution;</hi> yet on the 7th and 10th of <hi>May,</hi> it was fully executed with great rigour.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:97943:17"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> remained ſundry Years in the <hi>Tower</hi> upon this Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; and in that time Dr. <hi>Baſtmick</hi> (in the Year 1635) was brought into the <hi>High-Commiſſion Inquiſition,</hi> and impriſon'd in the <hi>Gatehouſe, Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Year 1636, Mr. <hi>Burton</hi> preached a <hi>Sermon</hi> upon the 5th of <hi>November,</hi> at his <hi>Church in Friday-ſtreet, London,</hi> wherein <hi>he laid open the Innovations, in Doctrine, Worſhip and Ceremonies, which had lately crept into the Church; and wiſhed the People to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of them.</hi> For this, <hi>LA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>D</hi> cauſed Articles to be drawn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him in the <hi>High-Commiſſion Court,</hi> and <hi>ſuſpended him:</hi> Then, cauſing his Houſe to be broken open, took and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him to the <hi>Fleet</hi> cloſe Priſoner; and he was ſhut up there di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Weeks from his Wife and Friends.</p>
            <p>Upon the 11th of <hi>March</hi> 1636, they exhibited an <hi>Information</hi> againſt Dr. <hi>Baſtwick,</hi> Mr. <hi>Pryn,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Burton,</hi> in the <hi>Star-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi> And upon the 14th of <hi>June</hi> 1637, they paſs'd this Sentence on them, <hi>viz. To loſe their Ears in the</hi> Palace-yard, Weſtminſter: <hi>To pay a Fine of</hi> 5000 <hi>l. a Man; and be perpetually impriſoned in three remote Places of the Kingdom,</hi> viz. <hi>the Caſtles of</hi> Carnarvan, Cornwal, <hi>and</hi> Lancaſter; <hi>and Mr.</hi> Pryn <hi>to be ſtigmatized in the Cheeks with two Letters,</hi> (S. <hi>and</hi> L.) <hi>for a ſeditious Libeller.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the 30th of <hi>June,</hi> 1637, to the great regret of the People, who ſtrowed their way with Herbs, theſe <hi>Confeſſors for the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Liberties,</hi> were brought to the Place appointed for the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the accurſed Sentence; which was done in a manner extraordinarily cruel.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Baſtwick</hi> being upon the Pillory, ſpoke thus to the lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting People, <hi>I wrote a Book againſt the Pope, and the POPE OF</hi> CANTERBURY <hi>ſaid I wrote againſt him.—So far am I from baſe Fear, that had I as much Blood as would ſwell the</hi> Thames, <hi>I would ſhed it every drop in this Cauſe: Had I as many Lives as I have Hairs on my Head, I would give them all for this Cauſe.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing let out of the Pillory, he took the Spunge from one of his Ears, which was all bloody, and waving it over his Head, ſaid, <hi>Bleſſed be my God, who hath counted me worthy, and of his mighty Power hath enabled me to ſuffer any thing for his ſake. And as I have now loſt ſome of my Blood, ſo am I ready and willing to ſpill every drop in my Veins in this Cauſe for which I have now ſuffered; which is, for maintaining the Truth of God, and the Honour of my King, againſt Popiſh <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations.</hi> LET GOD BE GLORIFIED,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97943:18"/>AND LET THE KING LIVE FOR EVER. [Theſe were not Expreſſions of a COMMON-WEALTH'S MAN, or <hi>a Rebel;</hi> Were they good Doctor-<hi>Chaplain at</hi> Aldgate?]</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi>'s turn being next; he expreſs'd himſelf thus, <hi>We are accounted FACTIO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S FELLOWS, Hereticks and REBELS, for</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Diſcoverers of Plots againſt the Proteſtant Religion, and Engliſh Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, have been ever uſed at the rate which Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> was, ever ſince <hi>Laud</hi>'s Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on got up in the Church.</note> 
               <hi>DICOVERING A PLOT OF POPERY: Alas, POOR</hi> ENGLAND! <hi>What will become of thee and thy Religion, if thou maintaineſt not thy own ESTABLISH'D FAITH</hi> [<hi>you ſee,</hi> Doctor, <hi>Mr.</hi> Pryn <hi>was for the Church as eſtabliſh'd by Law</hi>] <hi>AND LAW<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>F<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>L LIBERTIES?</hi> [Ay, that ſpoils all, for it renders him <hi>a Common-wealth's man</hi> no doubt; yet 'tis but ſuch a one as the late <hi>King</hi> Charles <hi>the ſecond,</hi> frankly told the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Bucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> he would have been, had he not been <hi>a King.</hi>] <hi>Chriſtian People,</hi> (proceeded Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi>) <hi>I beſeech you all ſtand firm, and be zealous for the Cauſe of God and his true Religion, to the ſhedding of your deareſt Blood, otherwiſe you will bring your ſelves and your Poſterities</hi> INTO PERPETUAL BONDAGE AND SLAVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RY, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Executioner</hi> coming to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ear and cut his Ears, he ſaid, <hi>Come Friend, Come, burn me, cut me, I fear not; I have learn'd to fear the Fire of Hell, and not what Man can do unto me: Come, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar me, ſear me, I ſhall bear in my Body the Marks of the Lord Jeſus.</hi> The <hi>Executioner</hi> having done his part, and that with the utmoſt Cruelty; Mr. <hi>Pryn,</hi> with a ſmiling Countenance ſaid; Now, <hi>bleſſed be God, I have conquer'd and triumphed over the Biſhop's Malice;</hi> and returning to the <hi>Tower,</hi> he made theſe <hi>Verſes</hi> by the way.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>S. L. STIGMATA LAUDIS.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <lg>
                  <l>Stigmata Maxillis referens inſignia Laudis,</l>
                  <l>Exultans remeo, victima grata Deo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Triumphant I return: My Face deſcries;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Laud</hi>'s ſcorching Scars, God's grateful Sacrifice.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>Next follows <hi>Reverend Mr.</hi> Burton; he being in the <hi>Pillory,</hi> ſaid, <hi>I was never in ſuch a Pulpit before; but little do you know what Fruit God is able to produce from this dry Tree; MARK MY WORDS; I ſay, through theſe Holes God can bring Light to his
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97943:18"/>Church.</hi> Moreover, he ſaid, <hi>My Conſcience in the diſcharge of my Miniſterial Duty, in admoniſhing my People to beware of the CREEPING IN OF POPERY, and exhorting of them to ſtick cloſe to God and the King, in Duties of Obedience, was that which firſt occaſioned my Sufferings. For the Truth I have preached, I am ready to ſeal it with my Blood; for this is my Crown both here and hereafter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this Execution done, they were baniſhed to the remote parts of the Kingdom, and there kept ſeveral Years in cloſe and ſolitary Confinement, not allowed Pen, Ink and Paper, nor the ſight of any Friend; and in this moſt deplorable caſe did the <hi>Parliament</hi> in <hi>November</hi> 1640, find theſe three diſtreſſed <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> of ſeveral Profeſſions, the nobleſt in the Kingdom, <hi>Divinity, Law, and Phyſick,</hi> but they were ſoon ſent for from their Exile, and brought into <hi>London</hi> by many thouſands of rejoycing Gentlemen and Citizens, who went out on Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back to meet and congratulate their Deliverance. And the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> taking their Caſe into Conſideration, <hi>voted,</hi> THAT THE JUDGMENTS GIVEN <hi>againſt them were illegal, unjuſt, and againſt the</hi> LIBERTY OF THE SUBJECT. Now <hi>good Doctor,</hi> was not here reaſon with a witneſs, <hi>to open every Man's Mouth with Complaints,</hi> againſt theſe moſt arbitrary and pernicious Courts, and to induce the Parliament to remove theſe Forges of Miſery, Oppreſſion and Violence? Nevertheleſs the KING, <hi>with a very unwilling Mind,</hi> as I have ſhew'd, <hi>yielded therein:</hi> but as he loſt much of the Thanks, which ſo great a Grace, <hi>freely and forwardly expreſs'd,</hi> might have deſerved; ſo I doubt it will be ſome dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution to your Credit, <hi>dear Doctor,</hi> that, <hi>contrary to what you affirm,</hi> HE DELAYED, and did not <hi>preſently</hi> comply in this matter. Well! what follows now? The <hi>King</hi> is ſtill on the giving hand no doubt of it.</p>
            <p>THE SHIP-MONEY (you add) <hi>tho great and very learned Lawyers had given their Opinion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 5.</note> 
               <hi>that the exacting of it in ſome Caſes was according to Law; yet he,</hi> GOOD MAN, <hi>gives up that alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here, <hi>good Doctor;</hi> you ſpeak like A MEER CLERGY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MAN, and I begin to ſuſpect that you never read any other than Dr. <hi>NALSON</hi>'s HISTORY, and are tainted with the Principles of thoſe famous <hi>Gentlemen</hi> of the <hi>Caſſock, SIBTHORP</hi> and <hi>MANWARING,</hi> who as well as ſome deſigning <hi>Lawyers,</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:97943:19"/>told your <hi>Martyr, That Authority of Parliament is not neceſſary for the raiſing Aids and Subſidies.</hi> That <hi>all Antiquity is abſolutely, for abſolute Obedience to Princes in all Civil and Temporal Things.</hi> You make the yielding up the Claim of <hi>Ship-Money</hi> to be an Act of <hi>pure Grace;</hi> for <hi>very able Lawyers gave their Opinion that the King might exact it by Law,</hi> and ſo I have told you, did <hi>as able and no leſs knaviſh Divines.</hi> But hearken, I beſeech you, what the <hi>Wiſdom of Parliament</hi> told him. <hi>They declared it a new and unheard of Tax;</hi> they voted it <hi>a moſt illegal Taxation, and unſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Grievance;</hi> they look'd into the Carriage of thoſe <hi>Judges</hi> who adviſed the <hi>King</hi> in this matter, and found that Sir <hi>JOHN FINCH</hi> (a <hi>Gentleman</hi> of good Birth, of an <hi>high and imperious</hi> Spirit, ELOQUENT IN SPEECH; <hi>tho in the knowledg of the Law not very deep)</hi> in the Year 1636, when <hi>Ship-Money</hi> was firſt plotted and ſet on foot, was made <hi>Lord Chief Juſtice of the Common-Pleas,</hi> and it appeared that by his Brokage and Sollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and that with Threats and Promiſes, ſeveral of the Judges were wrought upon to give it under their hand, that the King might by Law exact Ship-Money: Thereupon an <hi>Impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of High Treaſon</hi> was drawn up againſt him; and <hi>the great Lord FA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LKLAND (tho an Admirer of the Church, as you tell me)</hi> preſented it to the <hi>Lords,</hi> with a very pithy and ſharp Oration againſt <hi>Finch;</hi> but <hi>he</hi> (being at this time <hi>Lord-Keeper</hi>) not daring to abide the Teſt, <hi>took his Wings,</hi> and fled in a diſguiſe to <hi>Holland.</hi> In Concluſion, the Arbitrary Power, pretended to be in the <hi>King,</hi> of taxing the Subject without Conſent in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, was not only declared to be againſt Law by the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of both Houſes, but alſo by Act of <hi>Parliament.</hi> Thus we rid our Hands of SHIP-MONEY. And,</p>
            <p>Now indeed, Sir, you come to that which might well raiſe your Choler, and ſtir your Indignation: <hi>The King paſſed a Bill to remove the Biſhops out of the Houſe of Lords; he alſo paſſed a Bill for attainting the great Earl of</hi> Strafford, <hi>which offered Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to the Peace and Quiet of his Mind all the days of his Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To tell you the Truth, <hi>Doctor,</hi> the <hi>Parliament found the Biſhops</hi> of that day, <hi>to be the Troublers of the State,</hi> and that it was by conſequence become moſt neceſſary to abridg their immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Power uſurped over the <hi>Clergy,</hi> and other good Subjects, which they had moſt maliciouſly abuſed to the hazard of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97943:19"/>and great Prejudice and Oppreſſion of the Laws of the Kingdom, and juſt Liberty of the Subject: They had cheriſh'd <hi>Formality and Superſtition</hi> as the probable Supports of their own <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Tyranny and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation;</hi> they had multiplied and enlarged the Differences between <hi>the common Proteſtants,</hi> and thoſe whom they called <hi>Puritans,</hi> under which Name they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded all thoſe that deſired to preſerve the Laws and Liberties of the Kingdom, and to maintain the <hi>true Proteſtant Religion.</hi> They had been deſigning <hi>a Conjunction between Papiſts and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> in <hi>Doctrine, Diſcipline</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> only it muſt not yet be called <hi>Popery.</hi> They had triumphed in the <hi>Suſpenſions, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communications, Deprivations and Degradations</hi> of divers <hi>learned and pious Miniſters,</hi> in the Vexation and grievous Oppreſſion of great numbers of the People, whereby many thouſands were impoveriſhed, and others were ſo afflicted and troubled by them, that great numbers departed into <hi>New-England,</hi> and other parts of <hi>America,</hi> others into <hi>Holland.</hi> The moſt of the <hi>Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> that was allowed, was degenerate into <hi>railing againſt Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Puritans,</hi> (becauſe they were tenacious of juſt Liberty and true Religion) <hi>crying up Abſolute Authority, Paſſive Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> &amp;c. Streins of Wit, fitter for a Stage than a Pulpit. After the Diſſolution of the <hi>Parliament</hi> in <hi>May</hi> 1640, <hi>They continued the Convocation,</hi> and by unheard-of Preſumption, <hi>they made Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons contrary to the King's Prerogative, to the Fundamental Laws of the Realm, to the Right of Parliaments, to the Property and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the Subject,</hi> thereby eſtabliſhing their own <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations,</hi> juſtifying their <hi>Altar-Worſhip,</hi> and other <hi>Superſtitious Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> which they had formerly introduced without Warrant of Law; <hi>they impoſed a new Oath</hi> on the Subjects for mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of their own <hi>Tyranny,</hi> and <hi>laid a great Tax upon the Clergy.</hi> And now, to ſill up the meaſure of their Iniquity, <hi>the Houſe of Lords</hi> upon the 30th of <hi>December</hi> 1641, at a Conference with the Commons, told them, <hi>that the Biſhops,</hi> by a Proteſtation which they made to the King and Lords, <hi>had deeply intrenched upon the Fundamental Priviledges and Being of Parliament;</hi> whereupon the <hi>Commons impeached twelve of them of High-Treaſon,</hi> in endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſubvert the Fundamental Laws of the Realm, and the very Being of Parliaments; and <hi>they were</hi> by the Houſe of <hi>Peers ſequeſtred from Parliament, committed to the Tower,</hi> and ſhortly. after, by Act of <hi>Parliament,</hi> moſt deſervedly <hi>deprived of voting in the Houſe of Peers.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:97943:20"/>
            <p>I hope, <hi>good Doctor,</hi> you will acquieſce in the Reaſons which I have here offered for the paſſing this <hi>Bill of Excluſion;</hi> but <hi>the other Bill for attainting the great Earl of</hi> Strafford, you ſay, <hi>offered Violence to the Peace and Quiet of the King's Mind, all the days of his Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This great Man who had long run on in a full Career to eſtabliſh Tyranny, trampling down the Peoples Liberties, leaping the Hedges of the Laws, or making Gaps through them, was <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached</hi> by the <hi>Commons</hi> in many Articles, ſome whereof were <hi>for ruling</hi> Ireland (or which he had been <hi>Lord-Lieutenant</hi>) <hi>in an Arbitrary way,</hi> againſt the Fundamental Laws, which he had endeavoured to ſubvert. <hi>For abuſing his Power to the increaſe and encouragement of Papiſts; for maliciouſly endeavouring to ſtir up Hoſtility between</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Scotland; <hi>for labouring to ſubvert Parliaments,</hi> and incenſe the King againſt them; for <hi>levying Money by force of Arms;</hi> for <hi>impoſing an Oath upon the Subjects, That they ſhould not proteſt againſt any of the King's Commands:</hi> for <hi>telling the King, That he had an Army in</hi> Ireland, <hi>which his Majeſty might imploy to reduce this Kingdom to Obedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon this <hi>Impeachment</hi> the <hi>Earl</hi> was brought to <hi>Trial</hi> before the <hi>Lords,</hi> which laſted from the <hi>22d</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> (with but few days intermiſſion) till the midſt of <hi>April.</hi> After this long Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, <hi>the Commons voted him guilty of High-Treaſon,</hi> in divers Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, and drew up and paſſed <hi>a Bill of Attainder</hi> againſt him, <hi>but</hi> 59 <hi>diſſenting.</hi> This Bill being carried to the <hi>Lords,</hi> the <hi>King's Sollicitor General</hi> made it good by Law, to the ſatisfaction of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all that heard him: <hi>The Judges alſo delivered their Opinions, That the Matters proved againſt him amounted to Treaſon; and ſo the Lords paſſed the Bill.</hi> The <hi>King,</hi> having after this, <hi>called all the Judges to deliver their Opinions before him; and alſo ſent for</hi> FOUR BISHOPS TO RESOLVE HIM UPON SCRUPLE OF CONSCIENCE; He, at length, <hi>gave the Royal Aſſent to this Bill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Prithee, now <hi>Doctor,</hi> tell me, what ail'd your <hi>Martyr's Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> at this time? There muſt be ſomething extraordinary, and not commonly taken notice of in this Matter, that muſt (as you affirm) <hi>offer Violence to the Peace and Quiet of his Mind, all the Days of his Life.</hi> You know, he exacted the <hi>Ship-Money without ſcruple of Conſcience,</hi> upon the Advice of ſome <hi>Lawyers.</hi> And though they retracted their Opinions, both Houſes of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:97943:20"/>voted, and his <hi>Majeſty</hi> at length acknowledged it to be an illegal and unjuſt Exaction: Yet <hi>that Guilt ſoon were off,</hi> and we never heard that thereby, or by any other of the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt innumerable Oppreſſions of his People; no, nor by his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying the poor <hi>Proteſtants of Rochel;</hi> the Quiet of his Mind was any way diſturbed. Now, in the Caſe we are upon, here was a fair and moſt ſolemn <hi>Trial;</hi> The <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons voted the Crimes, Treaſon;</hi> The <hi>King's Counſel and Judges</hi> avowed the ſame; The <hi>Biſhops</hi> (MARK THAT, DOCTOR) <hi>pick'd the Thorn out of his Conſcience</hi> Nevertheleſs, his paſſing <hi>this Bill,</hi> violated the Peace of his Mind all the days of his Life. To offer ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing towards the enlightning you in this Matter, allow me to remind you what you have before read: When the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Buckingham</hi> was impeached for Treaſon, <hi>this ſame King</hi> told the <hi>Parliament,</hi> THAT <hi>B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CKINGHAM</hi> HAD NOT INTER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MEDLED, NOR DONE ANY THING CONCERNING THE PURBLICK, BUT BY HIS SPECIAL DIRECTIONS. Now, I have a ſtrong fancy, that <hi>the unhappy Earl of</hi> Strafford'<hi>s Caſe,</hi> was the ſame with the <hi>Duke</hi>'s;<note place="margin">'Tis a miſchievous Conſcience with whom one good Deed is ſo hard to paſs down, as to endanger almoſt a choaking; and bad Deeds without number, tho as big and as bulky as the Buin of three Kingdoms, go down currently without ſtraining.</note> and that it diſturbed the Quiet of the King's Mind, that he could not preſerve this, as he had done his other Servant, in the execution of his own Commands. And no marvel it ſtung his Conſcience to adjudg to death thoſe Miſdeeds whereof himſelf had been the chief Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor.</p>
            <p>In the next place, <hi>good Doctor,</hi> you inform us, <hi>That the King ſigned a Bill for a Triennial Parliament; which certainly was as great a condeſcention as was ever made by a Prince,</hi> I Why now, 'tis very unlucky, <hi>Doctor,</hi> that when you think your ſelf <hi>certainly</hi> in the right, you are moſt undoubtedly in the wrong; for <hi>this Act for a</hi> TRIENNIAL PARLIAMENT, <hi>did not extend to ſo much as by Law the Parliament ought to have required,</hi> there being at that time <hi>two Statutes</hi> of <hi>Edward 3d</hi> in force <hi>for a Parliament to be holden once a Year.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now you bring me to an Act of ſuperabundant Grace;<note place="margin">Pag. 6.</note> you ſay, That <hi>he paſſed an Act for the Parliament to ſit during pleaſure.</hi> This was ſomething indeed; we muſt therefore exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine what Reaſons the Parliament had to inſiſt upon this Bill,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97943:21"/>and what the Motives were that brought the King to comply herein.</p>
            <p>It appeared moſt evidently to both Houſes, by the Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Confeſſions of ſeveral of the Criminals, that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time before the paſſing of the Bill for the continuance of the Parliament, (which was upon the 10th of <hi>May</hi> 1641.) <hi>The KING had been tampering with the Army which he had raiſed againſt the Scots,</hi> and which lay undisbanded in the North, to bring them up to curb the Parliament, and ſubdue them to his Will. Many great Men were found to be engaged in this Conſpiracy, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Piercy,</hi> Brother to the Earl of <hi>Northumberland;</hi> Mr. <hi>Henry Jermin</hi> the Queen's Favourite, (afterwards <hi>Earl</hi> of St. <hi>Albans</hi>); Mr. <hi>Goring,</hi> eldeſt Son to the <hi>Lord Goring;</hi> Mr. <hi>Wilmot,</hi> the <hi>Lord Wilmot</hi>'s eldeſt Son; Sir <hi>John Suckling;</hi> Colonel <hi>Aſhburn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham; Pollard; Oneal,</hi> an Iriſh Papiſt; and many others: <hi>theſe had taken an Oath of Secrecy among themſelves.</hi> To joyn with this Army, and ſtrengthen the Plot, <hi>a French Army was to be landed at Portſmouth,</hi> which Town, for that purpoſe, was to be put into Mr. <hi>Jermyn's hands;</hi> and <hi>the</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The Parliament had addreſſed the King to disband this Army; but he anſwer'd, That <hi>he would not allow of the disbanding the Iriſh Army, for divers Reaſons beſt known to himſelf.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Iriſh Army,</hi> conſiſting of 8000, <hi>almoſt all Papiſts,</hi> was to be brought over.</p>
            <p>Upon the Diſcovery of this horrid Plot, <hi>Piercy,</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jermin,</hi> after this Diſcovery, went off with a Paſs under the King's own Hand; which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Governour of <hi>Portſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi> to provide, <hi>with all ſpeed,</hi> a Ship to carry him to any Port of <hi>France.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Jermin</hi> and <hi>Suckling</hi> fled into <hi>France; Goring</hi> being taken, made an ingenuous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and ſo was diſcharged: <hi>Oneal, Wilmot, Aſhburnham,</hi> and others, were committed to the Tower, from whence <hi>Oneal</hi> was permitted to make his Eſcape.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Piercy,</hi> by a Letter from beyond the Seas, to his Brother the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> dated the 14th of <hi>June,</hi> confeſſed much of this Conſpiracy; in particular, the taking the Oath of Secrecy; And that they had agreed to engage the Army to ſtand by the King againſt the Parliament, in
<q>
                  <l>The preſerving the Biſhops Functions and Votes.</l>
                  <l>The not disbanding the Iriſh Army till the Scots were disbanded.</l>
                  <l>The endeavouring to ſettle his Revenue to that proportion it was formerly.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:97943:21"/>
            <p>That <hi>he imparted all this to the King,</hi> and perceived, that <hi>he had been treated with by others, concerning ſomething of the Army;</hi> which did not agree with thoſe Propoſals, BUT INCLINED A WAY MORE HIGH AND SHARP, NOT HAVING LI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MITS EITHER OF HONOUR OR LAW. That <hi>Goring</hi> and <hi>Jermin</hi> were acquainted with the other Proceedings; and that <hi>the King</hi> preſſed Mr. <hi>Piercy</hi> to admit them to conſultation: To which he having yielded, and ſworn them to Secrecy, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted them what he had propoſed; but <hi>HE FO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ND THEIR PROPOSALS DIFFERED FROM HIS, IN VIO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LENCE AND HEIGHT.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Colonel <hi>Goring</hi> confeſſed, upon his Examination, that <hi>Jermin</hi> carried him to the <hi>King,</hi> who asked him, <hi>If he was engaged in any CABAL concerning the Army?</hi> To which <hi>Goring</hi> anſwering, That he was not: The <hi>King</hi> ſaid, <hi>I command you</hi> then <hi>to join your ſelf with</hi> Piercy, and ſome others whom you will find with him at his Lodgings. That he thereupon went, and found with Mr. <hi>Piercy; Wilmot, Oneal,</hi> and others: That he and <hi>Jermin</hi> having firſt taken <hi>the Oath of Secrecy,</hi> which the others had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken before: Mr. <hi>Piercy</hi> made his Propoſitions, <hi>viz. That the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ſhould preſently be put into a poſture to ſerve the King,</hi> and then ſhould ſend up <hi>a Declaration</hi> to the <hi>Parliament</hi> of theſe Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars: <hi>That nothing ſhould be done in Parliament, contrary to any for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Act of Parliament;</hi> and the <hi>King's Revenne</hi> be eſtabliſh'd: <hi>That</hi> Jermin <hi>propounded, that the Army ſhould be immediately brought to</hi> London; and they <hi>SHO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LD MAKE S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RE OF THE</hi> TOWER. and he confeſſed, that he himſelf urged theſe things, to ſhew the Vanity and Danger of the other Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, without undertaking theſe.</p>
            <p>Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Ballard</hi> and Capt. <hi>Chudleigh</hi> confeſſed, that <hi>the French that were about</hi> London, <hi>were to be mounted</hi> and would join with the Army; and that <hi>the Clergy would raiſe</hi> 1000 <hi>Horſe</hi> to aſſiſt them, And <hi>Chudleigh</hi> added, that <hi>the Queen had ſent down Money to fortify</hi> PORTSMOUTH: Further, that Mr. <hi>Jermin</hi> ask'd him, if he thought the <hi>Army</hi> would ſtick to their Officers, <hi>in caſe the King and Parliament ſhould not agree?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It further appeared by the Confeſſions of Sir <hi>Jacob Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>John Conniers,</hi> and Capt. <hi>Legg,</hi> eminent Commanders in the <hi>King</hi>'s Army; that <hi>Oneal</hi> the Papiſt was a principal Agent in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:97943:22"/>carrying on their Intrigue of working upon the Army to engage them againſt the Parliament; That <hi>THE KING ſent Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons under his Hand,</hi> for <hi>a Petition</hi> to be preſented from the <hi>Army:</hi> In which was a Clauſe to this effect; <hi>That, whereas all Men ought to give God thanks, for putting it into the King's Heart, to condeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend to the Deſires of the</hi> Parliament, <hi>to do many things, which none of his Anceſtors would have conſented unto, as giving way to the</hi> Triennial Parliament, <hi>and granting many other things for the Good of his Subjects; yet notwithſtanding, ſome turbudent Spirits ſeem'd not to be ſatisfied, but WO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LD HAVE THE TOTAL S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>B<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VERSION OF THE GOVERNMENT: That</hi> therefore, <hi>the Army,</hi> being of good Comportment, though ill Paid, <hi>might be called up to attend the Perſon of the</hi> King <hi>and</hi> Parliament <hi>for their Security.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>the Deſign was, that the Army ſhould move towards</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, <hi>and ſpoil the Country all along as they went,</hi> to hinder the <hi>Scots</hi> from following them. That <hi>Oneal</hi> propoſed to Sir <hi>Jacob Aſhley,</hi> the making the <hi>Scots Neutral;</hi> but Sir <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaid, that they would lay him by the Heels, if he ſhould come to move ſuch a thing, for they would never break with the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Upon this Diſcovery, I muſt tell you, <hi>Doctor,</hi> the Hearts of honeſt Men were highly grieved to find <hi>the King in this Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy;</hi> and they began to deſpair of that Happineſs which they had hoped for by this <hi>Parliament:</hi> And the <hi>two Houſes</hi> doubting (<hi>as they well might</hi>) the <hi>King</hi>'s ſincere Affection to them, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering what great Diſturbance they had, and were like to meet with, in ſettling the State; and what great Disburſments of Money were to be made for payment of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scotiſh Armies:</hi> They unanimouſly moved the <hi>King</hi> to ſign a Bill for continuance of this preſent Parliament: That it ſhould never be diſſolved till both Houſes did Conſent and agree, that Publick Grievances were fully Redreſs'd; and <hi>his Plot</hi> made it unſafe for him to deny it: Beſides, as his extream Wants had forc'd him to call this Parliament, ſo the ſame neceſſitated him to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with them. For, <hi>this great Parliament</hi> (taught by woful ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, that he uſed Parliaments but to ſerve his Turn; and ſo when he had attained his Ends, their End enſued in a ſudden Diſſolution) <hi>would grant no Supply</hi> to relieve his Neceſſities, <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:97943:22"/>by his Conceſſion, <hi>they had obtained this Continuance, to redreſs the Peoples many and great Grievances:</hi> And they themſelves de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, That <hi>though there were in it ſome ſeeming Reſtraint of the Regal Power in diſſolving Parliaments; yet it was no taking that Power from the Crown, but ſuſpending the Execution of it for this Time and Occaſion only:</hi> Which was ſo neceſſary for the Publick Peace, that without it they could not have undertaken any of thoſe great Charges, but muſt have left both the <hi>Armies</hi> to Diſorder and Confuſion, and the whole Kingdom to Blood and Ruin; For to pay the <hi>Armies,</hi> Money was to be borrowed upon the <hi>Publick Faith,</hi> which had been nothing worth, if that <hi>Parliament</hi> could have been diſſolved at the <hi>King</hi>'s Pleaſure.</p>
            <p>And whereas <hi>(Sir)</hi> you expreſs your ſelf as aſtoniſhed at this gracious Compliance, and ſay, that <hi>no King ever granted the like before.</hi> I anſwer, 'Twas moſt evident, that <hi>no King before ever made ſo great a Neceſſity for a Parliament to inſist upon it.</hi> And beſides, <hi>in the Conſtitution of</hi> ENGLAND <hi>'s GOVERNMENT, it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the meaning of the LAW-GIVERS, that the King ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve Parliaments, whilſt the Great Affairs of the Kingdom were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending:</hi> And though <hi>Kings</hi> have uſed to do ſo, it was never the more lawful.</p>
            <p>Well, <hi>Doctor,</hi> I agree with you, that the <hi>King</hi> paſſed theſe Bills, very advantagious for the Subject; yet in none of them was he bereaved of any juſt, neceſſary or profitable Prerogative of the Crown. And I muſt tell you, becauſe you are ſilent, and for ought I know, ignorant in the Point, <hi>All this was not done for nought;</hi> for <hi>the King</hi> had out of the <hi>Subjects Purſe,</hi> in the firſt Year of this <hi>Parliament, ONE MILLION AND AN HALF OF MONEY:</hi> And yet ſome Men have the impudence to ſuggeſt, That <hi>the Parliament did nothing for him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To proceed;</p>
            <p>What's the next Article in the Impeachment againſt this <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 7</note> 
               <hi>Theſe Men, to ſhew their Gratitude for what was done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, drew up a Remonſtrance, wherein they made the moſt bitter Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections upon the King's former Government.—And which was ſo unmannerly, as well as falſe, that when it came to be debated in the whole Houſe, 'twas carried only by eleven Voices.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You are out again, <hi>moſt unlusky Doctor!</hi> My Authentick Fliſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian tells me a Tale quite contrary to yours; The <hi>Remonſtrance,</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:97943:23"/>or <hi>Declaration of the State of the Kingdom,</hi> was carried but <hi>by eight Voices,</hi> ſaith he; yet it contained <hi>plain</hi> (which I will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low you to call <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmannerly,</hi> but muſt not yield to be falſe) <hi>Truths,</hi> reciting the chief Grievances and Oppreſſions which the Nation had groaned under ſince the beginning of this King's Reign until that time, but with as much tendernefs of Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and reſpect to his Perſon, as ſo much Truth could poſſibly be uttered. Many of the <hi>Members</hi> who oppoſed this <hi>Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance,</hi> were of the ſame Opinion with thoſe who voted for it; but urged, that <hi>no Cure could be hoped for by it:</hi> That <hi>inſtead of directing a ſtubborn King</hi> for the future, <hi>it would teach him only to hate the Makers of it,</hi> as Upbraiders of his Crimes: And they held it fitter to win him by the ſweeter way of concealing his Errors, rather than by publiſhing them, to hazard the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking him. And now, <hi>Sir,</hi> not to contend it with you, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>little Majority,</hi> or <hi>great Minority,</hi> were the beſt <hi>Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians,</hi> and moſt in the right; <hi>you are certainly in the wrong,</hi> when you inſiſt, that this <hi>Remonſtrance was ſo ſtrennouſly oppoſed, bocauſe the Matter thereof was unmannerly and falſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You add,<note place="margin">Pag. 8.</note> That <hi>the King fairly anſwered this Remonſtrance, and vindicated himſelf from thoſe horrid Aſperſions wherewith they loaded him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not to be tranſported, <hi>Reverend Sir,</hi> to ſuch an indecency of replying, as is uſual in ſuch a Caſe as this; I barely tell you, that you talk looſly, and with no regard to Truth in what you now ſay, for I have the <hi>Royal Anſwer</hi> and <hi>Vindication</hi> now under my Eye, and do find that the <hi>King doth fairly anſwer the Remonſtrance,</hi> which ſets forth the many Grievances and high Oppreſſions of the People; in theſe only words, <hi>We ſhall IN FEW WORDS PASS over that part of the Narrative, wherein the Misfortunes of this Kingdom, from our firſt entring to the Crown, to the beginning of this Parliament, are remembred in ſo ſenſible Expreſſions.</hi> And to this <hi>he adds not one word</hi> in vindication of himſelf from thoſe Miſcarriages enumerated in the <hi>Parliament's Romonſtrance,</hi> which you call <hi>HORRID ASPERSIONS;</hi> but <hi>his Majeſty</hi> knew to be <hi>ſad Truths.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What follows next?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The King</hi> (you ſay) <hi>through T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LTS,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>and too-much coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced RIOTS, withdrew from</hi> Whitehall, <hi>being under apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:97943:23"/>of Affronts deſign'd to be offer'd to his Perſon, if not ſomething worſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Story</hi> of theſe <hi>pretended Tumults and Riots, (dear Doctor)</hi> is ſo intermixt with another, relating to the greateſt Violation of the Privileges of <hi>Parliament</hi> that ever was committed, that 'tis moſt neceſſary to talk of both together.</p>
            <p>About the beginning of <hi>January</hi> 1641, the <hi>King ſought no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than to begin a Quarrel;</hi> and to ſupport himſelf there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, he employed <hi>Emiſſaries</hi> to cajole the <hi>young Gentlemen</hi> of the <hi>Inns of Courts,</hi> to make offer of their Service to him, <hi>as a Guard of Defence;</hi> and divers of them to ingratiate themſelves, repaired to the Court, and were highly careſſed by the <hi>King and Queen:</hi> He at the ſame time ordered <hi>Canoneers</hi> and other <hi>Aſſiſtants,</hi> into the <hi>Tower,</hi> and removed the <hi>Lieutenant</hi> thereof: He <hi>fortified White-hall</hi> with Men and Munition in an unuſual manner. And about the ſame time, <hi>Colonel Lunsford</hi> and others gathered <hi>Troops of Horſe at</hi> Kingſton <hi>upon</hi> Thames, where the Magazine of Arms for that part of the County of <hi>Surrey</hi> lay. Matters on his part being thus prepared, upon the third of <hi>January</hi> (not only againſt the Priviledg of Parliament, but the common Liberty of every Subject) he commanded the <hi>Chambers, Studies and Trunks</hi> of the <hi>Lord Mandeville,</hi> a Member of the Houſe of Lords, (<hi>Grandfather</hi> to the preſent <hi>Noble Earl</hi> of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> who inherits as well the Vertnes as Honours of that great Patriot) and of <hi>Denzel Holles,</hi>Eſq; (ſince known by the name of <hi>the great Lord Holles</hi>) Sir <hi>Arthur Haſterig,</hi> Mr. <hi>J. Pym,</hi> Mr. <hi>John Hambden</hi> (<hi>Grandfather</hi> to that highly deſerving <hi>Gentleman,</hi> who at this day bears his Name, and in whom his Vertues do live and flouriſh) and Mr. <hi>William Strode,</hi> Members of Parliament,<note n="*" place="margin">Theſe were all Gentlemen of great Eſteem and Reputation in the Houſe. Two of them, Mr. <hi>Holles,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Strode,</hi> having be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuffered many Years of ſharp and harſh Impriſonment from the King, after the Diſſolution of the Parliament in the fourth Year of his Reign, for Matters done in Parliament, contrary to the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of that high Court.</note> 
               <hi>to be ſealed up.</hi> Upon the next day the <hi>King</hi> came with about 300 <hi>Souldiers, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> and others to the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons,</hi> armed with Swords, Piſtols and other Weapons; and there demanded the ſaid five Members to be delivered to him, upon a pretended Charge of <hi>High-Treaſon.</hi> His <hi>Followers</hi> at the ſame time thruſting away the <hi>Door-keepers</hi> and <hi>Attendants</hi> of the <hi>Houſe,</hi> held up their <hi>Swords,</hi> and ſome their <hi>Piſtols ready cock'd,</hi> ſaying, <hi>I am a good
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:97943:24"/>Marks-man, I can hit right I warrant you:</hi> Others of them ſaid, <hi>A Pox take the Houſe of Commons; a Pox of God confound them,</hi> and violently aſſaulted and by Force diſarmed ſome of the <hi>Servants</hi> of the <hi>Members,</hi> and ſaid, WHEN COMES THE WORD? and afterwards declared, that queſtionleſs, <hi>if the Word had been given, they ſhould have fallen upon the Houſe of Commons, and</hi> HAVE CUT ALL THEIR THROATS; which <hi>Doings</hi> the <hi>Commons</hi> declared, <hi>were</hi> A TRAITEROUS DESIGN <hi>againſt the King and Parliament,</hi> and that they could not ſit any longer without <hi>a ſufficient</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">They petitioned the <hi>King</hi> to allow them <hi>a Guard</hi> to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the <hi>Lord Chamberlain</hi> of his <hi>Houſhould,</hi> but could not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it.</note> 
               <hi>Guard,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they might confide; wherefore <hi>they adjour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> to the Tueſday following, having appinted <hi>a Committee</hi> to ſit in the mean time at <hi>Guildhall London,</hi> to conſider of all things that might concern the Good and Safety of the Kingdom, and <hi>the Relief of Ireland.</hi> [And I am to tell you, <hi>Doctor,</hi> that <hi>the great Lord Falkland</hi> was <hi>the fourth Perſon</hi> named to this great <hi>Committee.</hi>]</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Commons</hi> further <hi>declared, That they were ſo far from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecting any of their Members that ſhould in a due manner be proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted according to the Laws of the Kingdom, and the Rights and Priviledges of Parliament, for Treaſon, or any other Miſdemeanours, that none ſhould be more ready and willing than themſelves to bring them to a ſpeedy and due Trial.</hi> And upon the 15th of <hi>Janua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> they ordered the <hi>Attonrny-General,</hi> who had preferred the <hi>Articles of Treaſon</hi> againſt the <hi>Members,</hi> to bring in his Proof, and make them good, <hi>if he could:</hi> Whereupon the <hi>King</hi> ſent <hi>a Meſſage,</hi> that HE NOW FOUND CAUSE <hi>wholly to doſiſt from proceeding againſt them;</hi> and had commanded his <hi>Attourny-General</hi> to proceed no further therein, <hi>nor to produce nor diſcover any Proof</hi> concerning the matter. Alſo BOTH HOUSES pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioned the <hi>King</hi> for the <hi>ſpeedy proceeding</hi> againſt the <hi>accuſed Members IN A LEGAL WAY, whereby they might be brought to condign Puniſhment, if guilty; or diſcharged from ſo heavy an Accuſation, if innocent.</hi> The <hi>King</hi> giving <hi>an evaſive Anſwer</hi> to this Petition, the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> apply to him again, by <hi>a ſecond Petition,</hi> praying that the <hi>Parliament</hi> might be infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med before <hi>Friday</hi> then next enſuing, <hi>what Proof there is againſt them,</hi> that they may be called to <hi>a Legal Trial.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:97943:24"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A Petition of about two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Freeholders of <hi>Backingham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhirs</hi> was preſented to the King, ſetting forth that Mr. <hi>Hambden,</hi> Knight of their Shire, (a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman in high Eſteem with them and the whole Kingdom) was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of Treaſon; that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved it to be the Malice which his Zeal to his Majeſty's Service and the State had contracted in the Enemies to the King, the Church and the Common-wealth, had occaſioned this foul Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and they prayed that he and the other Members might enjoy the Priviledg of Parliament.
<p>The City of <hi>London</hi> alſo peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, that the Lord <hi>Mandeville</hi> and the five Members might not be reſtrained of Liberty, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded againſt otherwiſe than according to the Priviledges of Parliament.</p>
               </note> To which <hi>Petition</hi> the <hi>King anſwered,</hi> that, AS HE ONCE CONCEIVED, he had ground enough to accuſe them; ſo now, <hi>his Majeſty finds as good Cauſe wholly to deſert any Proſecution of them.</hi> Do you hear this, DOCTOR? If you ever had till now, you would not ſurely have aſſumed the Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to have ſaid as you do, (<hi>Pa.</hi> 11, 12.) That <hi>nothing leſs would ſatisfy the Parliament, than that he muſt be obliged, AS IT WERE, and IN EFFECT, to beg the Members Pardon for wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, with what he thought and CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LD BY GOOD EVIDENCE PROVE MATTER OF TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TH.</hi> Now I do (AS IT WERE) think that you ought (not only IN EFFECT, but <hi>in earneſt</hi>) to humble your ſelf to the <hi>Deſcendents</hi> of theſe <hi>honourable and never to be forgotten PATRIOTS,</hi> for the horrid Slander which you here lay on their great Names and Families: For, tho <hi>the King gave up the Cauſe,</hi> ſaying, that HE FOUND GOOD REASON <hi>wholly to deſiſt from proceeding againſt them;</hi> and at another time, that <hi>he found GOOD CA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE wholly to deſert any Proſecution of them:</hi> Yet, <hi>you forſooth,</hi> muſt keep up the wicked Clamour, and falſly inform this Generation, that his <hi>Majeſty, GOOD MAN, had pregnant Evidence</hi> to prove them guilty of <hi>Treaſon.</hi> But, to <hi>put you to ſhame if poſſible</hi> ('tis what you threatned me with, <hi>Reverend Sir!</hi>) I ſhall add a few words more upon this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. The <hi>Lords and Commons</hi> told the <hi>King</hi> in a <hi>third Petition,</hi> that <hi>notwithſtanding his Majeſty found good cauſe wholly to deſert any further Proſecution of the accuſed Members;</hi> yet they remained ſtill under that heavy Charge ſo imputed unto them. And that by two Acts of <hi>Parliament,</hi> viz. 37 and 38 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. it was enacted, That <hi>if any Perſon whatſoever make Suggeſtion to THE KING HIMSELF of any Crime committed by another, the ſame Perſon ought to be ſent with the Suggeſtion before the Chancellor or Keeper of the Great Seal, Treaſurer, or the great Countil; there to find Surety to purſue his Suggeſtion, which if he cann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t prove, he is to be impriſoned till he ſatisfy the Party accuſed of his Damages and Slander, and made Fine and Ranſom to the King.</hi> Wherefore the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:97943:25"/>
               <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> beſeeched the <hi>King,</hi> that he would be pleaſed to ſend the <hi>Perſon</hi> or <hi>Perſons,</hi> that in this Caſe made the <hi>Sugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions</hi> or <hi>Informations</hi> to him, againſt the ſaid <hi>Members;</hi> together with the <hi>Suggeſtions</hi> or <hi>Informations</hi> to the <hi>Parliament;</hi> that ſo ſuch Fruits <hi>of the ſaid good Laws may be had, as was intended by them; and the Rights and Priviledges of Parliament may be vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, WHICH OF RIGHT AND J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STICE O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GHT NOT TO BE DENIED.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding this <hi>Petition,</hi> no <hi>Authors</hi> nor <hi>Witneſſes</hi> were ever produced, to avow the heavy Charge and Accuſation of the noble Lord <hi>Mandeville</hi> and the five <hi>Members,</hi> till now, that fifty Years are elapſed; You, <hi>unhappy Doctor,</hi> are trumping up <hi>good Evidence,</hi> though for want of juſt Matter, which yet never came to light; the <hi>King</hi> let the Buſineſs fall of his own accord. And ſee now how neatly you have noos'd your ſelf; for, <hi>by your idle Dedication to their Majeſties,</hi> you have made this <hi>falſe Suggeſtion TO THE KING HIMSELF,</hi> and ſo are fallen into the Mercy of the <hi>noble Earl of Mancheſter,</hi> and become liable to the ſevere Penalties in the <hi>Statutes</hi> of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Third.</p>
            <p>To diſpatch this Head; Was it not a Crime againſt the Law of Nature, againſt the Rules of Juſtice; that innocent Men ſhould be charged with ſo great an Offence as Treaſon, in the Face of the higheſt Judicature in the Kingdom, without Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, without any poſſibility of Reparation, even in point of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency? Such was the Caſe of theſe great Men; for <hi>the King denied to diſcover their Accuſers, and yet would not paſs a Bill for their Diſcharge, unleſs in the Narration they would deſert the avow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their own Innocency.</hi> Nay, was it not <hi>an Act of Tyranny</hi> beyond Parallel? <hi>He accuſed them, and yet would produce no Witneſs: he confeſs'd them clear in his own Judgment, yet they muſt not profeſs their own Innocency, for fear of wounding his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We will proceed now, <hi>Reverend Doctor,</hi> to what remains to be ſaid, about the <hi>terrifying Tumults and Riots</hi> which frighted his <hi>Majeſty</hi> from <hi>VVhitehall.</hi> You ſaid, that <hi>he withdrew from thence through Tumults, and too much countenanc'd Riots, being under ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of Affronts, deſign'd to be offer'd to his Perſon, IF NOT SOMETHING WORSE.</hi> When you return me an Anſwer to this Letter, <hi>dear Sir,</hi> you will infinitely oblige me, if you will
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:97943:25"/>tell me, in plain Engliſh, what you intend by <hi>SOMETHING WORSE,</hi> than that the <hi>Mob</hi> would affront his Majeſty's Royal Perſon? For, according to my preſent Apprehenſion, you ſeem to inſinuate, that HE ABDICATED <hi>WHITEHALL,</hi> under a dread, that theſe wicked <hi>Rioters</hi> would have forced his COMFOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TABLE IMPORTANCE, or perpretrated ſome Act ſo highly Villanous, that you could not find a Name for it. For the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, till I have better Light herein, I will lay before you my Thoughts in this Caſe: In the doing whereof, we muſt examine how things ſtood at that time, whereby 'twill be ſeen, <hi>whether there were any ſuch Tumules;</hi> and if there were, <hi>whether the King himſelf did not cauſe them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He had tempted the ENGLISH ARMY, with no leſs Reward than the Spoil of the City of</hi> LONDON, <hi>to come up and deſtroy the PAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAMENT; He had, in an unexcuſable and hoſtile manner, made a moſt high Invaſion upon the Priviledges of BOTH HO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SES:</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon many <hi>Citizens, unarmed,</hi> reſorted to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> to preſent their <hi>Petitions,</hi> and expreſs their ſtedfaſtneſs to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> whoſe Lives and Safeties, by more than ſlight Rumours, they doubted to be in Danger; the <hi>King</hi> having fortified <hi>VVhitehall,</hi> and entertained Armed Men, not a few, planted them at the<note n="*" place="margin">The firſt Blood that was drawn in this Cauſe, was in that very place where the King's own Blood was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards ſhed.</note> 
               <hi>Gate of his Palace,</hi> where they reviled, menaced, and with drawn Swords actually wounded many of the <hi>Citizens,</hi> as they paſſed by in a peaceable manner, whereof ſome died. Nay, they went farther, and were come to that height of Boldneſs, as to give out inſolent and menacing Speeches againſt the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> it ſelf, and to <hi>imbrue their Hands</hi> in the Blood of the <hi>King's Subjects</hi> in <hi>VVeſtminſter-Hall,</hi> and at the Doors of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> as well as at his own Gate. And when the <hi>Parliament</hi> and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple complained, and demanded Juſtice for thoſe Aſſaults,<note place="margin">1 K. 21, 19.</note> he juſtifyed and abetted his own Crew in what they did.</p>
            <p>Now, the paſſing by of a multitude of the <hi>King's</hi> Subjects, <hi>armed with no other VVeapons than Petitions,</hi> could neither be juſtly called <hi>Tumults,</hi> nor could the <hi>Parliament</hi> have forbid them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out breach of the Peoples Freedom: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>narmed Petitioners ſurely could not be formidable to any:</hi> And I muſt remember you, <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor,</hi> that a very ſhort time before his <hi>Majeſty</hi> pretended to dread theſe tumultuary Citizens, <hi>The City entertained, feaſted, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted him to</hi> Whitehall, <hi>with at pompous Solemnity, and coſtly Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of Love and Duty, as ever had been known.</hi> Nay, did he
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:97943:26"/>not the very next day, after his irruption in the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, than which nothing had more exaſperated the People, <hi>go in his Coach unguarded into the City?</hi> Did he receive the leaſt Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front, much leſs Violence in any of the Streets, but rather hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Demeanours and Supplications? He knew the People ſo full of Awe and Reverence to his Perſon, as to commit himſelf ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle amongſt the thickeſt of them, at a time when he had moſt provoked them: This ſhews, beyond doubting, that <hi>all his fear of Tumults, was but a meer Pretence and Occaſion taken, of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved abſence from the Parliament, that he might turn his Slaſhing at the Court-gate, to Slaughtering in the Field.</hi> Well,</p>
            <p>The <hi>King</hi> retires firſt to <hi>Hampton-Court,</hi> commanding his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, who were Members of Parliament, to leave their Service there, and to give their Attendance upon his Perſon. Shortly after, <hi>the Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EEN paſſes into</hi> Holland, <hi>carrying with her all, or the greateſt part of the Crown-Jewels; which ſhe immediately pawn'd, and with the Money bought Arms and Ammunition for the VVar, which was not yet begun.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I had almoſt forgot my ſelf, <hi>Reverend Sir,</hi> I muſt attend to what you ſay in the Caſe;<note place="margin">Pag. 8.</note> 'Tis this, I ſee; <hi>The King,</hi> though withdrawn, yet <hi>ceaſes not to call upon the Parliament to conſider the Nation's Good, and the ſettling it upon ſuch Foundations, as neither the Monarch might invade the juſt Rights of the People, nor the People incroach upon the Rights of his Crown and Dignity.</hi> Having ſaid this, you intimate that he told them ſomething upon their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting <hi>Petitions</hi> to him at <hi>Theobalds</hi> and <hi>New-market.</hi> Then it ſeems that <hi>they called upon him likewiſe,</hi> and 'tis fit my Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſhould know for what, ſeeing you do maliciouſly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold it.</p>
            <p>Upon the 1ſt of <hi>March</hi> 1641, BOTH HOUSES CALLED UPON HIS MAJESTY, by their <hi>Petition</hi> preſented at <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balds; That for the diſpatch of the great Affairs of the Kingdom, the Safety of his Perſon, the Protection and Comfort of his Subjects, he would be pleaſed to continue his Abode near the Parliament, and not to withdraw himſelf to any the remoter Parts; which if he ſhould do, muſt needs be a cauſe of great Danger and Diſtraction: And they prayed him to accept this humble Counſel, as the Effect of that Duty and Allegiance which they owed unto him, and which would not ſuffer them to admit of any Thoughts, Intentions or Endeavours, but ſuch as were neceſſary and advantagious for his Majeſties Greatneſs and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:97943:26"/>and the Safety and Proſperity of the Kingdom:</hi> Expreſſions ſurely, that do not in the leaſt ſavour of that <hi>Sedition</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion,</hi> with which at this time, by you, <hi>Doctor,</hi> and many other <hi>WICKED Clergy-men,</hi> the Memory of this great Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is charged.</p>
            <p>The <hi>King</hi> being deaf to the importunate Supplication of the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> for his Return: They again <hi>called upon him</hi> more earneſtly, ſending after him <hi>a Declaration</hi> to <hi>Newmarket,</hi> by the <hi>Earles</hi> of <hi>Pembroke</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>a Committee</hi> of the <hi>Commons,</hi> wherein they laid before him the Cauſes of their own <hi>Fears and Jealouſies</hi> in theſe Particulars.</p>
            <q rend="margQuotes">
               <list>
                  <item>1. That <hi>the deſign of altering Religion</hi> had been potently carried on by thoſe in greateſt Authority about him; <hi>the Queen's Agent at</hi> Rome, <hi>the Pope's Nuncio here,</hi> are not only Evidences of this Deſign, but <hi>have been great Actors in it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. That <hi>the War with</hi> Scotland <hi>was procured to make way for this Intent,</hi> and chiefly <hi>fomented by the Papiſts, and other Popiſhly affected,</hi> whereof we have many Evidences.</item>
                  <item>3. That <hi>the Rebellion in</hi> Ireland <hi>was framed and contrived here in</hi> England; and that <hi>the Engliſh Papiſts ſhould have riſen about the ſame time,</hi> we have ſeveral Teſtimonies, <hi>&amp;c. The Iriſh Rebels affirm, that they do nothing but by Authority from the King; they call themſelves the Queen</hi>'s <hi>Army:</hi> The Booty which they take from the Engliſh, they mark with the Queen's mark; and it is proved that <hi>their purpoſe was to come to</hi> England, <hi>after they had done in</hi> Ireland.</item>
                  <item>4. The labouring to infuſe into your Majeſty's Subjects an evil Opinion of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and other Symptoms of a Diſpoſition of raiſing Arms, and dividing your People by a <hi>Civil War,</hi> in which Combuſtion <hi>Ireland</hi> muſt needs be loſt, and this Kingdom miſerably waſted and conſumed, if not wholly ruined and deſtroyed.</item>
                  <item>5. That your <hi>Majeſty</hi> ſent away the <hi>Lord Digby</hi> by your own Warrant beyond the Sea, after a Vote had paſſed in the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> declaring, that he had appeared in a Warlike manner at <hi>Kingſton upon Thames,</hi> to the Terror of your Majeſty's good Subjects; that he being ſo got beyond Sea, he vented his traiterous Conceptions, <hi>That your Majeſty ſhould declare your ſelf, and retire to a place of Strength;</hi> and intimated ſome Service which he might do in thoſe Parts;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:97943:27"/>whereby in probability, he intended the procuring of ſome Foreign Force to ſtrengthen your Majeſty, in that Condition into which he would have brought you; which malicious Counſel we have great Cauſe to doubt, made too deep an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion in your Majeſty, CONSIDERING THE COURSE YOU ARE PLEASED TO TAKE, OF ABSENTING YOUR SELF FROM YOUR PARLIAMENT, <hi>and carrying the Prince with you, which ſeems to expreſs a purpoſe in your Majeſty to keep your ſelf in a readineſs for the acting of it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. <hi>The manifold Advertiſements</hi> which we have had <hi>from Rome, Venice, Paris,</hi> and other parts, <hi>that they ſtill expect that your Majeſty has ſome great Deſign in hand, for the altering of Religion,</hi> the breaking the Neck of your Parliament, and that you will yet find means to compaſs that Deſign: That <hi>the Pope's Nuncio hath ſollicited the Kings of</hi> France <hi>and</hi> Spain <hi>to lend your Majeſty</hi> 4000 <hi>Men apiece,</hi> to help to maintain your Royalty againſt the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Theſe are ſome of the grounds of our <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Jealouſies,</hi> which made us ſo earneſtly to implore your Royal Authority and Protection for our Defence and Security in all the ways of Humility and Submiſſion, which being denied by your Majeſty, <hi>We do with Sorrow apply our ſelves to the uſe of that</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">The Militia.</note> 
                  <hi>Power, which, by the Fundamental Laws of this Kingdom, reſides in us; yet ſtill reſolving to keep our ſelves within the Bounds of Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and Allegiance to your Sacred Perſon and your Crown.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>as to the Fears and Jealouſies</hi> which his Majeſty ſeemed to have entertained of them; <hi>The Lords and Commons thus anſwered:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We have, according to your Majeſty's Deſires, laid our Hands upon our Hearts; we have ask'd our ſelves in the ſtricteſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of our Conſciences, we have ſearch'd our Affections, our Thoughts; conſidered our Actions, and can find none that can give your Majeſty and juſt occaſion to abſent your ſelf from</hi> Whitehall <hi>and the Parliament;</hi> but that you may with more Honour and Safety continue there, than in any other place.</p>
               <p>Your Majeſty lays a general Charge upon us: if you will be graciouſly pleaſed to let us know the Particulars, we ſhall give a clear and ſatisfactory Anſwer. But <hi>what hope can we have of ever giving your Majeſty Satisfaction, when thoſe Particulars which you have been made believe were true; yet being produced and made
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:97943:27"/>known to us, appeared to be falſe;</hi> and your Majeſty notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, will neither puniſh nor produce the Authors; but go on to contract new Jealouſies and Fears, upon general and uncertain grounds, affording us no means or poſſibility of particular Anſwer, to the clearing of our ſelves?</p>
               <p>WE BESEECH YOUR MAJESTY TO CONSIDER IN WHAT STATE YOU ARE, <hi>how eaſy and fair a way you have to Happineſs, Honour and Greatneſs, Plenty and Security; if you will join with the Parliament in the Defence of the Religion and publick Good of the Kingdom;</hi> THIS IS ALL WE EXPECT FROM YOU; and <hi>for this we return to you our Lives, Fortunes</hi> and utmoſt Eadeavours to ſupport your Majeſty, your juſt Soveraignty and Power over us; but IT IS NOT WORDS THAT CAN SECURE US in theſe our humble Deſires: <hi>We cannot but</hi> too well and ſorrowfully <hi>remember what</hi> GRACIOUS MESSAGES <hi>we had from you this Summer, when</hi> WITH YOUR PRIVITY, <hi>the bringing up the Army was in Agitation: We cannot but</hi> with the like Affections, <hi>recal to our Minds, how not two days before your own coming to the Commons Houſe, you ſent a</hi> GRACIOUS MESSAGE, <hi>that you would always have care of their Priviledges, as of your own Prerogative; of the Safety of their Perſons, as of your own Children;</hi> that which we expect, which will give us aſſurance, that you have <hi>no thought but of Peace and Juſtice</hi> to your People, muſt be ſome real Effect of your Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to them, in granting thoſe things which <hi>the preſent Neceſſity</hi> of the Kingdom do inforce us to deſire: And that you will be graciouſly pleaſed to put from you thoſe <hi>miſchievous Counſellors,</hi> which have cauſed all theſe Dangers and Diſtractions, and to <hi>continue your own Reſidence and the Princes, near</hi> London <hi>and the Parliament,</hi> which we hope will be a happy beginning of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment and Confidence betwixt your Majeſty and your People; and be followed with many ſucceeding Bleſſings of Honour and Greatneſs to your Majeſty, and of Security and Proſperity to them.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Theſe are brief Heads, <hi>good Doctor,</hi> of <hi>the Declaration</hi> which you mention to be read to the King at <hi>Newmarket;</hi> and you, with very little regard to his Majeſty's Honour, do affirm, that after the hearing this <hi>Declaration</hi> read, <hi>he expoſtulated</hi> in theſe words: <hi>What would you have? Have I violated your Laws?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 8.</note> Were you ſo well read in the Hiſtory of that Day, as you pretend to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:97943:28"/>be, this his ſtrong <hi>Expoſtulation</hi> with the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> would never have found room in your <hi>Defence</hi> of the <hi>King;</hi> for his high violation of the Laws were too well known to the whole World, to be denied; and you, <hi>his Majeſty's Defender,</hi> would never have revived the thing, had you remembred the ſhort, but moſt pertinent <hi>Reply</hi> which <hi>both Houſes</hi> made thereto, in theſe words; <hi>We are heartily ſorry we have ſuch plentiful mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an Anſwer to that Queſtion,</hi> HAVE I VIOLATED YOUR LAWS?</p>
            <p>You proceed,<note place="margin">Pag. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Sir,</hi> ſaying, That <hi>the Applications from the two Houſes at this time, were for NOTHING LESS than the MI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LITIA.</hi> You are out again, <hi>Doctor,</hi> and would I uſe the <hi>Royal Language,</hi> wherewith the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Holland</hi> was intterrupted by the <hi>King</hi> in reading <hi>the Declaration</hi> to him at <hi>New-market,</hi> I might, with more Truth than he did ſay, <hi>THAT'S FALSE, THAT'S A LIE:</hi> For in recounting ſome Particulars of the <hi>Declaration</hi> I have demonſtrated, that <hi>their Application was alſo for other and leſs Matters than the Militia;</hi> they humbly <hi>petitioned him to put away his wicked Counſellors, and to return to his Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You add; That <hi>the King continuing ſtedfaſt to his Reſolution, and DEAF TO ALL THEIR IMPORI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NITIES,</hi> [The want of Ears, I muſt tell you, <hi>Reverend Sir,</hi> coſt him his Head at laſt] <hi>telling them, That he would nor part with his Militia for an Hour.</hi> I muſt help you a little in this part of the Story too; The <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Pembrook</hi> ask'd him, <hi>Whether the Militia might not be granted, as was deſired by the Parliament for a time?</hi> HIS MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>JESTY SWORE, BY GOD, NOT FOR AN HOUR. This ſhews him a little more <hi>ſtubbornly ſtedfaſt</hi> than you would tell the World; however, <hi>you told too much</hi> in this place, or <hi>his Majeſty</hi> reſolved <hi>and ſwore too faſt;</hi> for afterwards you ſay, That at the <hi>Treaty</hi> at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridg,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 20.</note> 
               <hi>He conſented that the Militia, for three Years, ſhould be in the Hands of twenty Commiſſioners,</hi> the one half to be nominated by the <hi>two Houſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your next words are theſe, THE MILITIA THEY MUST HAVE,<note place="margin">Pag. 9.</note> OR THE NATION IS UNDONE.</p>
            <p>The State of the Kingdom at that Day conſidered, there ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fell from your Pen a greater Truth than what you have here delivered; for, beſides the particular Inſtances which I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready given you of the <hi>King's</hi> Invaſion of the <hi>Priviledges</hi> of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> of the <hi>Rights</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> and of <hi>his Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ations
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:97943:28"/>for War</hi> againſt them; I muſt here inform you, that in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Year 1641, a time when the <hi>King</hi> was, in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, tranſacting Matters amicably with the two Houſes; and we ſeemed to be in a deep Peace; a time when <hi>he declared, that he had received no other carriage from his Parliament, than what he profeſſed himſelf ſatisfied with; and that if the Bills he had paſt, were again to be offered, he ſhould chearfully and readily aſſent unto them;</hi> even then <hi>he diſpatched away Letters,</hi> and an <hi>Agent</hi> to the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Denmark,</hi> complaining of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and <hi>asking Supplies</hi> from thence, <hi>AD PROP<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LSANDOS HOSTES,</hi> you know the Engliſh of that is, <hi>to ſubdue his Enemies;</hi> and declared himſelf in theſe words, <note place="margin">☜</note>
               <hi>ad alia Conſilia Animum convertendum duximus; VVe reſolve to betake our ſelf to new Counſels;</hi> the very words he uſed to the <hi>Parliament</hi> in the Year 1628.</p>
            <p>Further, upon the Diſcovery of <hi>his Plot to bring up the Engliſh Army againſt the Parliament,</hi> he turned to the <hi>Scotiſh Army,</hi> then at <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> and baited his <hi>Temptation</hi> with a rich Reward, <hi>not only to have</hi> 300000 l. <hi>in hand, and the Spoil of</hi> London, <hi>but four Northern Counties</hi> to be made <hi>Scotiſh.</hi> Moreover, to encourage them to joyn with him, <hi>he declared</hi> to them, that <hi>he was to have Money and Horſe from</hi> Denmark, and that <hi>he would made</hi> York <hi>the place of his Reſidence,</hi> for the better Accommodation of both Nations, or <hi>fuller Revenge upon</hi> London: He alſo gathered Men in <hi>London,</hi> under pretence of raiſing <hi>Forces</hi> for <hi>Portugal, who were to poſſeſs themſelves of the Tower.</hi> The <hi>Queen</hi> in Holland <hi>was buying Arms,</hi> and his <hi>Majeſty</hi> had actually raiſed Forces in divers Counties: The <hi>Parliament</hi> was all this time <hi>petitioning</hi> in Peace: And for the Reaſons now aſſigned, amongſt many others, <hi>They humbly beſought him, that he would be pleaſed to put the Tower of</hi> London <hi>and the Militia into the hands of ſuch Perſons as ſhould be recommended to him by both Houſes of Parliament.</hi> The <hi>King</hi> ſeemed to comply herein, and by <hi>his Anſwer promiſed</hi> them, <hi>that the Militia ſhould be put into ſuch hands as they ſhould approve of, or recommend to him:</hi> hereupon <hi>both Houſes</hi> nominated Perſons of the greateſt Honour, as fit for that Truſt; to give you the Names of ſome of them, the Earls of <hi>Holland, Rutland, Bedford, Bullingbrook, Salisbury, Warwick, Pem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brook, Leiceſter, Stamford, Eſſex, Clare, Northumberland, Lincoln, Suffolk,</hi> &amp;c. Lords, <hi>Paget, North, Strange, Roberts, Grey</hi> of <hi>Werk, Chandois, Dacres, Mandeville, Wharton, Spencer, Brook,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:97943:29"/>Herbert, Fielding, Littleton,</hi> Lord Keeper, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Men eminent in all Quallifications of Honour and Sufficiency were recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for ſeveral <hi>Counties,</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> was deſired to agree thereunto, <hi>as he had promiſed;</hi> upon his delaying to give a ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory Anſwer, they again petition him to give ſuch <hi>an Anſwer as might raiſe in them a Confidence that they ſhould not be expoſed to the Practices of thoſe who thirſt after the Ruin of the Kingdom, and the kindling that Combuſtion in</hi> England <hi>which they had effected in</hi> Ireland: <hi>That nothing could enable them to ſuppreſs THE RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BELLION IN</hi> IRELAND, <hi>and ſecure</hi> England, <hi>but the granting of their humble Petition;</hi> which they find ſo abſolutely neceſſary for the preſervation of the King and Common-wealth, that <hi>the Laws of God and Man injoyn them to ſee it put in Execution.</hi> They again by <hi>a Petition</hi> preſented at <hi>Theobalds, March</hi> 1, 1641. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated him, that he would at laſt be pleaſed to grant their <hi>neceſſary Petition</hi> concerning the <hi>Militia,</hi> and declared, that <hi>if he refuſed to do it in theſe times of Diſtraction, they muſt be inforced to diſpoſe of it for the Safety of the Kingdom, in ſuch manner as had been propounded to his Majeſty.</hi> They followed him with the ſame <hi>humble Supplication,</hi> in his ſeveral Removes to <hi>York;</hi> but HE HAVING ABDICATED <hi>the Parliament,</hi> and BEING DEAF (as you moſt ingenuouſly confeſs) TO ALL THEIR IMPORTUNITIES; they declared, that <hi>there had been of late a moſt deſperate Deſign upon the Houſe of Commons, which they had juſt cauſe to believe was an Effect of the BLOODY CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NSELS of PAPISTS, and other ill-affected Perſons, who had already raiſed A REBELLION IN</hi> IRELAND, <hi>and by reaſon of many Diſcoveries, they could not but fear they would proceed, not only to ſtir up the like REBELLION AND INS<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RRECTION in this Kingdom,</hi> but alſo to back them with <hi>Forces from abroad;</hi> and thereupon <hi>both Houſes</hi> made <hi>an Ordinance</hi> for the <hi>ordering the Militia of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Wales; there appearing an urgent and inevitable Neceſſity for putting his Majeſty's Subjects in a Poſture of Defence for the Safeguard of both his Majeſty and the People. And they RESOLVED, <hi>that in this caſe of extream Danger, and of his Majeſty's refuſal, the Ordinance agreed to by both Houſes for the Militia, doth oblige the People, and O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GHT TO BE OBEYED by the Fundamental Eaws of this Kingdom.</hi> They further about that time, RESOLVED, <hi>That the King's Abſence ſo far remote from his Parliament, was not only an Obſtruction, but MIGHT BE A DESTR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CTION to the Affairs of</hi> Ireland.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:97943:29"/>
            <p>And now, <hi>Sir,</hi> having laid before you the Grounds of the <hi>Parliament</hi>'s proceeding as they did, in the buſineſs of the <hi>Militia:</hi> I will ſhew you how much higher <hi>our Fore-fathers</hi> went than we did in 1641. They were of that Courage and Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Zeal to Juſtice, and their Native Liberty, againſt the proud Contempt and Miſ-rule of their <hi>Kings;</hi> that when <hi>RICHARD</hi> the Second departed but from a <hi>Committee</hi> of <hi>Lords,</hi> who ſat preparing Matters for the <hi>Parliament, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired the King,</hi> then withdrawn no further off than the <hi>Tower, to come to Weſtminſter,</hi> WHICH HE REFUSING, THEY FLATLY TOLD HIM, THAT UNLESS HE CAME, THEY WOULD CHOOSE ANOTHER KING. So high a Crime it was accounted then, for a <hi>King</hi> to abſent himſelf; much leſs would they have ſuffered, that a <hi>King</hi> ſhould leave his Regal Station, and the whole Kingdom, bleeding to Death of thoſe Wounds which his own unskilful and perverſe Government had made. Yet, WE IN OUR DAY <hi>went not their length;</hi> THE KING HAD ABDICATED; <hi>our Religion, Lives and Liberties were threatned with moſt imminent Danger, from inteſtine Enemies and Foreign Force; WE only made a moſt neceſſary Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that our own Swords ſhould not be imployed to the Deſtruction of all that was dear unto us.</hi> And pray, <hi>what harm, what Rebellion</hi> was there in all this?</p>
            <p>The next thing we meet with in <hi>your Defence,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 10.</note> REVEREND DOCTOR, is this; <hi>Before the War actually broke out, the King was gone to</hi> York, <hi>hoping thereby to COOL THE HEATS that were AT</hi> LONDON, <hi>and in ſome little time TO BE INVITED thither, to live with more Honour and Safety than he did before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>King</hi> in truth went to <hi>York</hi> in a high Chafe, hoping for ſomething beyond and contrary to what you intimate; 'twas in hopes that to enable himſelf the better for that diſmal War, which he had reſolved upon, he might poſſeſs himſelf of <hi>Hull,</hi> a Town of great Strength, and moſt advantagiouſly ſituated, both for Sea and Land Affairs; and which was at that time <hi>the Magazine</hi> of all the Arms which he had bought with Money moſt illegally extorted from his Subjects, to uſe in a cauſleſs and moſt unjuſt <hi>Civil War</hi> againſt his <hi>Subjects</hi> of <hi>Scotland:</hi> Did he hope for <hi>an Invitation</hi> back to <hi>London?</hi> Why, he had that very often made to him, in a moſt humble and earneſt manner; in particular, by <hi>a Petition</hi> of the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> preſented
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:97943:30"/>to him at <hi>York,</hi> the 26th of <hi>March,</hi> 1642. <hi>They humbly adviſed and beſeeched him, that FOR THE RECOVERY OF</hi> IRELAND, <hi>and ſecuring this Kingdom, he would be graciouſly pleaſed, with all convenient ſpeed, to return to</hi> London, <hi>and to cloſe with the Counſel of his Parliament; where he ſhould find their dutiful Affections and Endeavours ready to attend him, with ſuch Entertainment, as ſhould not only give him juſt cauſe of Security in their Faithfulneſs; but other manifold Evidences of their Intentions and Endeavours to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance his Majeſty's Service, Honour, and Contentment, and to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh it upon the ſure Foundation of the Peace and Proſperity of his Kingdoms.</hi> EXPRESSIONS, ſurely <hi>Doctor,</hi> THAT DO NOT IN THE LEAST SAVOUR OF REBELLION AND TREASON. The deaf <hi>King,</hi> inſtead of hearkning to this dutiful <hi>Petition</hi> and <hi>Invitation, ſummoned the Gentry of that County to attend him at</hi> York, where he made the moſt bitter Invectives againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and ſtirred them up to raiſe <hi>Horſe</hi> and <hi>Foot</hi> for his Service: <hi>His Majeſty</hi> found <hi>but ſix Gentlemen</hi> to comply with his Demand of raiſing Men, tho made under the pretence of <hi>a Guard. The greater part of the Gentlemen, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers thouſands of Freeholders,</hi> gave him an Anſwer under their hands to this effect, <hi>We humbly beſeech your Majeſty to impart the grounds of your Fears and Jealouſies to your High Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (OF WHOSE MOST LOYAL CARE AND AFFECTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON TO YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R MAJESTY'S HONO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R AND SAFETY WE ARE MOST CONFIDENT) and WHATSOEVER SHALL BE ADVISED BY YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R GREAT CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NCIL, we ſhall moſt willingly imbrace, and give our Concurrence and Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to it, as ſhall become us.—And WE ARE MOST ASS<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RED, that your Royal Perſon ſhall be ſecure in the general Fidelity of your Subjects of this County without any extraordinary</hi> GUARD.</p>
            <p>The <hi>King</hi> was preſented the next day with <hi>a Petition</hi> from <hi>many thouſands,</hi> who juſtly ſtiled themſelves <hi>peaceably affected Subjects in the County of</hi> York, in which they ſpeak thus:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That many of them in their late Deſires of petitioning your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, were denied Acceſs, kept back with Violence, and affronted by ſome who had Dependance on your Majeſty; and were threatned, that WHEN YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R MAJESTY'S ARMY SHO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LD BE ON FOOT, thoſe ſhould be firſt pillaged that refuſed to ſubſcribe to the raiſing of Forces; which we humbly conceive are POSITIVELY
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:97943:30"/>CONTRARY TO YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R MAJESTY'S OWN EXPRES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIONS,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We humbly ſupplicate your Majeſty, to caſt your Eye upon the preſent State of this your Kingdom.—We are confident that no ſo abſolute and hearty Obſervance to your Majeſty's juſt Commands can be demoſtrated, as what your Majeſty in Parliament ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare; which IF IT BECOME DIVIDED, (as God forbid) our Hearts even tremble to conſider the Dangers and Diminution of the Honour and Safety your Majeſty's Poſterity and Kingdoms will unavoidably be put upon: Since it is clear to every <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that IT IS NOT A DIVIDED PART OF ONE OR SEVERAL CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NTIES THAT can afford that Honour and Safety to your Majeſty, AS THE WHOLE KINGDOM, WHICH YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> MAT COMMAND, no ground of Fear or Danger remaining, if a good Confidence were begot betwixt your Majeſty and your Parliament; whoſe grave and loyal Counſels are, we humbly conceive, the viſible way, under God, to put a ſpeedy end to the Troubles of</hi> Ireland, <hi>and eſtabliſh your Throne in Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>We moſt humbly ſupplicate, that we may repreſent our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfitneſs to become Judges betwixt your Majeſty and Parliament, in any thing, or diſpute the Authority of either; which we humbly conceive do fortify each other—We ſhall be ready to maintain your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's juſt Rights, the Priviledges and Power of Parliaments, and the lawful Liberties of the Subjects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have now ſhown <hi>you, Doctor,</hi> that <hi>the King wanted not Invitations to return and live in Honour and Safety at</hi> London: The <hi>Parliament</hi> importunately preſs'd it, the <hi>Gentlemen and Freeholders of York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> humbly ſupplicated it: But nothing is more certain, than that inſtead of hoping <hi>to cool the Heats</hi> at <hi>London,</hi> by retiring to <hi>York;</hi> 'twas his ſole purpoſe and intention to put that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and <hi>the whole Kingdom into a Flame,</hi> as he quickly did; and purſuant to that Deſign, having rejected with Scorn, the <hi>Petitions</hi> I have mentioned, he perſiſted in his former way of raiſing Forces, and made <hi>Proclamation,</hi> requiring all <hi>Gentlemen</hi> and others of that County to attend him in Arms.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Lords and Commons</hi> wiſely foreſeeing the impending Miſchief, and obſerving the Clouds to gather ſo faſt, and threaten a Storm, they as wiſely endeavoured to prevent it; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore paſſed a <hi>Vote, May</hi> 20, 1642, That <hi>it appears the King</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:97943:31"/>(ſeduced by wicked Counſel) <hi>intends to make War againſt the Parliament; who in all their Conſultations and Actions, have propoſed no other end unto themſelves, but the Care of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and the performance of all Duty and Loyalty to his Perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That whenſoever the King maketh War upon the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, it is a Breach of the Truſt repoſed in him by his People, contrary to his Oath, and tending to the Diſſolution of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That whoſoever ſhall ſerve, or aſſiſt him in ſuch War, are Traitors by the Fundamental Laws of this Kingdom, and have been ſo adjudged by two Acts of Parliament, and ought to ſuffer as Traitors,</hi> 11 Rich. 2. 1 Hen. 4.</p>
            <p>But I muſt hear you,<note place="margin">Pag. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Sir,</hi> upon this Point of <hi>the firſt beginning</hi> of the unnatural and bloody War; you ſuggeſt that <hi>he was forced to raiſe an Army, which was after the Parliament had voted a Neceſſity of a War with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Will you never leave your L—<hi>Doctor? The Parliament did not vote a neceſſity of a War: They</hi> indeed <hi>voted,</hi> as I told you but now, <hi>That it appeared that the King intended to make War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them;</hi> and it was near two Months afterwards, <hi>viz.</hi> the 12th of <hi>July</hi> 1642, that the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> (finding his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty to perſiſt in that Intention) <hi>voted, that an Army ſhould be forthwith raiſed for the Safety of the King's Perſon, Defence of both Houſes of Parliament, and preſerving of the true Religion, the Laws, Liberty, and the Peace of the Kingdom. That the Earl of</hi> Eſſex <hi>ſhould be General, and that they will live and die with him in this Cauſe; and that the Earl of</hi> Bedford <hi>ſhould be General of the Horſe.</hi> Nevertheleſs, they reſolved that a <hi>Petition</hi> ſhould be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> by the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Holland,</hi> Sir <hi>John Holland,</hi> and Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> to move the King to a good Accord with his Parliament, to prevent <hi>a Civil War,</hi> which was to the effect following.</p>
            <q rend="margQuotes">
               <p>Although, We <hi>your Majeſty's moſt humble and faithful Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,</hi> the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> aſſembled in <hi>Parliament,</hi> have been very unhappy in many <hi>former Petitions</hi> to your <hi>Majeſty;</hi> and with much Sorrow do perceive that your <hi>Majeſty, incenſed by many falſe Calumnies and Slanders,</hi> doth continue to raiſe Forces againſt us, and to make great Preparations for War, both in the Kingdom and from beyond the Seas; yet ſuch is our earneſt deſire of diſcharging our Duty to your Majeſty and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:97943:31"/>to preſerve the Peace thereof, and to prevent the Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Civil War: That notwithſtanding we hold our ſelves bound to uſe all the Means and Power, which by the Laws and Conſtitutions of this Kingdom we are truſted with, for De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and Protection thereof, and of the Subjects from Force and Violence; We do in this our humble and loyal Petition, proſtrate our ſelves at your Majeſty's Feet, beſeeching that you will forbear and remove all Preparations and Actions of War. — That <hi>you will come nearer to your Parliament,</hi> and hearken to their faithful Advice and humble Petitions, which ſhall only tend to the Defence and Advancement of Religion, your own Royal Honour and Safety, the preſervation of our Laws and Liberties: And <hi>we have been, and ever ſhall be careful to prevent and puniſh all Tumults and ſeditious Actings, Speeches and Writings,</hi> which may give your Majeſty juſt cauſe of Diſtaſte, or apprehenſion of Danger.</p>
               <p>And we, for our Parts, ſhall be ready to lay down all thoſe Preparations which we have been forced to make for our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. And for the <hi>Town of Hull,</hi> and <hi>the Ordinance</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Militia,</hi> as we have in both theſe Particulars, only ſought the preſervation of the Peace of the Kingdom, and the Defence of the Parliament from Force and Violence; ſo we ſhall moſt willingly leave the <hi>Town of Hull</hi> in the ſtate it was before Sir <hi>John Hotham</hi> drew any Forces into it, delivering <hi>your Majeſty's Magazine</hi> into the <hi>Tower of London: We ſhall be ready to ſettle the</hi> Militia <hi>by a</hi> Bill, in ſuch a way as ſhall be honourable and ſafe for your <hi>Majeſty,</hi> moſt agreeable to the Duty of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> and effectual for the Good of the <hi>Kingdom, that the Strength thereof be not employed againſt it ſelf; and that which ought to be for our Security, applied to our Deſtruction.</hi> And that the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and thoſe who profeſs and deſire ſtill to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> both in this <hi>Realm,</hi> and in <hi>Ireland,</hi> may not be left <hi>naked and indefenſible,</hi> to the miſchievous Deſigns and cruel Attempts of thoſe who are <hi>the profeſs'd and confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Enemies</hi> thereof, in your Majeſty's Dominions, and <hi>other Neighbour Nations:</hi> To which, if <hi>your Majeſty's Courſes and Counſels</hi> ſhall from henceforth concur; We doubt not but we ſhall quickly make it appear to the World, by the moſt eminent Effects of Love and Duty, That <hi>your Majeſty's perſonal Safety your Royal Honour and Greatneſs, are much dearer to us than our
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:97943:32"/>own Lives and Fortunes, which we do moſt heartily dedicate, and ſhall moſt willingly imploy for the ſupport and maintenance thereof.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>And now, <hi>Sir,</hi> I appeal to you, and to all the World, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe Men talk'd here, as though they were reſolved to make War, and engroſs all into their own Hands, let what would become of the King?</hi> as a certain <hi>Aldgate Doctor of Divinity</hi> falſly accuſes the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons. Thanks</hi> be to <hi>God,</hi> Sir <hi>John Holland</hi> (as well as Sir <hi>John Prattle</hi>) is yet alive in <hi>Norfolk,</hi> in perfect Health and Underſtanding; and is ready to give the ſame account I have here given you, to any Man that asks him about it.</p>
            <p>What ſay you next,<note place="margin">Pag. 10.</note> Mr. <hi>Chaplain at Aldgate?</hi> Why, <hi>To let the World ſee what the King aimed at, He does aſſure the Gentlemen, whoſe Loyalty engaged them early on his Side; and does promiſe them, in the Preſence of</hi> Almighty God, <hi>and as he hopes for his Bleſſing and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, that he would, to the utmoſt of his Power, defend and maintain the true Proteſtant Religion eſtabliſh'd in the</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> England.</p>
            <p>You almoſt provoke me, <hi>Doctor,</hi> to draw up <hi>a Petition</hi> to your <hi>Right Honourable and Right Reverend Dioceſan,</hi> to ſuſpend you from writing DEFENCES, till you ſwear to do them honeſtly; then, and not till then, we may hope for <hi>the Truth, the whole Truth, and nothing but the Truth:</hi> I am credibly informed, that there was ſomething more in this <hi>Speech,</hi> than you are willing to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg; 'Tis the ſame, I take it for granted, that his Majeſty made at the Head of <hi>his Army,</hi> between <hi>Stafford</hi> and <hi>Wellington,</hi> the 19th of <hi>September</hi> 1642. He then had theſe Expreſſions alſo; <hi>The time cannot be long before we come to Action—You ſhall meet with no Enemies, but TRAITORS, MOST OF THEM <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ROW<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NISTS, ANABAPTISTS AND ATHEISTS.</hi> Theſe were the Words of <hi>a King,</hi> I ſhall not therefore reflect further upon them, than to ask you, upon <hi>the Oath which you are to take,</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you do in your Conſcience believe, that <hi>the Great, the Good, the pious King,</hi> ſpoke Truth here? Whether he had not more <hi>Atheiſts</hi> and <hi>Papiſts</hi> in his <hi>Army,</hi> than the <hi>Parliament</hi> had <hi>Browniſts</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> in theirs?</p>
            <p>Your next Effort is this;<note place="margin">Pag. 12.</note> You fall upon <hi>the Conſideration of the Steps his Majeſty made towards Peace,</hi> and thus expreſs your ſelf; <hi>Truly, I think, ACCORDING TO MY POOR J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DGMENT, he now Acts according to what he always pretended, and ſolemnly avowed; to wit, as a true Father of his Country; for be propoſes, That HIS REVEN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E, MAGAZINES, TOWNS,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:97943:32"/>SHIPS AND FORTS may be reſtored to him,</hi> and all ſhould be well.</p>
            <p>Now I will readily agree, that there is here and there found <hi>a Doctor, nay a Chaplain too, of a poor Judgment;</hi> but one would think, that he that is conſcious of his own Weakneſs and Inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, ſhould not aſſume the Arrogance to judg in Matters of Right between <hi>Princes and their People.</hi> And I will here tell you, what better Heads than you or I ever wore, ſaid upon this Point; The <hi>Opinion</hi> of the <hi>Parliament</hi> was, That <hi>his Majeſty's Towns were no more his own, than his Kingdom is his own; and his Kingdom is no more his own, than his People are his own: And if the King had a Propriety in all his Towns, what would become of the Subjects Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty in their Houſes therein? And if he had a Propriety in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, what would become of the Subjects Property in their Lands throughout the Kingdom, or of their Liberties, if his Majeſty had the ſame Right in their Perſons, that every Subject hath in his Lands? This ERRONEO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S MAXIM being infuſed into Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, THAT THEIR KINGDOMS ARE THEIR OWN; and that they may do with them what they will, (AS IF THEIR KING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DOMS were for them, and not they for their Kingdoms) is the Root of all the Subjects Miſery, and of the invading of their juſt Rights and Liberties; whereas INDEED THEY ARE ONLY INTR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TED with their Kingdoms, and with their Towns, and with their People, and with the Publick Treaſures of the Common-Wealth, and whatſoever is bought therewith; and by the known Law of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, the VERY JEWELS OF THE CROWN are not the King's PROPER Goods, but are only intruſted unto him for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe and Ornament thereof; as the Towns, Forts, Treaſure, Magazines, Offices and the People of the Kingdom; and the whole Kingdom it ſelf is entruſted unto him, for the Good, Safety, and beſt Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage thereof. And AS THIS TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ST IS FOR THE <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE OF THE KINGDOM, SO IT O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GHT TO BE MANAGED BY THE ADVICE OF THE HO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SES OF PARLIAMENT, whom the Kingdom hath truſted for that purpoſe, it being their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to ſee it be diſcharged, according to the condition and true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent thereof, and as much as in them lies, by all poſſible means to prevent the contrary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not to enquire what you, <hi>Sir, in your poor Judgment</hi> do think of this <hi>high Principle,</hi> I will move, with what ſpeed I can, to a Concluſion: I told you, not long ſince, That <hi>the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:97943:33"/>voted</hi> the raiſing an <hi>Army</hi> to be commanded by the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Eſſex;</hi> and at the ſame time humbly (but <hi>in vain</hi>) <hi>ſupplicated:</hi> the <hi>King</hi> for Peace, and <hi>to return to his Parliament.</hi> When the <hi>General</hi> marched with his Forces towards the <hi>Army raiſed againſt the Parliament and Kingdom:</hi> He was inſtructed to fight at ſuch Time and Place as he ſhould judg moſt to conduce to the Peace and Safety of the Kingdom, but was alſo commanded to cauſe <hi>a Petition</hi> of <hi>both Houſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> to be preſented to his <hi>Majeſty;</hi> wherein they thus expreſſed themſelves.</p>
            <q rend="margQuotes">
               <p>We cannot, without great grief and tenderneſs of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, behold <hi>the preſſing Miſeries, the imminent Dangers, the devouring Calamities</hi> which do extreamly threaten the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms</hi> of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> by the practice of <hi>a Party pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing with your Majeſty,</hi> who by many <hi>wicked Plots</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies,</hi> have <hi>attempted the alteration of the true Religion, and the ancient Government of this Kingdom, and the introducing of POPISH IDOLATRY AND S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>PERSTITION in the CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH, and TYRANNY and CONF<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SION in the STATE.</hi> And for the compaſſing thereof, have long <hi>corrupted your Majeſty's Counſels,</hi> abuſed your Power, and <hi>by ſudden</hi> and untimely <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving of the former Parliaments,</hi> have often hindred the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> and <hi>Prevention</hi> of thoſe <hi>Miſchiefs;</hi> and being now diſabled to avoid the Endeavours of this <hi>Parliament,</hi> by any ſuch Means, <hi>have TRAITERO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SLY attempted to over-awe the ſame by Force:</hi> And in proſecution of their wicked Deſigns, <hi>have EXCITED, ENCO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RAGED AND FOSTER'D an unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural REBELLION in</hi> IRELAND; and have drawn your <hi>MAJESTY to make War againſt your Parliament,</hi> as if you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, <hi>by CONQ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EST,</hi> to eſtabliſh an <hi>ABSOL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TE ILLI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MITED I OWER</hi> over them.</p>
               <p>And <hi>by YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R POWER, and the countenance of your Preſence, have SPOILED, IMPRISONED, M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RDERED divers of your People.</hi> And for their better aſſiſtance in theſe wicked Deſigns, <hi>do ſeek to bring over the Rebels of</hi> Ireland to join with them. <hi>WE HAVE, for the juſt and neceſſary Defence of the Proteſtant Religion, of your Majeſty's Perſon, of the Laws and Liberties of the Kingdom, and the Priviledg and Power of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; TAKEN <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>P ARMS,</hi> and appointed <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi> to be <hi>Captain General</hi> of all the Forces by us raiſed; and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:97943:33"/>to head and conduct the ſame, againſt <hi>theſe REBELS</hi> and <hi>TRAITORS,</hi> and them to ſubdue and bring to condign Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.</p>
               <p>And do moſt <hi>humbly beſeech</hi> your <hi>Majeſty to withdraw your Royal Preſence and Countenance from theſe wicked Perſons; and THAT YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R MAJESTY WILL NOT MIX YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R OWN DANGER WITH THEIRS; but,</hi> in Peace and Safety, <hi>forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with return to your Parliament,</hi> and by their faithful Counſel and Advice, compoſe the preſent Diſtempers and Confuſions abounding in both your Kingdoms, and <hi>provide for the Security and Honour of your Royal Poſterity,</hi> and the proſperous Eſtate of all your Subjects: <hi>And we do, in the preſence of Almighty God, profeſs, That we will receive your Majeſty with all Honour, yield you all due Obedience and Subjection, and faithfully endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to ſecure your Perſon and Eſtate from all Danger; and to the uttermoſt of our Power, to procure and eſtabliſh to your Self, and to your People, all the Bleſſings of a glorious and happy Reign.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>You ſee, <hi>Sir,</hi> the <hi>LORDS AND COMMONS TALK'D LIKE CHRISTIANS; They were grieved at the Miſeries of the Kingdoms; They deteſted the Romiſh Idolatry: When they ſent their Army againſt the Enemies of the King and Kingdom, they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicate his Majeſty not to mix his Danger with theirs, but to return in Peace to his Parliament, and compoſe the Diſtempers of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and provide for the Security and Honour of his Poſterity: They IN THE PRESENCE OF GOD PROFESS, that they would receive him with all Honour, yield him all due Subjection, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to ſecure him from Danger, and make his Reign Glorious and Happy; WHICH WORDS CERTAINLY ARE NOT THE WORDS OF TRAITORS.</hi> But all this would not do, for <hi>he reſolved to anſwer their Petitions in Blood,</hi> and proclaimed the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Eſſex, Rebel.</hi> Yet, to blind the Eyes of the Multitude, and diſguiſe his pernicious and cruel Intentions, under the ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of Peace and Juſtice, he made <hi>(as you, Doctor, have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved)</hi> divers <hi>ſolemn Proteſtations, with fearful Imprecations up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelf, and invocation of God's Holy Name, That he intended nothing but the Peace and Welfare of his People, the maintenance of Religion, and the Laws of the Kingdom;</hi> and for his own ſecurity only, to raiſe <hi>a Guard for his Perſon;</hi> and that <hi>he did from his Soul abhor the thought of making War againſt the Parliament,</hi> or
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:97943:34"/>to put the Kingdom into a Combuſtion: Nevertheleſs, his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary intentions were at that very inſtant manifeſted, by theſe enſuing Actions and Proceedings, before the <hi>Parliament voted the raiſing of their Army.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He put <hi>a Gariſon</hi> of Souldiers into <hi>Newcaſtle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Upon the 27th of <hi>Septemb.</hi> 1642 he not only allowed, but required the Papiſts of <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> to provide Arms for themſelves, their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants and Tenants; and all with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt for the Service of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Papiſts,</hi> in a peremptory manner, <hi>in the King's Name, demanded their Arms,</hi> taken from them according to the Laws, <hi>to be again reſtored to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He cauſed the Mouth of the <hi>River Tine</hi> to be fortified, whereby the whole Trade of <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle</hi> for Coals, was ſubject to be interrupted whenſoever he ſhould pleaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Ship</hi> laden with <hi>Cannon for Battery, Powder and Ammunition,</hi> was brought for him into the <hi>River</hi> of <hi>Humber;</hi> which alſo brought ſeveral <hi>Commanders</hi> from Foreign Parts: Alſo divers other large Preparations of Warlike Proviſions were made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Sea, and ſhortly expected; beſides, great Numbers of <hi>Gentlemen, Horſes and Arms,</hi> were drawn from all parts of the Kingdom; and all the <hi>Gentlemen</hi> of <hi>Yorkſhire required to bring in their Horſes for the King's Service.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Commiſſions for raiſing Horſe</hi> were granted, and divers <hi>Officers</hi> for his Army were appointed.</p>
            <p>Upon the 4th of <hi>July,</hi> the King rendezvouzed an <hi>Army</hi> of a conſiderable number of Horſe and Foot and <hi>Beverly;</hi> amongſt whom there were divers <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and other Perſons of deſperate Fortune and Condition, ready to execute any Violence, Rapine and Oppreſſion.</p>
            <p>He ſent ſome <hi>Troops of Horſe</hi> into <hi>Lincolnſhire,</hi> to the great Terror of the People: <hi>They began to take away Mens Horſes</hi> by force, and to commit Acts of Hoſtility.</p>
            <p>Theſe are ſad Truths, <hi>Reverend Doctor;</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> having thus, contrary to his ſolemn Proteſtation, begun the War; the <hi>Lords and Commons</hi> aſſembled in Parliament, held themſelves bound in Conſcience to raiſe Forces for the preſervation of the Peace of the Kingdom, and Protection of the People in their Perſons and Eſtates, according to Law; and for the Defence and Security of the Parliament: and accordingly upon the 12th of <hi>July,</hi> 1642, and not before <hi>(as I have already told you)</hi> they voted the raiſing an Army for theſe purpoſes.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:97943:34"/>
            <p>Now in regard, as I underſtand, you were before your Dotage, a <hi>Presbyterian Miniſter</hi> of <hi>Eſſex;</hi> I would gladly ſet your <hi>poor Judgment</hi> right in this great Point, of as well the <hi>Neceſſity as Juſtice of the Parliament War;</hi> and in regard that I find you prejudiced againſt Dr. <hi>Seaman</hi> and Mr. <hi>Calamy,</hi> I will not offer their Opinion to you; but pray ſee what the learned and pious Mr. <hi>Daniel Rogers</hi> of <hi>Wethersfield,</hi> Mr. <hi>Matthew New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comen</hi> of <hi>Dedham,</hi> and above <hi>ſixty</hi> eminent <hi>Miniſters</hi> of ſo many ſeveral Towns in <hi>Eſſex:</hi> left under their hands, in relation to this Controverſy between you and me.</p>
            <q rend="margQuotes">
               <p>
                  <hi>We</hi> (ſay they) <hi>call the God of Heaven and Earth to witneſs</hi> upon our Souls, that <hi>it was not hatred to any Party or Perſon,</hi> much leſs to the Perſon of OUR KING, <hi>that firſt drew <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s to engage with and for the PARLIAMENT;</hi> but clearly this, ſome Years before the aſſembling of this <hi>Parliament, we evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſaw the Affairs of Church and State in imminent and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent hazard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> many and <hi>great Alterations made in Doctrine, Innovations in Worſhip, the Power of Godlineſs diſgrac'd, true Religion undermined, the faithful and conſcientious Profeſſors of it perſecuted,</hi> even to Bonds, Flight and Impriſonment, POPE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RY CONNIVED AT, COUNTENANCED, COURTED; beſides many <hi>grievous Oppreſſions of the Subjects in their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Properties.</hi> Theſe things we ſaw and ſigned for, but <hi>had no thoughts of inviting any to make Reſiſtance,</hi> (tho againſt the abuſed Name and Power of <hi>a miſguided King, whom, we much pitied in his Miſcarriages</hi>) until it pleaſed <hi>God</hi> to bleſs us with A PARLIAMENT, THE ORDINARY MEANS WHICH HE HATH APPOINTED IN THIS NATION FOR THE REDRESSING OF SUCH GROWING EVILS.</p>
               <p>The Parliament meet, declare their Apprehenſions of the Danger of CHURCH AND STATE, apply themſelves to all <hi>humble and ſubmiſs ways,</hi> by PETITIONS,<note place="margin">See the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance of the State of the Kingdom. <hi>Decemb.</hi> 15. 1641.</note> REMON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STRANCES, <hi>&amp;c. ſpeak nothing but honourably of the</hi> King; lay the blame of all Miſcarriages upon <hi>Evil Counſellors; require them to Trial:</hi> But <hi>God, for our Sins and his,</hi> ſhuts up his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Heart againſt theſe <hi>Addreſſes:</hi> inſtead of yielding up thoſe whom the Parliament demands, he <hi>demands ſome of their Members,</hi> ſeconds his Demand with <hi>a. Face of Violence:</hi> And HERE BEGAN THAT MOST UNHAPPY BREACH:
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:97943:35"/>the <hi>Parliament</hi> upon this deſire <hi>a Guard; the King apprehended OR PRETENDED Terror,</hi> he <hi>leaves his Parliament</hi> upon it, and UNDER SHADOW OF A GUARD <hi>for his Perſon,</hi> RAISETH AN ARMY, <hi>ſets up his</hi> STANDARD, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Story is too long and ſad for us to relate; but <hi>hence aroſe that Fire,</hi> which ſince hath burnt almoſt to the very Foundation, and who knows when it will be quenched?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Parliament</hi> ſeeing which way the <hi>Counſels</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> ſteered, <hi>apprehend a neceſſity of raiſing Arms FOR THE DEFENCE OF THEMSELVES AND THE KINGDOM.</hi> —When the War was firſt commenced, <hi>their Army carried a Petition in the one hand, as well as a Sword in the other,</hi> in which <hi>the Lords and Commons</hi> do, <hi>IN THE PRESENCE OF ALMIGHTY GOD, profeſs,</hi> That <hi>if his Majeſty will forthwith return to his Parliament,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>they will receive him with all Honour, yield him all due Subjection and Obedience, and faithfully endeavour to ſecure his Perſon and Eſtate from all Danger, and do the utmoſt of their Power, to procure and eſtabliſh to himſelf and his People all the Bleſſings of a glorious and happy Reign. WE DID THEN VERILY BELIEVE, AND YET DO, that theſe were the ſincere and cordial Intentions of the Lords and Commons;</hi> and altho the <hi>King</hi> was ſo unhappy as <hi>to reject that Petition,</hi> yet <hi>they perſiſted ſtill in the ſame Loyalty</hi> of Intentions and Affections to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, as appears in their many <hi>Meſſages</hi> to himſelf, and <hi>Declarations</hi> to the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>Upon theſe Grounds we engaged in this <hi>CA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE, being called to it by a lawful Authority;</hi> The <hi>TWO HO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SES OF PARLIAMENT, BEING THE ORDINANCE OF GOD <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NTO THIS NATION, FOR THE PREVENTING OF TYRANNY, AND THE REG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LATING OF THE EX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ORBITANCIES OF REGAL POWER;</hi> and being convinced in our Judgments both of <hi>the Equity and Neceſſity</hi> of <hi>THE PARLIAMENT'S DEFENSIVE ARMS,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>WE APPEAL TO GOD</hi> the Searcher of all Hearts, to whom we muſt give an Account of all our Ways, <hi>THAT THESE WERE THE GRO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NDS OF O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R FIRST EN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GAGEMENT.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Now, <hi>Sir,</hi> to look back to your <hi>Defence</hi> of the <hi>King;</hi> I find you frequently glorying in his <hi>Majeſty</hi>'s oft-repeated <hi>Gracious
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:97943:35"/>Meſſages, Offers, Propoſals and Condeſcentions for Peace;</hi> and in relation to the Deportment of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> you thus expreſs your poor Judgment. <hi>I cannot but perſwade my ſelf,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 17.</note> 
               <hi>they were reſolved to continue the War, and engroſs all into their own hands, let what would become of the King: But yet that they might pacify the Minds of a great number of the Nation, who groaned under the Miſeries of the War, and began to ſee too much of a private Spirit under publick Pretences; they conſent to a Treaty at</hi> Uxbridg; they did ſo, and you declare that <hi>two Heads</hi> were agreed to be there debated, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Of Religion and Church Government.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Of the Militia.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Now in reading the Hiſtory of that <hi>Treaty,</hi> I find that <hi>a third great thing</hi> was agreed to be alſo <hi>debated,</hi> viz. <hi>The buſineſs of</hi> Ireland; but that being a Point which you care not to touch, I muſt not allow you to hide it.</p>
            <p>To diſcourſe a little about this <hi>Treaty;</hi> notwithſtanding the <hi>King for his Credit-ſake, and to ſatisfy his own Party, weary of War, yielded to a Treaty; I cannot perſwade my ſelf but he was reſolved to continue the War;</hi> and if you appear not <hi>a Man of reſolved Prejudices, or elſe of profound and ſtupid Ignorance,</hi> I do half think that I may bring you over to my Opinion in this matter. For to let you ſee what diſpoſed him to hearken to this <hi>Treaty,</hi> take his own words in his <hi>Letter</hi> to the <hi>Queen</hi> in <hi>December</hi> 1644. <hi>I ſhall ſhew thee upon what Grounds I came to a Treaty, to the end thou mayſt the better underſtand and APPROVE of my Ways: Then know (as A CERTAIN TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TH) that all, EVEN MY PARTY, are ſtrongly impatient for Peace; which obliged me ſo much the more (at all occaſions) to ſhew my real Intentions to Peace.—NO DANGER OF DEATH SHALL MAKE ME DO ANY THING <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NWORTHY OF THY LOVE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the very inſtant of this <hi>Treaty,</hi> which was had in <hi>February</hi> 1644, the King uſed all imaginable means to bring not only FOREIGN FORCES, but the <hi>Iriſh</hi> CUT-THROATS againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> to clear up this Point, and alſo to evince how inſincere he was in his <hi>pretended Intentions of Peace.</hi> I will briefly preſent to your view his <hi>under-hand Tranſactions,</hi> as well with <hi>Foreign Princes</hi> as thoſe <hi>Rebels:</hi> and in the firſt place, I ſhall mind you of ſome Paſſages between <hi>Him</hi> and the <hi>Queen</hi> in relation to this and other <hi>Treaties.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:97943:36"/>
            <p>In a <hi>Letter</hi> to her of <hi>January</hi> 9, 1644, he writes thus. The <hi>Scots Commiſſioners</hi> have ſent to me to ſend a <hi>Commiſſion</hi> to their <hi>General Aſſembly,</hi> WHICH I AM RESOLVED NOT TO DO; but to the end of <hi>making ſome uſe of this occaſion,</hi> by ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an honeſt Man to <hi>London,</hi> and <hi>that I may have the more time for the making</hi> A HANDSOME NEGATIVE, I have demanded a Paſsport for <hi>Phil. Warwick,</hi> by whom to return my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</p>
            <p>At another time in the ſame Month he tells her, that <hi>as for my my calling thoſe at</hi> London<note n="*" place="margin">He had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed to treat with them as <hi>a Parliament,</hi> the <hi>Queen</hi> upbraid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him for ſo doing, and he thus vindicates himſelf.</note> A PARLIAMENT, IF THERE, HAD BEEN BUT TWO OF MY OPINION. <hi>I had not done it,</hi> THE CALLING DID NO WAYS ACKNOWLEDG THEM TO BE A PARLIAMENT, <hi>upon which Condition and Conſtruction I did it, and accordingly it is regiſtred in the Council-Books.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nothing is more evident than that <hi>the King was ſteered by the Queen's Counſel in the Management of this</hi> Uxbridg-<hi>Treaty,</hi> and that which you call the <hi>Church of</hi> England [THE BISHOPS] <hi>was greatly her Care.</hi> By Letter in <hi>January</hi> 1644, before the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of that Treaty, <hi>She inſtructs him not to abandon thoſe who have ſerved him leſt they for ſake him in his need; that SHE hopes he will have a care of her and HER RELIGION: That in her Majeſty's Opinion,</hi> RELIGION SHOULD BE THE LAST THING UPON WHICH HE SHOULD TREAT; <hi>for if he do agree upon Strictneſs againſt the Catholicks, it would diſcourage them to ſerve him; and if afterwards there ſhould be no Peace, he could never expect Succours either FROM</hi> IRELAND, <hi>or any other</hi> CATHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LICK PRINCE.</p>
            <p>In another of her <hi>Letters</hi> we find her writing thus, <hi>Jan.</hi> 17, 1644. <hi>It comforts me much to ſee the Treaty ſhall be at</hi> Uxbridg. —I RECEIVED YESTERDAY LETTERS FROM THE DUKE OF <hi>LORRAIN,</hi> WHO SENDS ME WORD, IF HIS SERVICE BE AGREEABLE TO YOU, HE WILL BRING YOU 10000 MEN — ABOVE ALL <hi>have a care not to</hi> ABANDON <hi>thoſe who have ſerved you,</hi> AS WELL THE BI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHOPS AS THE POOR CATHOLICKS.</p>
            <p>By the <hi>King's Letters</hi> to the <hi>Queen</hi> in <hi>February,</hi> when the <hi>Treaty</hi> at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridg</hi> was depending, <hi>he ſtiles the Parliament</hi> UNREASONBLE, STUBBORN, PERFIDIOUS REBELS; <hi>preſſes her to haſten all poſſible Aſſiſtance to him, particularly that of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:97943:36"/>the Duke of</hi> Lorrain. He tells her, that the <hi>limited days</hi> for treating are now almoſt expired, without the leaſt Agreement upon any one Article; wherefore <hi>I have ſent for enlargement of Days,</hi> THAT THE WHOLE TREATY MAY BE LAID OPEN TO THE WORLD; and I ASSURE THEE THOU NEEDEST NOT DOUBT THE ISSUE OF THIS TREATY; for MY COMMISSIONERS ARE SO WELL CHOSEN, <hi>(tho I ſay it) that they will neither be threatned nor diſputed from the Grounds I have given them, which</hi> (upon my word) IS ACCORDING TO THE LITTLE NOTE THOU SO WELL REMEM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BERS. —<hi>Be confident that in making Peace I ſhall ever ſhew my</hi> CONSTANCY IN ADHERING TO BISHOPS, AND ALL OUR FRIENDS, <hi>and not forget to put a ſhort Period to this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We find him in another <hi>Letter</hi> dated the 5th of <hi>March,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing himſelf in theſe words: <hi>I have thought of one means more to furniſh thee with for my Aſſiſtance, than hitherto thou haſt had; it is, that</hi> I GIVE THEE POWER TO PROMISE IN MY NAME, THAT <hi>I will</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">If this were ſo good a King, Why ſo much Clamour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt K. <hi>James</hi> the Second for deſigning the ſame thing?</note> 
               <hi>take away all the Penal Laws againſt the Roman Catholicks in</hi> England, <hi>as ſoon as God ſhall enable me to do it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another <hi>Letter</hi> to her of the 20th of <hi>March,</hi> hath this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, <hi>I find that Thou much miſtakes Me concerning</hi> Ireland; I DESIRE NOTHING MORE THAN A PEACE <hi>there, and never forbad thy Commerce there.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In relation to <hi>Ireland,</hi> he wrote to the Marqueſs of <hi>Ormond</hi> to this effect, <hi>Jan.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p>THE REBELS HERE <hi>have agreed to</hi> TREAT, AND MOST ASSUREDLY ONE OF THE FIRST <hi>and chief</hi> ARTICLES <hi>they will inſist on will be,</hi> TO CONTINUE THE IRISH WAR, WHICH IS A POINT NOT POPULAR FOR ME TO BREAK ON; <hi>of which you are to make a double uſe: Firſt,</hi> TO HASTEN WITH ALL POSSIBLE DILIGENCE THE PEACE THERE; <hi>the timely concluſion of which, will take off that Inconvenience which otherwiſe I may be ſubject to, by the refuſal of that Article, upon any other Reaſon.</hi> Secondly, <hi>By dexterous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veying to the Iriſh, the Danger there may be of their total and perpetual</hi> EXCLUSION FROM THOSE FAVOURS I
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:97943:37"/>INTEND THEM, <hi>in caſe</hi> THE REBELS <hi>here elap up a Peace with me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>NOT DOUBTING OF A PEACE, <hi>I muſt again remember you,</hi> TO PRESS THE IRISH <hi>for their ſpeedy Aſſistance to me here, and their Friends in</hi> Scotland.—I DESIRE <hi>that</hi> THE I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RISH <hi>would ſend as great a Body as they can, to land about</hi> Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berland, WHICH WILL PUT THOSE NORTHERN COUN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIES IN A BRAVE CONDITION.</p>
            <p>Upon the 14th of <hi>January,</hi> he writes thus to the <hi>Queen; As for the Peace of</hi> Ireland, <hi>to ſhew thee the Care I have had of it, and the Fruits I hope to receive from it, I have ſent thee the laſt Diſpatches I have ſent concerning it.</hi>—FOR GOD'S SAKE LET NONE KNOW THE PARTICULARS OF MY DISPATCHES.</p>
            <p>By another <hi>Letter,</hi> he commanded <hi>Ormond, To diſpatch the Iriſh Peace out of hand; and thereby promiſes that the</hi> PENAL LAWS <hi>againſt Roman Catholicks</hi> SHALL NOT BE PUT IN EXECU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION, <hi>the Peace being made; and that when the Iriſh give him that Aſſiſtance which they have promiſed for the ſuppreſſion of</hi> THIS REBELLION, <hi>then he would conſent to the Repeal of them by a Law: and concludes,</hi> RECOMMENDING TO HIM AGAIN, THE SPEEDY DISPATCH OF THE PEACE OF <hi>IRELAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another Letter to <hi>Ormond,</hi> upon the 27th of <hi>Feb.</hi> 1644, was, That HE THOUGHT HIMSELF BOUND IN CONSCIENCE <hi>not to loſe that Aſſiſtance which he might hope from his</hi> IRISH SUBJECTS, <hi>for ſuch Scruples as in a leſs preſſing condition might reaſonably be ſtuck at by him, and therefore commanded him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude a Peace with the Iriſh,</hi> WHATSOEVER IT COST, <hi>ſo that his Proteſtant Subjects there might be ſecured, and his Regal Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity preſerved.—If the preſent taking away of the Penal Laws againſt Papiſts will do it,</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I ſhall not think it a hard Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, ſo that freely and vigorouſly they engage themſelves in my Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance againſt</hi> MY REBELS <hi>of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Scotland; FOR WHICH NO CONDITIONS CAN BE TOO HARD, <hi>not being aginſt Conſcience or Honour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By another <hi>Letter</hi> to the <hi>Marqueſs</hi> of <hi>Ormond,</hi> in the ſame Month, he writes thus; <hi>Now again I cannot but mention the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of haſtening the Iriſh Peace, for which I hope you are already furniſhed by me with Materials ſufficient. But in caſe (againſt all Expectation and Reaſon)</hi> PEACE CANNOT BE HAD UPON THOSE TERMS, YOU MUST NOT BY ANY MEANS
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:97943:37"/>FALL TO A NEW RUPTURE <hi>with them, but continue</hi> THE CESSATION.</p>
            <p>He wrote to the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Richmond,</hi> one of his <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> for the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridg Treaty;</hi>
               <note place="margin">There was at this time high Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion in <hi>London,</hi> between the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Independents;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>to ruin both,</hi> by ſomenti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Miſunderſtandings between them, the <hi>Independents</hi> are to be <hi>cajoled:</hi> A thing worthy remembrance in all times.</note> TO REMEMBER TO CAJOLE WELL THE INDEPENDENTS AND THE SCOTS; <hi>Nay, he inſtructed Secretary</hi> Nicholas <hi>to bribe the Commiſſioners for the Parliament, with the promiſe of Security, Rewards, and Places.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, now upon the whole Matter, pray tell me ingenuouſly, <hi>good Doctor, Whether did the King or the Parliament more ſincerely aim at the deſired Peace in this Treaty?</hi> I am clearly of opinion, that he fruſtrated the Hopes of a happy Compoſure at this time, for whatever you alledg, had he uſed the ſame moderation here, and granted thoſe things he offered to yield to afterwards, (as I may have occaſion to ſhew you hereafter) <hi>the unhappy War had then been ended:</hi> But though he pretended to liſten to Overtures of Peace, becauſe <hi>his own Party were weary of the War;</hi> yet he was found to uſe <hi>Tricks</hi> of <hi>Legerdemain;</hi> and by this, and his <hi>other Treaties,</hi> aimed only at the getting ſome Advantage by <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Treacheries</hi> and <hi>under-hand Dealings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have told you, that <hi>one of the three main Heads</hi> to be treated upon, <hi>was Ireland;</hi> That was to be <hi>anticipated</hi> and <hi>foreſtall'd,</hi> by <hi>a Peace at any Rate to be huddled up</hi> with the <hi>Iriſh Rebels, e're the Treaty could begin;</hi> that he might pretend his <hi>Word and Honour paſt,</hi> againſt the <hi>popular Arguments</hi> which the <hi>Parliament</hi> might urge upon him, for the continuance of that <hi>juſt War. The Engliſh,</hi> during the Treaty, <hi>were called perfidious Rebels, the</hi> IRISH GOOD AND CATHOLICK SUBJECTS. <hi>He contrived how to make handſom Negatives:</hi> For faſhion-ſake <hi>he called the Parliament a</hi> PARLIAMENT, <hi>yet by a Jeſuitical Slight, he did not acknowledg, tho call them ſo.</hi> He preſs'd earneſtly for <hi>Ten thouſand Lorrainers</hi> to be tranſported hither; and that <hi>a Body of the bloody Iriſh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels</hi> might be landed in <hi>Cumberland,</hi> delighting himſelf, that they would put the <hi>Northern Counties into</hi> A BRAVE CONDI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION; for he well knew that they had deſtroyed above <hi>One hundred and forty thouſand Proteſtants in their own Kingdom;</hi> and were therefore, without doubt, very <hi>fit Men to aſſist him in the maintaining</hi> THE CHURCH OF <hi>ENGLAND.</hi> He boaſted of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:97943:38"/>his choice of <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> for the Treaty, and that they would ſtick cloſe to the NOTE OF INSTRUCTIONS which <hi>he</hi> and the <hi>Queen</hi> had concerted; and <hi>aſſured her that</hi> HE WOULD EVER SHEW HIS CONSTANCY IN ADHER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ING TO BISHOPS AND PAPISTS. He impowered the <hi>Queen</hi> to treat with the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and to give aſſurance, that <hi>he would take away</hi> THE PENAL LAWS <hi>againſt Papiſts in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. In fine; Nothing is more evident, than that <hi>he uſed Treaties pretending Peace, to no other End, than to gain Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that might enable him to carry on War.</hi> And methinks it ſhould not offend you to hear that Opinion, not only <hi>a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter,</hi> but <hi>a Martyr</hi> for <hi>Mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>oy</hi> had of this <hi>King;</hi> the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Mr. <hi>Chriſtopher Love, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> loſt his Head upon</hi> Tower-hill, (which I am confident you w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> never do for any Cauſe, tho you live near it) preaching before the <hi>Parliament Commiſſioners</hi> at this <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridg Treaty,</hi> expreſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> himſelf thus; <hi>It would ſearch to the quick to find out</hi> WHETHER KING <hi>JAMES</hi> AND PRINCE <hi>HENRY</hi> HIS SON CAME TO A TIMELY DEATH, YEA OR NO; <hi>Some Parliaments have been but ſhort-liv'd, when, there was but a muttering, that enquiry ſhould be made of their Deaths. It would ſearch to the quick, to know</hi> WHETHER <hi>ROCHEL, and all</hi> THE PROTESTANTS <hi>in it, were not betrayed into the hands of their Enemies,</hi> AND BY WHOM. <hi>It would go to the quick to find out</hi> WHETHER THE IRISH REBELLION <hi>was not plotted, promoted, countenanced and contrived in</hi> England, AND BY WHOM.</p>
            <p>Now, I hope, <hi>Reverend Sir,</hi> that you will not have the face to deny, but Mr. <hi>Love</hi> was a Conſciencious and Pious. <hi>Divine;</hi> and I will finiſh this Head in telling you, (though a little out of courſe) that the <hi>Earls</hi> of <hi>Northumberland, Pembroke, Salisbury</hi> and <hi>Denbigh;</hi> with the Lord <hi>Wainman,</hi> Sir <hi>Henry Vane,</hi> Mr. <hi>Piere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pont,</hi> Mr. <hi>Holles,</hi> Mr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> Mr. <hi>St. John,</hi> Mr. <hi>Whitlock</hi> and Mr. <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>w, Commiſſioners</hi> for the <hi>Parliament,</hi> in the Treaty we have been talking of, <hi>were</hi> (as well as you boaſt the <hi>King's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſioners</hi> to have been) <hi>Men of Honour and Honeſty, Men of Fortunes and Eſtates; Men of great Parts and Endowments, who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the Buſineſs they went about, and were very fond of healing the Nations Breaches, and putting things into ſuch a poſture as might ſettle the King upon his juſt Rights, and the People upon their ancient Priviledges.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:97943:38"/>
            <p>Well, <hi>Sir,</hi> for my own Comfort, if not for yours, I purpoſe to trouble my ſelf <hi>(at leaſt at this preſent)</hi> with but one thing more in your <hi>Tract,</hi> You ſay, That <hi>the Scots, notwithſtanding all their Promiſes and Obligations,</hi> SELL THE KING TO THE ENGLISH PARLIAMENT. 'Tis <hi>a Divine Truth, Men are not only ignorant becauſe they cannot, but becauſe they will not know the Truth:</hi> And I cannot conceive that you believe what you here aſſert; Therefore, that <hi>my Country-men</hi> may be undeceived, and <hi>our Brethren of</hi> Scotland vindicated, I will ſet this Matter in its true Light: The <hi>King</hi> had fled to the <hi>Scotiſh Army</hi> at <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle,</hi> then <hi>in the Parliament's Service and Pay;</hi> there <hi>Propoſitions for Peace</hi> were made unto him, which he rejected. The War being happily ended, the <hi>Parliament</hi> were in arrear to the <hi>Scots</hi> for their aſſiſtance in it, <hi>Four hundred thouſand Pounds:</hi> It was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, that half that Sum ſhould be preſently paid; upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt whereof, the <hi>Scots were to deliver up</hi> (not the King, but) Berwick, Newcaſtle, <hi>and</hi> Carliſle to the <hi>Parliament.</hi> 'Tis far from Truth, that this was <hi>the Price</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> for <hi>the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment freely granted to the Scots, that they might carry him</hi> (if they pleaſed) <hi>to</hi> Edinburgh: But <hi>they refuſed it,</hi> affirming, that <hi>by his Preſence,</hi> in an unſettled Nation, <hi>new Commotions might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe;</hi> They rather deſired <hi>(which was alſo the King's deſire)</hi> that he might be carried into the <hi>Southern parts of</hi> England, and live in ſome of his <hi>Palaces</hi> near <hi>London,</hi> which they thought more convenient for treating of a Peace: So that <hi>in all the whole De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, they ſeemed to contend, not who ſhould have the King, but who ſhould not have him.</hi> Nevertheleſs, to caſt a ſlander upon both Nations; for certainly 'tis as wicked a thing to buy, as to ſell ſuch Merchandize; You, <hi>Sir,</hi> will have it, that <hi>the Scots ſold him,</hi> the <hi>Engliſh bought him;</hi> but WILFULNESS EVER WAS THE GREATEST BLINDNESS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reverend Sir,</hi> I ſhall for the preſent diſcharge you and my ſelf from further trouble. You think, I ſuppoſe, that you make me a very merciful Offer, That <hi>if I will repent, and do ſo no more,</hi> I may hope to live in Peace, and you will not further laſh me with any more ſuch Scourges, as I have been but now tortured with; but <hi>if I ſhall perſiſt,</hi> and appear incorrigible, you have more Rods in Piſs, and will pay me off. <hi>You have much more to ſay in the behalf of King</hi> Charles <hi>the Firſt,</hi> ['tis well if you have, for <hi>I am ſure 'tis very little that you have hitherto
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:97943:39"/>ſaid] and you aſſure me I ſhall have it;</hi> and reſolve, That <hi>as long as you can hold a Pen in your Hand, you will not drop his Cauſe.</hi> There's no Remedy then, but I muſt abide your Fury, for <hi>I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve never to ask Forgiveneſs, and promiſe to do ſo no more:</hi> But on the contrary, <hi>to write on,</hi> as I have leiſure, and you give me occaſion, <hi>in the defence of the Laws and Liberties of my Country.</hi> Upon which Subject <hi>I have much more to ſay,</hi> and if you will not be quiet, <hi>you ſhall have it; I love the Cauſe too well to drop it,</hi> and will wear my <hi>Steell Pen</hi> to the ſtumps in its defence. And,</p>
            <p>Now ſeeing we are eternally to differ in this Point, I deſire to ſettle two things with you, for the more orderly Proſecution of this dreadful War.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That we (as <hi>Duelliſts</hi> agree the length of their Weapons) may reſolve how often to trouble the World with our <hi>Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinencies;</hi> I think once, or if you will have it ſo, twice (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>there are</hi> TWO MADDING-DAYS) in a Year, may ſuffice.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That after you have <hi>fairly anſwer'd</hi> this and my former <hi>Letter,</hi> by <hi>falſifying</hi> (which as a <hi>Preliminary</hi> I ſhall expect from you) the many particular Inſtances I have brought to ſhew that <hi>your admired Prince was a Tyrant;</hi> or elſe <hi>to prove</hi> that they are not <hi>Acts</hi> or <hi>Evidences of Tyranny,</hi> you would then (in the further Proſecution of that <hi>Defence</hi> which you have undertaken, and indeed of <hi>Criminating</hi> one of <hi>the greateſt and beſt deſerving Parliaments</hi> that even <hi>England</hi> ſaw) lay aſide your looſe and general way of diſcourſing, and <hi>come to Particulars;</hi> when you ſhall ſo proceed, and are failed of a <hi>clear Anſwer,</hi> then and not till then, the day will be your own. For tho, throughout your whole Diſcourſe, which I have been examining, <hi>you Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize the Lords and Commons, and fly in the Face of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with the King's gracious MESSAGES, SAYINGS,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s may,</hi> upon better grounds, <hi>ſum up the humble, condeſcending, convincing PETITIONS, MESSAGES, DECLARATIONS,</hi> &amp;c. of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and daſh them all into your Face, than you can thoſe <hi>Meſſages</hi> and <hi>Sayings</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> into the Faces of all who declare that he was <hi>a proud</hi> Nimrod, <hi>a hardened</hi> Pharaoh; in plain Engliſh, A MERCILESS TYRANT.</p>
            <p>Laſtly; To encourage you to further Converſation with me; the ſome Men are ſo impudent as to ſay that it is not Day when the Sun it ſelf doth ſhire, you ſhall ſee that <hi>I am not reſolved
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:97943:39"/>againſt Conviction;</hi> but that <hi>being under the Command of good Manners.</hi> I reſt not ſatisfied in the <hi>Confeſſion</hi> which I made in the beginning of this <hi>Letter,</hi> of <hi>an Error</hi> committed in my former, in relation to the <hi>Noble Lord Conway,</hi> ſometime <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary</hi> of <hi>State</hi> to <hi>King Charles</hi> the Firſt, but ſhall more fully do it in this place.</p>
            <p>Being miſguided by the <hi>Printer's Miſtake</hi> in <hi>Ruſhworth</hi>'s firſt <hi>Collections,</hi> from whence I took it, I was led to ſay in my laſt Year's Letter, <hi>pag.</hi> 7. <hi>That the Lord</hi> Conway <hi>ſaid in Parliament that he never hated Popery;</hi> whereas <hi>his words were, that he ever hared it:</hi> and I have now certain ground to ſay, that thoſe words were not only conſonant to <hi>his Speech</hi> then made in <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> but agreeable to the conſtant Tenour of his whole Life, even unto the laſt Period. His <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Mother</hi> lived and died <hi>pious Proteſtants;</hi> ſuch was his <hi>Religious Lady,</hi> and ſuch are his <hi>Grand-Children</hi> at this day.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Lord Conway</hi> was <hi>Knighted</hi> at the taking of <hi>Cadiz</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> in the time of <hi>Queen Elizabeth;</hi> he was afterwards for many Years <hi>Governour</hi> of the <hi>Brill</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> where he and his Family lived as became <hi>zealous Proteſtants,</hi> and greatly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved and eſteemed by the <hi>Proteſtant Magiſtrates</hi> and <hi>Miniſters</hi> of that Town.</p>
            <p>He was greatly favoured by <hi>the never to be forgotten</hi> MOST PIOUS PRINCE <hi>HENRY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the <hi>Brill</hi> and other <hi>Cautionary Towns</hi> were deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to the <hi>Dutch;</hi> upon his return into <hi>England,</hi> he was imployed to <hi>Jerſey</hi> to compoſe ſome Differences there, which he performed to ſo much Satisfaction, that <hi>the good Proteſtants</hi> of that Place always mentioned him with Honour.</p>
            <p>He was then ſent <hi>Ambaſſador</hi> to <hi>Germany</hi> in behalf of the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen</hi> of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and was very acceptable to thoſe UNHAPPILY DESERTED <hi>Proteſtant Princes.</hi> Upon his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to <hi>England</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh-Match</hi> was warmly preſs'd; againſt which he ſpake with ſo much Reaſon and Courage, that the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Buckingham</hi> (who for particular ends, reſolved to ruin that Project) introduced him as a proper Inſtrument for that purpoſe, to be <hi>Principal Secretary of State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In that Station he refuſed many great Gifts tendred to him by particular Perſons, and 10000 <hi>l. Sterling</hi> offer'd and preſs'd upon him by the <hi>Spaniſh Ambaſſador.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:97943:40"/>
            <p>In the beginning of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. Reign, at the opening of one of thoſe <hi>Parliaments,</hi> and according to the Cuſtom then, the <hi>Holy Communion</hi> being to be received by both Houſes of <hi>Parliament, by the Contrivance of ſome</hi> LAUDEANS, the SACRAMENT was offered to the <hi>Lords</hi> in <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh's <hi>Chappel,</hi> NOT IN BREAD, BUT IN WAFERS: This <hi>Lord Conway</hi> was one of the <hi>Lords</hi> who refuſed the <hi>Wafers,</hi> and cauſed them to be taken away, and Bread to be brought.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">He that would not make the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to <hi>Rome,</hi> was to be nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Secretary,</hi> nor <hi>Miniſter</hi> of <hi>State</hi> to King <hi>Charles</hi> I.</note> Not long after K. <hi>Charles</hi> I. <hi>ſent for the Seals of the Secretary's Office from him;</hi> which (as the <hi>Lord</hi> imployed in that Meſſage would often ſay) the <hi>Lord Conway</hi> delivered with an admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Generoſity, becoming indeed one that in that Miniſtry of State, had ſerved the Publick with extraordinary Ability and Integrity; had performed many noble Offices to parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Perſons, without Injury to any, and left that Place and ſome others of great Profit, without one Farthing advantage to the State of his Family.</p>
            <p>When he was upon his <hi>Death-Bed,</hi> a <hi>Lady</hi> of great Wit, who was turned <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and was the Widow of a near Relation of his Lordſhip, very ſubtilly and earneſtly preſs'd upon him concerning his <hi>Religion;</hi> whereupon he ſtrengthened himſelf, and made full Profeſſion of his firm Stedfaſtneſs in the <hi>Reformed Proteſtant Religion,</hi> caus'd the Servants to convey this <hi>Lady</hi> out of his Houſe, and commanded them not to ſuffer any of that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion to come to him.</p>
            <p>And now, <hi>Doctor,</hi> I aſſure you at parting, That as faſt as you ſhall convince me of any <hi>Error</hi> or <hi>Miſtake,</hi> committed in my Scriblings about <hi>your Martyr;</hi> I ſhall as openly and frankly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract it, as I have now done this, which relates to my <hi>Lord Conway.</hi> Might I be made ſo happy as to find a ſutable return from you; and that you would give a free and impartial Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to the uſe of your own Reaſon, I would yet hope, that we might mutually conclude, as I now do,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Friend in and for the Truth, <hi>Edmund Ludlow.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> 
                  <date>Jan. 30, 1691/2.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="index">
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:97943:40"/>
            <head>A Table of ſome remarkable Things in this Book.</head>
            <list>
               <item>KIng <hi>Charles I.</hi> favouring Popery, and diſpenſing with the Laws, <hi>&amp;c. Page 3</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His Biſhops cheriſhed Popery, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenanced conformable Orthodox Miniſters. <hi>Page 3</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Montague</hi> one of his Chaplains, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to reconcile <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> made a Biſhop. <hi>Page 4</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The King's lending Ships to the French to deſtroy the Proteſtants of <hi>Rochel. Page 4</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ship-Money, Loan, Coat and Conduct-Money required, and the Refuſers im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned and impreſs'd to ſerve at Sea. <hi>Page 4</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Archbiſhop <hi>Abbot</hi> ſuſpended and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined, By <hi>Williams</hi> diſgraced and impriſoned. <hi>Page 5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Randolph Crew</hi> Lord Chief Juſtice diſplas'd. <hi>Page 5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Tonnage and Poundage levied againſt Law. <hi>Page 5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Earl of <hi>Briſtol</hi> confined. <hi>Page 6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Earl of <hi>Arundel</hi> impriſon'd. <hi>Page 6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> protected againſt the Parliament. <hi>Page 6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Members of Parliament impriſon'd. <hi>Page 6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>John Elliot</hi>'s Death in the Tower. <hi>Page 7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The King's threatning Speeches in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. <hi>Page 7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His Speech at the Meeting of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, <hi>Nov. 1640. Page 11</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Biſhops obtruded upon <hi>Scotland</hi> againſt their Laws. <hi>Page 12</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Laud</hi> framed a Common-Prayer for <hi>Scotland,</hi> and ſent it to be approved by the Pope. <hi>Page 12</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Scots proteſt againſt it. <hi>Page 13</hi>
               </item>
               <item>King <hi>James I.</hi> took the Scotiſh Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in the Year <hi>1580. Page 13</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Scots renewed that Covenant in the Year <hi>1638. Page 13, 14</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Scots require to have the Liturgy aboliſhed, and to have a National Synod. <hi>Page 14</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Synod called and diſſolved by the King; the Scots proteſt againſt the Diſſolution, and continue it. <hi>Page 14</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The King reſolves upon a War againſt <hi>Scotland. Page 14</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That War called <hi>Bellum Epiſcopale. Page 15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Scots raiſe an Army. <hi>Page 15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Pacification concluded, the King ſoon after burns it by the Hangman's hands. <hi>Page 15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Scotiſh Commiſſioners ſent to the King, impriſoned. <hi>Page 16</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Parliament called in <hi>April 1640,</hi> and diſſolved. <hi>Page 16</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Members impriſoned. <hi>Page 17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Clergy and Bapiſts contribute to a ſecond War againſt <hi>Scotland. Page 17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Nicholas Rainton,</hi> Sir <hi>Stephen Soame,</hi> and other eminent Citizens. impriſon'd for refuſing a Loan. <hi>Page 17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Scots poſſeſs themſelves of <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle</hi> and <hi>Durham. Page 17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Lords at <hi>York</hi> petition for a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. <hi>Page 18</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ceſſation of Arms with the Scots. <hi>Page 18</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Star-Chamber and High-Commiſſion-Courts ſuppreſs'd by Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. <hi>Page 21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Poll-money granted. <hi>Page 21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Leighton</hi>'s Cenſure in the Star-Chamber. <hi>Page 22</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi>'s, Dr. <hi>Baſtwick</hi>'s and. Mr. <hi>Burton</hi>'s Cenſures and horrid Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions by Archbiſhop <hi>Laud. Page 24, 25</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Thoſe Sentences declared illegal in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. <hi>Page 27</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ship-Money illegal. <hi>Page 27</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lord Keeper <hi>Finch</hi> impeach'd of High-Treaſon about Ship-Money, and flies. <hi>Page 28</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The many Exorbitances and Oppreſſions of the Biſhops. <hi>Page 28</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Twelve of them impeach'd of Treaſon,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:97943:41"/>and all remov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> from the Lords Houſe. <hi>Page 29</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi> impeach'd and att<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inted of Treaſon. <hi>Page 30</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Bills for Triennial Parliaments, and for continuing the preſent Parliament, paſſed. <hi>Page 31</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Conſpiracy to bring the Army againſt the Parliament diſcovered. <hi>Page 32</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The King had a Million and half of Money in the firſt Year of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>1640. Page 35</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Remonſtrance of the State of the Kingdom, <hi>Dec. 1641. Page 35</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Tumults and Riots in <hi>1641. Page 37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Account of the occaſion of thoſe Tumults. <hi>Page 41</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The King accuſes the Lord <hi>Mandeville</hi> and five Members of Treaſon. <hi>Page 37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>He goes to the Houſe of Commons with an armed Force, and demands the five Members. <hi>Page 37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Commons demand a Guard. <hi>Page 38</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Caſe of the five Members diſcuſſed. <hi>Page 38</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The King leaves <hi>White-hall. Page 42</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Parliament petitions him at <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balds</hi> to return. <hi>Page 42</hi>
               </item>
               <item>They ſend a Declaration to him to <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>market,</hi> praying his return, and the putting the Militia into ſafe hands. <hi>Page 43</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His Anſwer about the Militia. <hi>Page 46</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His ſending to the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> for Aid againſt the Parliament. <hi>Page 47</hi>
               </item>
               <item>He invited the Scots againſt them. <hi>Page 47</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Queen buys Arms in <hi>Holland. Page 47</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Names of the Peers recommended by the Parliament to be entruſted with the Militia. <hi>Page 47</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Lords and Commons petition about the Militia. <hi>Page 48</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Their Ordinance for ordering the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia. <hi>Page 48</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Proceedings of the Parliament with King <hi>Richard</hi> the Second. <hi>Page 49</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Lords and Commons petition the King at <hi>York</hi> to return. <hi>Page 50</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The King ſummons the Gentry to <hi>York,</hi> and requires them to raiſe him a Guard. <hi>Page 50</hi>
               </item>
               <item>They petition him to return to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. <hi>Page 50</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Petition of many thouſand Freeholders of <hi>Yorkſhire. Page 50</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The King requires the Gentlemen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of <hi>Yorkſhire</hi> to attend him in Arms. <hi>Page 51</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Lords and Commons vote, that the King Intends to raiſe War, and that it is a Breach of his Truſt, and that ſuch as aſſiſt him in that War are Traitors. <hi>Page 52</hi>
               </item>
               <item>They vote the raiſing an Army to be commanded by the Earl of <hi>Eſſex. Page 52</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Their Petition to the King to return. <hi>Page 52</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The King's Speech at the head of his Army. <hi>Page 54</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Petition of the Parliament ſent by the Earl of <hi>Eſſex. Page 56</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Preparations made by the King for War. <hi>Page 58</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Opinion of above ſixty <hi>Eſſex</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Parliament War. <hi>Page 59</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>Uxbridg</hi>-Treaty. <hi>Page 61</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Heads of Letters between the King, Queen and Marqueſs of <hi>Ormond,</hi> about the <hi>Uxbridg</hi>-Treaty, and for procuring a Peace with the Iriſh Rebels to bring them againſt the Parliament. <hi>Page 63</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The vulgar Error of the Scots ſelling the King refuted. <hi>Page 67</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Vindication of the Lord <hi>Conway. Page 69</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:97943:41"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97943:42"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97943:42"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:97943:43"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:97943:43"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:97943:44"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:97943:44"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:97943:45"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:97943:45"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:97943:46"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:97943:46"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:97943:47"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:97943:47"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:97943:48"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:97943:48"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:97943:49"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:97943:49"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:97943:50"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:97943:50"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:97943:51"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:97943:51"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:97943:52"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:97943:52"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:97943:53"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:97943:53"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:97943:54"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:97943:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
